<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<link rel="self" href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/" />
	<id>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/</id>
	<title>Ian Bebbington</title>
	<rights>2018</rights>
	<updated>2018-01-29T15:08:22Z</updated>
	<logo>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/y3mVYjKPwLNM4SpxZ-xLtIcMigGcxEzKTdUxFym5tI2hMna1NOz6e5axIvMYoGFlV1ftnmELd2YUX4QowbgtJ_iJkEHUEXpngrQ47dG5_hm88hO2ZJM1mRZLWwhDoB0KfKuu6WFFqmWoKb_2f18gkAqJQ20PkRodrAj4PzkSSgO9A4%253Fwidth=660&amp;height=371&amp;cropmode=none</logo>
	<subtitle>IObservable&lt;Opinion&gt;</subtitle>
	<entry>
		<link href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/ReactiveReadModels" />
		<id>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/ReactiveReadModels</id>
		<title>Reactive ReadModels</title>
		<updated>2015-11-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<content>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;If you're starting out with &lt;a href="http://docs.geteventstore.com/introduction/event-sourcing-basics/" title="Event Sourcing Basics at GetEventStore"&gt;Event Sourcing&lt;/a&gt; you're probably looking for the ability to project events into &lt;a href="http://cqrs.nu/tutorial/cs/03-read-models" title="CQRS tutorial - Read Models"&gt;read models&lt;/a&gt; that can be used by the views in your application. Today I'd like to share a neat little mechanism I've established for building read model in C# by employing a strongly typed yet functional approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting with infrastructure, you probably have some form event distribution mechanism, normally a pub/sub style bus. From this bus you need to be able to selectively subscribe to all the events you need to collate the information required by your read model. Furthermore, you will often need to initialize the read model with information from a persistent store - often this is a persistent store of the read model itself but this isn't necessarily the case. Lastly, your application must be able to request a specific read model and receive notifications when the read model changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To illustrate how this might be achieved, I have written a &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs/Blog.ReactiveReadModels" title="ReactiveReadModels repository on Github"&gt;small sample project&lt;/a&gt; following the traditional Account/Order model that features the following components:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/posts/ReactiveReadModels-SampleComponents.png" alt="Sample Components" class="img-responsive" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; margin-top: 4px; margin-bottom: 4px"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this system, the application is able to request a stream of read models from a repository. The repository will retrieve initial read model state from a persistence service and then subscribe to events from an event bus to continually update and publish the read model. Only read models the application needs should be published and only events the read model requires should be processed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By leveraging Rx we're able to implement a stub of the repository very easily as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;public class Repository
{
    private readonly Service.IAccountService _accountService;
    private readonly IEventAggregator _bus;

    public Repository(Service.IAccountService accountService, IEventAggregator bus)
    {
        _accountService = accountService;
        _bus = bus;
    }

    public IObservable&amp;lt;ReadModel&amp;gt; For(Guid id)
    {
        if (id == null) throw new ArgumentNullException("id");

        return Observable.Create&amp;lt;ReadModel&amp;gt;(
            async observer =&amp;gt;
            {
                Service.AccountInfo accountInfo = await _accountService.GetAccountInfoAsync(id);

                ReadModel readModel = accountInfo.ToReadModel();

                // Subscribe to events and apply to read model

                return Observable.StartWith(readModel).Subscribe(observer);
            }
        );
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This code is written such that, when an observer &lt;em&gt;subscribes&lt;/em&gt; to the &lt;code&gt;IObservable&amp;lt;ReadModel&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; returned from the &lt;code&gt;For&lt;/code&gt; method, an asynchronous request will be made to the &lt;code&gt;IAccountService&lt;/code&gt; for the initial state of the read model, a &lt;code&gt;ReadModel&lt;/code&gt; instance will be constructed from the information returned by the  service and finally the &lt;code&gt;ReadModel&lt;/code&gt; will be emitted to the subscriber. Note that the observable is deliberately left incomplete to indicate the further &lt;code&gt;ReadModel&lt;/code&gt; instances might be emitted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we have the current read model, we need to subscribe to events from the event bus that represent changes pertinent to the read model and, when received, modify and emit the read model so that the subscriber is always up to date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do this, we might think to write something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;public IObservable&amp;lt;ReadModel&amp;gt; For(Guid id)
{
    if (id == null) throw new ArgumentNullException("id");

    return Observable.Create&amp;lt;ReadModel&amp;gt;(
        async observer =&amp;gt;
        {
            Service.AccountInfo accountInfo = await _accountService.GetAccountInfoAsync(id);

            ReadModel readModel = accountInfo.ToReadModel();

            return new CompositeDisposable(
                _bus.GetEvent&amp;lt;Event.AccountNameChanged&amp;gt;().Where(@@event =&amp;gt; id.Equals(@@event.AccountId)).Select(@@event =&amp;gt; readModel.WithAccountName(@@event.AccountName)).Subscribe(observer),
                _bus.GetEvent&amp;lt;Event.AddBillingAddress&amp;gt;().Where(@@event =&amp;gt; id.Equals(@@event.AccountId)).Select(@@event =&amp;gt; readModel.WithBillingAddress(new Address(@@event.AddressName))).Subscribe(observer),
                _bus.GetEvent&amp;lt;Event.RemoveBillingAddress&amp;gt;().Where(@@event =&amp;gt; id.Equals(@@event.AccountId)).Select(@@event =&amp;gt; readModel.WithoutBillingAddress(@@event.AddressName)).Subscribe(observer),
                _bus.GetEvent&amp;lt;Event.OrderInvoiced&amp;gt;().Where(@@event =&amp;gt; id.Equals(@@event.AccountId)).Select(@@event =&amp;gt; readModel.WithCurrentOrder(new Order(@@event.OrderId))).Subscribe(observer),
                _bus.GetEvent&amp;lt;Event.OrderDispatched&amp;gt;().Where(@@event =&amp;gt; id.Equals(@@event.AccountId)).Select(@@event =&amp;gt; readModel.WithCompletedOrder(@@event.OrderId)).Subscribe(observer)
            );
        }
    );
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this code looks sensible, we'll very quickly run into problems with it. Firstly and primarily each subscription is only ever modifying the initial &lt;code&gt;readModel&lt;/code&gt; instance meaning changes are not cumulative. Secondly, if we somehow overcame the initial issue, because we're maintaining a series of subscriptions here, changes are not thread safe nor deterministic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No, what we need is a way of writing the effect of these changes into a common read model instance, aggregating those changes across multiple events and emitting the new read model each time it is updated. Fortunately, Rx has &lt;strong&gt;exactly&lt;/strong&gt; the operator we need for this: &lt;code&gt;IObservable&amp;lt;TAccumulate&amp;gt; Scan&amp;lt;TSource, TAccumulate&amp;gt;(this IObservable&amp;lt;TSource&amp;gt; source, TAccumulate seed, Func&amp;lt;TAccumulate, TSource, TAccumulate&amp;gt; accumulator)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This operator takes an initial &lt;code&gt;TAccumulate&lt;/code&gt; seed and applies each item emitted from the &lt;code&gt;IObservable&amp;lt;TSource&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; source to the accumulator by invoking a function that takes the current accumulator value and the emitted item and returning a new accumulator value. Each of these new accumulator values are then emitted as an &lt;code&gt;IObservable&amp;lt;TAccumulate&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; instances to the subscriber.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Great, so it's pretty obvious here that our accumulator should be our read model, but how do we subscribe to all the different message types and apply a different modifications to the read model for each type of  message received when the &lt;code&gt;Scan&lt;/code&gt; function only allows for a single &lt;code&gt;TSource&lt;/code&gt; type. We need to somehow homogenise the source stream to a single type. Often this is done with inheritance but, as there's no common base type for each of these messages, we'd have to write something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;public IObservable&amp;lt;ReadModel&amp;gt; For(Guid id)
{
    if (id == null) throw new ArgumentNullException("id");

    return Observable.Create&amp;lt;ReadModel&amp;gt;(
        async observer =&amp;gt;
        {
            Service.AccountInfo accountInfo = await _accountService.GetAccountInfoAsync(id);

            ReadModel readModel = accountInfo.ToReadModel();

            IObservable&amp;lt;object&amp;gt; events = Observable.Merge(
                _bus.GetEvent&amp;lt;Event.AccountNameChanged&amp;gt;().Where(@@event =&amp;gt; id.Equals(@@event.AccountId)).Cast&amp;lt;object&amp;gt;(),
                _bus.GetEvent&amp;lt;Event.AddBillingAddress&amp;gt;().Where(@@event =&amp;gt; id.Equals(@@event.AccountId)).Cast&amp;lt;object&amp;gt;(),
                _bus.GetEvent&amp;lt;Event.RemoveBillingAddress&amp;gt;().Where(@@event =&amp;gt; id.Equals(@@event.AccountId)).Cast&amp;lt;object&amp;gt;(),
                _bus.GetEvent&amp;lt;Event.OrderInvoiced&amp;gt;().Where(@@event =&amp;gt; id.Equals(@@event.AccountId)).Cast&amp;lt;object&amp;gt;(),
                _bus.GetEvent&amp;lt;Event.OrderDispatched&amp;gt;().Where(@@event =&amp;gt; id.Equals(@@event.AccountId)).Cast&amp;lt;object&amp;gt;()
            );

            return events.Scan(readModel,
                (readModel, @@event) =&amp;gt;
                {
                    if (@@event is Event.AccountNameChanged)
                    {
                        return readModel.WithAccountName(((Event.AccountNameChanged)@@event).AccountName);
                    }
                    else if (@@event is Event.AddBillingAddress)
                    {
                        ...
                    }
                    ...
                    else
                    {
                        throw new ArgumentException("Unknown message type");
                    }
                }
            );
        }
    );
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... which is not type safe, has very little compile time checking, requires a fall-through exception and, quite frankly, is horrible. I'm sure with Rx we can do something better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, lets look at this from a functional perspective. The action we want to perform when receiving each type of event can be considered to be a function in the form of &lt;code&gt;Func&amp;lt;TReadModel, TEvent, TReadModel&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;. This is very similar to the third parameter of the &lt;code&gt;Observable.Scan&lt;/code&gt; function with the problem being that we have multiple types of &lt;code&gt;TEvent&lt;/code&gt;. If only there was a way to produce a generic function that would operate correctly across all the event types.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, by leaning on a concept from functional languages, this might be possible. &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Partial_application" title="Partial Application definition from wikipedia"&gt;Partial application&lt;/a&gt; has been available in C# - via &lt;a href="http://csharpindepth.com/Articles/Chapter5/Closures.aspx" title="C# in Depth - The Beauty Of Closures"&gt;closures&lt;/a&gt; - since lambdas were introduced and allows you to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;fix a number of arguments to a function, producing another function of smaller arity. Given a function f:(X * Y * Z) -&amp;gt; N , we might fix (or 'bind') the first argument, producing a function of type (f){partial}:(Y * Z) -&amp;gt; N . Evaluation of this function might be represented as f{partial}(2, 3). Note that the result of partial function application in this case is a function that takes two arguments&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So is there some way we can leverage this to remove the &lt;code&gt;TEvent&lt;/code&gt; argument from the function? Absolutely, by making the observable emit a &lt;em&gt;stream of partial functions&lt;/em&gt; in the form &lt;code&gt;Func&amp;lt;ReadModel,ReadModel&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; which can then be applied to the read model as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;public IObservable&amp;lt;ReadModel&amp;gt; For(Guid id)
{
    if (id == null) throw new ArgumentNullException("id");

    return Observable.Create&amp;lt;ReadModel&amp;gt;(
        async observer =&amp;gt;
        {
            Service.AccountInfo accountInfo = await _accountService.GetAccountInfoAsync(id);

            IObservable&amp;lt;Func&amp;lt;ReadModel, ReadModel&amp;gt;&amp;gt; mutators = Observable.Merge(
                _bus.GetEvent&amp;lt;Event.AccountNameChanged&amp;gt;().Where(@@event =&amp;gt; id.Equals(@@event.AccountId)).Select(Functions.Apply),
                _bus.GetEvent&amp;lt;Event.AddBillingAddress&amp;gt;().Where(@@event =&amp;gt; id.Equals(@@event.AccountId)).Select(Functions.Apply),
                _bus.GetEvent&amp;lt;Event.RemoveBillingAddress&amp;gt;().Where(@@event =&amp;gt; id.Equals(@@event.AccountId)).Select(Functions.Apply),
                _bus.GetEvent&amp;lt;Event.OrderInvoiced&amp;gt;().Where(@@event =&amp;gt; id.Equals(@@event.AccountId)).Select(Functions.Apply),
                _bus.GetEvent&amp;lt;Event.OrderDispatched&amp;gt;().Where(@@event =&amp;gt; id.Equals(@@event.AccountId)).Select(Functions.Apply)
            );

            return mutators.Scan(accountInfo.ToReadModel(), (readModel, mutator) =&amp;gt; mutator(readModel)).Subscribe(observer);
        }
    );
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here the &lt;code&gt;Functions.Apply&lt;/code&gt; is an overloaded method for each of the event types. For example, the method for &lt;code&gt;Event.AccountNameChanged&lt;/code&gt; is implemented as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;public static Func&amp;lt;ReadModel, ReadModel&amp;gt; Apply(Event.AccountNameChanged @@event)
{
    return readModel =&amp;gt; readModel.WithAccountName(@@event.AccountName);
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This method takes the event to be processed as a parameter and returns a function in the form &lt;code&gt;Func&amp;lt;ReadModel,ReadModel&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; that closes over the parameter and calls the &lt;code&gt;WithAccountName&lt;/code&gt; extension method when executed. A similar pattern is followed for all the other event types.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we have projected and merged all the event streams into a single &lt;code&gt;IObservable&amp;lt;Func&amp;lt;ReadModel, ReadModel&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; we can use the scan function to iteratively apply each function to the cumulative read model instance and emit the result after each event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pretty neat huh!&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;If you're starting out with &lt;a href="http://docs.geteventstore.com/introduction/event-sourcing-basics/" title="Event Sourcing Basics at GetEventStore"&gt;Event Sourcing&lt;/a&gt; you're probably looking for the ability to project events into &lt;a href="http://cqrs.nu/tutorial/cs/03-read-models" title="CQRS tutorial - Read Models"&gt;read models&lt;/a&gt; that can be used by the views in your application. Today I'd like to share a neat little mechanism I've established for building read model in C# by employing a strongly typed yet functional approach.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<link href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/MonsterPi" />
		<link rel="enclosure" type="image" href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/y3mJgriVgVEFWAdldfy7Bj9MEJznwpJtJ4NFHotqnwZ0rWbC2h8ewxTr9MSxr6LCGyQBB-TvmYCV9j4YVZbu2EtVHagPnyc6O_LIZV2NqAiPfrfNkZ8P-XBV6SI0GiL7zx0iuOTniKjZ-Gq9_lN6SLkkIMHMx14EE3l2XuZQ1cTPfI%253Fwidth=967&amp;height=273&amp;cropmode=none" />
		<id>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/MonsterPi</id>
		<title>MonsterPi</title>
		<updated>2016-10-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<content>
                                        


&lt;h2&gt;Preface&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've long loved the idea of home automation. From X10 and LightwaveRF through to modern Bluetooth and Wifi connected devices, I have played with dozens of technologies in search of home automation nirvana. But recently I have watched with growing bewilderment at the incredible number of "cloud-connected" home automation devices being released and the eagerness with which they're snapped up by naive consumers hungry to control everything from the carefree comfort of their iPhone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You see, while you can buy a myriad of IoT devices off the shelf nowadays, they nearly all come with some form of "cloud-service" that is necessary in order for the device to work as sold. As the more wily of reader will no doubt be aware, this exposes your home network to innumerable &lt;a href="https://it.slashdot.org/story/16/10/03/1359200/source-code-for-iot-botnet-mirai-which-took-down-krebs-on-security-website-with-ddos-attack-released"&gt;security concerns&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://it.slashdot.org/story/16/08/08/1449221/hackers-make-the-first-ever-ransomware-for-smart-thermostats"&gt;potential abuses&lt;/a&gt; and an &lt;a href="https://tech.slashdot.org/story/16/01/14/1347243/nest-thermostat-bug-leaves-owners-without-heating"&gt;external point of failure&lt;/a&gt; that cannot be closed/fixed without sacrificing some or all of the functionality of the new fangled device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I understand the ostensible benefits of this approach (ease of setup, remote use without manually opening firewall ports, centralised patching and upgrading, etc), sacrificing control of (potentially hazardous or invasive) devices within my home is not a value proposition I am comfortable with. I would very much like to see a new (or is that old?) breed of device that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;does not require an internet connection to operate with all features intact,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;with which the owner can proactively decide what control and data is available to servers outside of the home network and,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;which surface simple, open interfaces to the owner allowing them to completely control all aspects of the device.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, I'd like to drop the 'Inter' from IoT and expand the 'net' to become a 'Network of Things', or NoT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of the consumer market, I am undoubtedly swimming against the tide here. Fortunately with the rise of hobbyist devices such as Arduino and RaspberryPi, IoT technologies have been democratised to the extent that anyone with just the smallest ability with a soldering iron and faculty with an IDE can create such devices for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ladies and gentlemen, I present my first (finished) NoT device, the...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;MonsterPi&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Years ago, while setting up my (living room) home cinema, I came across the &lt;a href="http://www.adverts.ie/home-audio/monster-hts-1600-home-theatre-powercenter-5-outlet-with-stage-2-clean-power-purge-protector-uk-version/7055360"&gt;Monster Power HTS 1600&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href="https://www.scan.co.uk/"&gt;Scan's website&lt;/a&gt;. It seems Monster Products were end-of-lining their power products in the UK (the above link was literally the only one I could find that still works!) and Scan were selling them off at £30 a piece. It was exactly what I was looking for at the time and, not being one to pass up a bargain, I bought two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://0oiczq.dm2302.livefilestore.com/y3mwcGE45bQwRPaCXRNuB9tGejIT6aSpahgDN02u9ag661uCa_ZmYbNnaKz2aW81rjG8BTgsUhtZ0aDQ8ioIsagbcFP6LtM-IgV_rcPoCs8UI4dZNegv8JembGIuIr7ETkwTZwOTEUjsAAbQHy0jCyAGNkGu3NJZLkXjnGwgzUMlTI?width=700&amp;amp;height=466&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="One of the few remaining pictures online of the Monster Power HTS 1600 UK version"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both devices found homes powering and protected my front room and study AV equipment and, to this day, I am still very happy with them. However, I always felt that Monster had missed a trick with this product: the ability to individually and - ideally - remotely turn each of the sockets on the unit on and off as desired.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Microsoft announced that Windows IoT Core would run on a RaspberryPi the learning curve ahead of making this happen evaporated and I knew it was something I wanted to do. Unfortunately both Monster Power devices were in full time use and I didn't want to potentially sacrifice one on a project that might not work and could consign the device to the scrap yard. Given that you couldn't purchase the UK version of these devices any more and that, when they occasionally appeared on eBay, they'd invariably be priced at £100+ the project was indefinitely parked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, a couple of months ago, a 'used' one appeared on eBay without a reserve and with bidding at thirty odd quid having just a few hours to go. I placed a bid without really hoping it would be successful and, to my surprise, ended up winning the auction for £40'ish including delivery. When it arrived I was delighted to find that it seemed to be brand new and unused (twisty wire on all the cables, supplementary cables still in sealed bags, etc). Plugging it in proved that everything worked as it should so everything was in place to build the MonsterPi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Software&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While waiting for the time and space required to start hacking up the hardware, I took a look into what was required to write a headless UWP app, self-hosting a HTTP REST endpoint that could be deployed to the RaspberryPi and set values on the GPIO pins necessary to control the &lt;a href="http://www.waveshare.com/rpi-relay-board.htm"&gt;Waveshare RaspberryPi Relay Board&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It didn't take long to find &lt;a href="https://github.com/tomkuijsten/restup"&gt;Restup&lt;/a&gt;, a beautifully simple if somewhat minimal 'Webserver for Universal Windows Apps'. The github repository provided ample samples for writing various types of 'controller' and in less than an hour, I had a working solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the Waveshare relay board just required GPIO pins to be set in order to control the relay (low to close, high to open) this was achieved very simply using the classes available in the &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/library/windows/apps/windows.devices.gpio.aspx"&gt;Windows.Devices.Gpio namespace&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deployment was taken care of by Visual Studio and configuration performed using the Windows IoT Core Device Portal. The Device Portal allows you to configure deployed apps to run at start up thereby creating a "service-like" experience for headless apps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://0oidzq.dm2302.livefilestore.com/y3myuJMpQJ0iee-DzmucnuUu2r69IZ2c_KNukHEjoPB0--qRcndLbk0EwUszv8MLYj207fNIWEelQn4TYtW40FVp_y77RW-aTL3AcxQWcowLMB_zsw9jYdH0SwepJ0l6_XC0z9erqkYt4k4TaUBdnqxPYUlSf786xKVx1zwTC4jEsg?width=1363&amp;amp;height=905&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Using the device portal to set Start-up apps"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Full source code is available on my &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs/MonsterPi"&gt;Github account&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Hardware&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hardware side of things proved to be both easier and more tricky than I expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially I thought fitting the Pi was going to be child's-play when, upon opening the Monster Power chasis I found that the configuration of sockets providing isolation for RJ11 and RJ45 devices (phone and ethernet respectively) matched the layout of the ethernet and USB connectors of the Pi almost perfectly. Furthermore, these sockets were mounted on an easily removable daughter-board providing an obvious way to fix the pi in place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://nhtcwg.dm2302.livefilestore.com/y3mKq_74GixCoND7XvyavcDTjnNPdW2xd58RqEk1KZtO4f8nqKhcwyGbMRJqYhtuIHOmJCrJo6O-pltKB1pW0DFAHNy2oi6CNuyOle6TUxrjb4UzQo5_uDIPhNAP1uF8llVVLds4J6Bcp5b2s0GRI_T1uLx__qES0eUimFSxaTWddk?width=1024&amp;amp;height=576&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="The sockets on the RaspberryPi aligned almost perfectly with the RJ11 isolator sockets"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While alignment wasn't perfect, filing the holes in the chasis to provide access to all ports would be easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Complexity came when I realised that, although the Monster Power included a micro-controller driven digital display, it was unlikely that the DC subsystem in place to power this would be adequate for the RaspberryPi. So here I had to get creative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bought a small &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/B01H0OH3PI/ref=oh_aui_detailpage_o02_s01?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1"&gt;12v 80W switching power supply&lt;/a&gt; which would fit down one side of the Moster Power chasis and wired it to the 240v input of using the conveniently provided ring terminals. I used a &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/3DPrintingWithTheCelRobox"&gt;custom printed bracket&lt;/a&gt; to secure the PSU in place while providing a platform to mount the &lt;a href="http://www.waveshare.com/rpi-relay-board.htm"&gt;Waveshare RaspberryPi Relay Board&lt;/a&gt; above, in close proximity to the sockets I wanted to control with the relays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The live wire to the three sockets to be controlled by relays were daisy-chained together so one side of this wire was cut from each socket and connected to the normally-closed output of the relay (extending where necessary using crimp connectors).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://zphbnq.dm2302.livefilestore.com/y3mBGmj_-221eHr5ChhkWQfyEOjewU-6JEKOKlqHR-UqR0eMZdf2xPtI5qfP_K1rjguEplhOWObkMJ2fiGI4T4WSQOGh8GfodMLL2lPWD5QZFnBFPYwPUID3FZgVTYndwwL5jDybtRBC6JE_hhcTokWGrmppuLoHccNLsmFZyUsAvM?width=576&amp;amp;height=1024&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="12v switching PSU with relay board mounted in custom bracket"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the perspective in the picture makes it look like it hangs over the edge of the chasis, it does actually fit. It's tight, but it fits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used a &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/B01CUA5Q74/ref=oh_aui_detailpage_o02_s00?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1"&gt;12V To 5V 3A 15W Power Converter Regulator with Micro USB Cable&lt;/a&gt; to power the RaspberryPi and - given I now had plenty of power to spare, decided to also fit the &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Step-Down-Step-down-Power-Module/dp/B00ENE55SQ/ref=pd_nav_hcs_bia_t_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1&amp;amp;refRID=J91844QA901NNMPP9XHJ"&gt;4-port USB power module&lt;/a&gt; I had bought, but not used, for our &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/WotNoBlogPosts"&gt;travels earlier in the year&lt;/a&gt;. Again, this aligned almost perfectly in the remaining holes in the Monster Power chasis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://nhtcwg.dm2302.livefilestore.com/y3mKq_74GixCoND7XvyavcDTjnNPdW2xd58RqEk1KZtO4f8nqKhcwyGbMRJqYhtuIHOmJCrJo6O-pltKB1pW0DFAHNy2oi6CNuyOle6TUxrjb4UzQo5_uDIPhNAP1uF8llVVLds4J6Bcp5b2s0GRI_T1uLx__qES0eUimFSxaTWddk?width=1024&amp;amp;height=576&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="The sockets on the USB power module aligned almost perfectly with the RJ11 isolator sockets"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both these were mounted - upside down - on a custom printed bracket using the screw holes for the original daughter board to secure it in place. Terminal connectors were used to provide connection to the power supply just in case I needed to remove the components at a later date for some reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://zphcnq.dm2302.livefilestore.com/y3mMyQU1JCq5r9g0pnmuLGrrVm1-_D8Bq9UVm5uZgUD2lx9t3LVnjEIgWzqzwKeKbju29iHfBntmTX0FPZFKzWK6RAnFwWw-rxMfWyslJf52FN4XkFlglfGHc97-z24asPfR-NLEAd8nEE9e8X9V-tEP_wen7kF0zsAchvQJYwOjJk?width=576&amp;amp;height=1024&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Mounting the RaspberryPi and USB power module on a custom bracket"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, boards were fixed in place and a ribbon cable connected between the GPIO socket on the RaspberryPi and the relay board to allow control of the relays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://nhtewg.dm2302.livefilestore.com/y3mYTQzOsTukjrHcb69XX-50V18rcvHJUP4R8u6hmsgR1yAm2DCpFzoK9UdUNyfxseH59qtuRbVeIVVX9AM1h8lde7IbZDOPRYz0le7cac0bFkoC4pzsyjVKNO3QapjDdlCK-awMaL_NOhYEw6rW4_7lMTobDNRqGrK17yE1SmeRHA?width=1024&amp;amp;height=576&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Brackets in place and RaspberryPi fitted"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a thorough check to make sure there were no shorts on any of the connections and that I had connected polarity correctly, I plugged it in and turned it on....&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Testing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... and everything worked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The RaspberryPi booted but didn't switch the sockets on as - I think - not having a network connection meant it couldn't get an IP address which meant the software hadn't enabled to relays due to being configured to fail safe (leave the sockets off). The power indicator on the USB power module suggested it was working fine too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next I relocated to another room where a network connection was available. I plugged it in, turned it on and saw the network connection LED's start blinking. After 15-20 seconds or so while the RaspberryPi booted, the relays tickets on and I was able to hit the REST endpoint from &lt;a href="https://www.getpostman.com/"&gt;Postman&lt;/a&gt;. I'd even managed to get the names of the sockets on the rest service to match the sockets the relays were controlling, although I admit this was more luck than judgement (I had completely expected to have to re-configure the software to match after the hardware was complete).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I plugged in a small table lamp and recorded this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src="https://onedrive.live.com/embed?cid=03DF8A28BD9D0BC9&amp;amp;resid=3DF8A28BD9D0BC9%21266322&amp;amp;authkey=AI5IzCXupiYl-CU" width="600px" height="340px" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" allowfullscreen=""&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boom! (Figuratively speaking of course... the MonsterPi didn't literally go boom... yet :0)&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;I've long loved the idea of home automation. From X10 and LightwaveRF through to modern Bluetooth and Wifi connected devices, I have played with dozens of technologies in search of home automation nirvana. But recently I have watched with growing bewilderment at the incredible number of "cloud-connected" home automation devices being released and the eagerness with which they're snapped up by naive consumers hungry to control everything from the carefree comfort of their iPhone.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<link href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/IContributedAndAllIGot" />
		<link rel="enclosure" type="image" href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/y3mNzf5Sylp6SOZbv6t2Q_atZh0reZJW7RYL9EgdZ4V4aZSaf_8Sqe8UPzCEaq7t3RKQn5GX1DvkSWdsolooyOHZj9Ma389uQChI7uhzICOmFTm8aZaRBYS4jS0K8g07vYNjEJofO_Io8VnpaqgTRsLJwSIEMEzg1P1TOt9dbXzm6s%253Fwidth=2465&amp;height=1039&amp;cropmode=none" />
		<id>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/IContributedAndAllIGot</id>
		<title>I contributed and all I got...</title>
		<updated>2016-11-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<content>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;A while back, I contributed my &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/UsingHyperlinkInMVVM"&gt;HyperlinkExtensions&lt;/a&gt; to the &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/UWPCommunityToolkitv1_1"&gt;UWP Community Toolkit&lt;/a&gt;. This morning postman brought me a very pleasant surprise:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://orvy1q.dm2302.livefilestore.com/y3mcg6h9OGMl0tKB0ohOeyyBSVI-CwtcQF9XPWLXHBQI1inTRaPd9_k1jeoOpTIga1ZVnezoWRp34VnQuSmMduXhLro6OeJ4Unrgxe3PVOAh2kA3Pae1SN3wmxv3sxPDJlD1uTFxMKkKMk2lRjxKWZE1Ktqvs7k-mr6mCjq0UdKLh8?width=574&amp;amp;height=660&amp;amp;cropmode=none" alt="T-shirt front"&gt;&lt;img src="https://orvx1q.dm2302.livefilestore.com/y3mzcdee8-cKnRVTO-rrLFoC5rQMdorNPkUwiu49xlSHN6OeisdbwOFTzvPTLZzInaP0JBQLgOu9bkX8eZZZa4SuKd2ruJI80mI38NbMcTftpRMmE9zFx6DwWNGSctfhS6F2HRlKQ7Ve60D8Y6G94bbLVuFJ5hp4E9mYWQTG0QhxVk?width=594&amp;amp;height=660&amp;amp;cropmode=none" alt="T-shirt back"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How cool is that?! Not too many open source projects provide such swag!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the &lt;a href="https://github.com/Microsoft/UWPCommunityToolkit"&gt;UWP Community Toolkit&lt;/a&gt; maintainers, keep up the good work!&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;A while back, I contributed my &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/UsingHyperlinkInMVVM"&gt;HyperlinkExtensions&lt;/a&gt; to the &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/UWPCommunityToolkitv1_1"&gt;UWP Community Toolkit&lt;/a&gt;. This morning postman brought me a very pleasant surprise:&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<link href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/ASentimentalAnalysisOfRedDwarf" />
		<id>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/ASentimentalAnalysisOfRedDwarf</id>
		<title>A sentiment(al) analysis of why Red Dwarf is no longer funny</title>
		<updated>2017-01-31T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<content>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I had a lot of fun playing with &lt;a href="http://jupyter.org/"&gt;Project Jupyter&lt;/a&gt;. For those that aren't aware of this project, it's an effort to provide a workspace for performing repeatable experimentation with data. In short it mixes markdown editing capabilities with a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Read%E2%80%93eval%E2%80%93print_loop"&gt;REPL&lt;/a&gt; environment for a large number of languages. From the website:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"a web application that allows you to create and share documents that contain live code, equations, visualizations and explanatory text. Uses include: data cleaning and transformation, numerical simulation, statistical modeling, machine learning and much more"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After having my interest tweaked by the &lt;a href="https://try.jupyter.org/"&gt;browser version&lt;/a&gt; I bit the bullet and spent ages downloading and installing the &lt;a href="http://jupyter.org/install.html"&gt;full version&lt;/a&gt; to a virtual machine. It's a Python based web-app so requires quite a bit of setup and unfortunately I found the documentation to be a bit sparse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so it was that while trying to work out how to install the &lt;a href="https://github.com/fsprojects/IfSharp"&gt;FSharp module&lt;/a&gt; I came across &lt;a href="https://notebooks.azure.com/"&gt;Azure Notebooks&lt;/a&gt;. This is a free, Azure hosted version of Jupyter that has almost all the features of a local installation but with none of the faff. After quickly spinning up a new notebook here I didn't even look back at the local installation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A Jupyter [Data] Mining Core Project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As per the title and lead of this post, I decided to use Jupyter to have a little fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in September, while grinding my way through &lt;a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0094535/episodes?season=11&amp;amp;ref_=tt_eps_sn_11"&gt;season 11 of Red Dwarf&lt;/a&gt;, I began to wonder why it wasn't as funny as it used to be. Had the writing deteriorated? Were the actors past it? Or were these elements still as great as they used to be and it was me who had changed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started thinking about ways this could be investigated such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using IMDB rating as a measure of humour in each episode of Red Dwarf&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Performing semantic analysis of episode's transcript to see if the sentiment had changed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using word-count to determine whether there was a correlation between character participation and overall humour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, it was a funny notion and provided a pleasant distraction from the &lt;a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt5218266"&gt;pretty awful episode&lt;/a&gt; of Red Dwarf I was watching at the time. I added it to my "ideas" list in &lt;a href="https://trello.com/b/KoTWuFUi/public-board"&gt;Trello&lt;/a&gt;, finished the episode and went to bed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, when I came across Project Jupyter, I knew it'd be a great medium for performing this investigation so shifted the analysis from "Ideas" to "In progress" and got cracking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Data Science using F#&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, while in relation to this investigation I use the term "data science" to basically mean "munging a few numbers and drawing a few graphs", I do think F# makes a fantastic language for the discipline in general. It has some incredible mechanisms for &lt;a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/articles/fsharp/tutorials/type-providers/"&gt;acquiring&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://fsharpforfunandprofit.com/posts/the-option-type/"&gt;cleaning&lt;/a&gt; data as well as for &lt;a href="http://www.quanttec.com/fparsec/"&gt;parsing natural language&lt;/a&gt;. Couple this with it's concise, functional, elegant language and the ability to leverage components from the entire breadth of .NET ecosystem and you have quite a significant offering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Azure Notebooks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Azure implementation of Project Jupyter is first class and, for now at least, totally free. Getting started is as simple as logging in with Microsoft credentials and then clicking 'Add notebook'. Being an MS implementation, I used Edge to edit the notebook and found the experience extremely robust, especially given it's a "Preview" program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact I experience just two issues while authoring my notebook:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data Store - It's not currently possible to upload or store data within the Azure notebook library (despite having functionality to do this in the web-interface). Instead you need to host your data on one of a small number of whitelisted sites. Fortunately Github is one of these sites so this doesn't prove to be much of an issue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Packages - While Azure Notebooks provides access to a large number of packages "out-of-the-box" (i.e. FSharp.Data, XPlot.Plotly, etc) it can be tricky to add/use other packages. For example, I wanted to use the XPlot.GoogleCharts package (as it provided trendline capabilities) and ended up having to write a custom display printer for it to work (due to an &lt;a href="https://github.com/fsprojects/IfSharp/issues/118"&gt;open issue&lt;/a&gt; on Github).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from these issues, authoring and scripting F# in an Azure Notebook was almost as fast as using &lt;a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/articles/fsharp/tutorials/fsharp-interactive/"&gt;"F# Interactive"&lt;/a&gt;. It even provides Intellisense capabilities but, in practice, these are usually too slow to be of actual use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Sharing Notebooks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From Azure Notebooks you're able to download your notebook as a native ".ipynb" file (in fact this is encouraged as MS reserves the right to remove unused notebooks after 60 days). You can then share this file to other people who have Jupyter installed or, preferably, commit it to a repository in Github which has excellent support for Jupyter Notebooks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find my notebook "A sentiment(al) analysis of why Red Dwarf is no longer funny (to me)" &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs/RedDwarfAnalysis/blob/master/Investigation.ipynb"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. As you will see when you click the link, Github not only shows you the static parts of the notebook but actually tries to spin up a kernel and execute the code parts too. This is a "limited rendering only" so Github also provides a link to open the notebook in 'nbviewer' &lt;a href="http://nbviewer.jupyter.org/github/ibebbs/RedDwarfAnalysis/blob/2712285e1f9c69fc347bdfe6404792101eaea5f1/Investigation.ipynb"&gt;web-app&lt;/a&gt;. This link is shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://mvpfyw-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3mppldGfaYEhvWkV7mdUw26-lP3SOzlMTGFbf8slchIfjBL57IH-GrJev6ai_rISiHBKrom7Abg9YFjfhZ1ArOFT7a7mh4gJuGq-CErv1dun48GQC_BdhMV08fh6hbw400d9nHSEXJ0jA2nPBIrpOPNrOz0I3lVY1tu_L656ylQKg?width=660&amp;amp;height=283&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:660; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Open external view with nbviewer"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The analysis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had timeboxed my investigation into Project Jupyter and therefore didn't get round to performing an actual sentiment anaylsis of the content of each episode. However I did manage to do the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Programmatically download episode information from several sources in JSON format and use &lt;a href="http://fsharp.github.io/FSharp.Data/library/JsonValue.html"&gt;JsonValue&lt;/a&gt; to dynamically query these sources&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scrape demographically categorized rating information from IMDB and use &lt;a href="http://fsharp.github.io/FSharp.Data/reference/fsharp-data-htmldocument.html"&gt;HtmlDocument&lt;/a&gt; to parse the data into strong types&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Resolve issue with rendering XPlot.GoogleCharts charts within the notebook and use these charts to provide an interactive visualisation of the decline in rating of Red Dwarf across time and demographic categories.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This provided a fair stab at correlating episode rating with the overall decline in Red Dwarf's humourousness but is a long way short of any form of "data science". It was both enlightening and a lot of fun doing this small project and I will certainly consider Azure Notebooks as a valuable tool in my toolbox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should I find the time, I would certainly like to return to this project and use &lt;a href="http://www.quanttec.com/fparsec/"&gt;FParsec&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://azure.microsoft.com/en-gb/services/cognitive-services/text-analytics/"&gt;Azure Text Analytics&lt;/a&gt; to perform an actual sentiment analysis. Hopefully it'll overturn, or at least help justify, my somewhat disturbing conclusion!&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I had a lot of fun playing with &lt;a href="http://jupyter.org/"&gt;Project Jupyter&lt;/a&gt;. For those that aren't aware of this project, it's an effort to provide a workspace for performing repeatable experimentation with data. In short it mixes markdown editing capabilities with a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Read%E2%80%93eval%E2%80%93print_loop"&gt;REPL&lt;/a&gt; environment for a large number of languages. From the website:&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<link href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/CqrsEsMvvmRxEfSqlUwpPcl" />
		<id>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/CqrsEsMvvmRxEfSqlUwpPcl</id>
		<title>CQRS/ES &amp; MVVM using RX, EF &amp; SQL in UWP &amp; PCL …</title>
		<updated>2016-12-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<content>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;So, while ToddlerBox is riding high, I'd like to share some thoughts about another app I have in the store; &lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-gb/store/p/littlelittle/9nblggh51b1b"&gt;LittleLittle&lt;/a&gt;. This app has been the subject of most of my efforts over the last few months and is significantly more complex (and, frustratingly, less successful!) than ToddlerBox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LittleLittle was started shortly after my baby girl started weaning and became constipated - apparently a very common occurrence. When we visited a paediatrician about it, they asked that we keep a record of her bowel movements so that we could track the condition to see if it was getting better or worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"I wonder if there's an app for that", I thought. And, of course, there was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Opportunity and Methodology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, while there are plenty of other baby tracking apps out there, very few work across platform (I use Windows Mobile while my partner uses Android) and even fewer work as I feel they should.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the requirement to work across a variety of platforms, maximising code re-use was extremely desirable. As such, I decided that all of the core-logic for the app needed to be written in a PCL. Furthermore, particular care would be taken to observe a pure MVVM methodology so that ViewModels (an embodiment of the app's UX) could also be shared across platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, following some work in the CQRS/ES space at my previous employer, I wanted to write an app that used this methodology end-to-end. LittleLittle seemed a perfect opportunity to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Technology and Platform&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To partner the &lt;a href="http://martinfowler.com/bliki/CQRS.html"&gt;CQRS&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href="http://martinfowler.com/eaaDev/EventSourcing.html"&gt;ES&lt;/a&gt; methodology, I was keen to use &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/hh242985.aspx"&gt;Rx&lt;/a&gt; as the driving technology for implementation. As readers of my blog will know, I am very much of the opinion that "&lt;a href="http://slides.com/robwormald/everything-is-a-stream#/" title="Everything is a stream - Rob Wormald"&gt;everything&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/staltz/868e7e9bc2a7b8c1f754" title="The introduction to Reactive Programming you've been missing - andrestaltz"&gt;is&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://weareadaptive.com/blog/2014/05/05/everything-is-a-stream/" title="Reactive Trader 2: Everything is a Stream - Matt Barrett"&gt;a&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://colintheshots.com/blog/?p=85" title="Be Reactive - Colintheshots"&gt;stream&lt;/a&gt;" and event sourcing from "a stream of events" seemed a perfect fit for Rx.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that the Event Sourcing methodology - not to mention the nature of the app itself - required a persistence layer, I decided to use a recently new technology; &lt;a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/ef/core/"&gt;Entity Framework Core&lt;/a&gt;. I decided on EFCore simply because the tooling for the UWP platform was pretty good and I liked the 'code-first' approach to schema and migration generation. Coupled with this, I decided to use a &lt;a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/ef/core/providers/sqlite/"&gt;SQLite&lt;/a&gt; database as it was a proven data store for use with EFCore and across a variety of underlying platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, when I started LittleLittle I was studying for the &lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/learning/exam-70-357.aspx"&gt;Microsoft Beta Exam "Developing Mobile Apps"&lt;/a&gt;. As such, while I was keen for the app to be cross-platform, the initial platform I wanted to support was UWP. I was - and still am - amazed by how, if you craft your code and views carefully, an application can run on an amazing number for platforms including RaspberryPi, Phone, Tablet, PC, Xbox and Hololens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;And here's one I made earlier…&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After many weeks of work, innumerable iterations and much refactoring, I ended up with this:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;div class="horizontal_list"&gt;
    &lt;div class="horizontal_list_item"&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://zuimew-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3mcsjpC-olqYg0zbsOtSdJ1adHni1Apkeklf-2gzDpiB9ph_25HlwE5jeyMxex_1ryS-zVZxkMw0vtNsDCMrnzser84bs_zq9S75PZqddHWrRfMGfo3YbQhc-3ZwJGzjHMRuX_Ml0UQ_81MQnW4oOqva8Ap2jw2DIbULXOgc9ER7E?width=144&amp;amp;height=256&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:256px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Splashscreen"&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="horizontal_list_item"&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://zuilew-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3muwswRbqzTW9QY2Ms8LyW2AAl8vIDTt8DKl-lsB_0uqQvGZJDkqFRF1Jg151-YQzqyUxourRpTXaaHttLPaXkE3hXmavIZKYyI7isdayp_PLbXDVOKCX_u83bEdzFmsfPRAikqWEVteWkTaFnX1SH8YgEd4UABUffd5dVZ4QAkvM?width=144&amp;amp;height=256&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:256px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Available actions"&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="horizontal_list_item"&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://zuikew-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3mCHoxbDYsMkbkH-RQlFyxK5Y6zVhP_TU7JYj_MLCQrEfQsClKqlWoVqSsEt-ae7tYBvH89lvstPnIfhrA6MKPXNyjAp7O9EMy28Cof7nnc22DTFYs5FUECbQUEV_P8HxaVwWSFUyEN1MGAuWfY1x-36ZHviTEjqBOZM9m6pYm80Q?width=144&amp;amp;height=256&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:256px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="History"&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="horizontal_list_item"&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://zuiiew-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3mz7gADh3Y09Fb6QuQ2CY35gjWD2T9KEY_oWWbcijxNl2URePlVW0IjLhEBWeIoPOR1a-gAhRyoYNTdtefVfe8vd6d-Lnq5Cq_rcXEt4HZ5kt-jxOsCPLkJCaJtnfi5P-dTVNtJhMBYNbOtfiHXiPd9HsZODdjUwX-LphBvBAl_98?width=144&amp;amp;height=256&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:256px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Height and weight charts"&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="horizontal_list_item"&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://zeirew-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3miUjsB3mUDyGdRCPudsd1I42ad9-MAI5JRV15z821gQAc7H_mqIgEeEDr1YWCvZh5AZOT6BAuAVSdMwz-Qnr6mG53KzP8xbeo2hinEJyplWnHoVs4FG7sbga6HMgLP6qd_x_mxRx2uqEVTfVAgXSOLMmHnQSpMxbV7DzQzPT1LXY?width=144&amp;amp;height=256&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:256px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Sleep and excretion charts"&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="horizontal_list_item"&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://zeiqew-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3m2ZYqI7vBDCM_Ptv8Xvgo-UeDhvqtKIh5cxNy40KinoCzXem7V_-gIOsrkYvWyOtI6dod-HgNweHuue9DUB9r2yvgPNNXVvkPkIJKshYS4z-M1Qts9DPdqobqwnfHpIjewlWDj_Z6sFFVgbRlvsySton_n_nQrk4buXjebRss5JQ?width=144&amp;amp;height=256&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:256px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Sleep and excretion charts"&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I'm extremely happy with the result. CQRS/ES and Rx are a perfect match and the technology stack in general has been extremely productive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This morning I drew up a (retrospective) architecture to illustrate how much of the application is portable and how simple yet extensible it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://bdliqq-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3mdSQ-fHhXJWrDI-4wfqFoaso56RU_vCH51ognfdTMYlml6nEgxQHUJWgTgHg5fw4cAEwpaJM1GVookE2ok4HscXXmd-a6WAcU7Xd509Rdmb35JaS2-5Zzx5G_YiNpAoxLekZifHRzDQittyVv6rybVIp33YiqopFatHZVcND-lhY?width=1024&amp;amp;height=626&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:800; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Architecture diagram"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;"The proof is in the dog-fooding"&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apologies for the mixed metaphors but, suffice to say, while the technology choices may be deemed to be a success, the app can only be consider to be so if it is fit for purpose. As such, I have been using LittleLittle everyday for the past several weeks - across a number of iterations and versions - and I'm very, very pleased with the result. The UI is fast and efficient to use and the app has yet to crash or lose any data (either at runtime or between versions).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, a little while ago my other half took our baby to stay with her grandparents for a several days and agreed to keep LittleLittle up to date while she was away. She came back with a couple of small suggestions but overall very impressed by how fast and easy to use it was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it has yet to see a significant number of Windows Store acquisitions, Store Analytics shows there are a few people actively using the app and, so far, I have yet to see any crashes or failures. I intend to leverage the success of ToddlerBox to promote LittleLittle in the near future so, fingers crossed, it'll start getting some serious use and useful feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Moving forward&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I intend to put LittleLittle on hold for a little while in order to work on some other projects I've been meaning to look at, I very much intend to return to the project early in the new year. I have a backlog full of features I'd like to implement not to mention the need to write a version which runs on Android/iOS (which will probably be in Xamarin).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the mean time, I will be blogging about a few of the components in the architecture diagram above and sharing some of the approaches I have taken and successes (or problems!) I encountered.&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;So, while ToddlerBox is riding high, I'd like to share some thoughts about another app I have in the store; &lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-gb/store/p/littlelittle/9nblggh51b1b"&gt;LittleLittle&lt;/a&gt;. This app has been the subject of most of my efforts over the last few months and is significantly more complex (and, frustratingly, less successful!) than ToddlerBox.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<link href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/HomeNetworkMonitoring-PartIV" />
		<id>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/HomeNetworkMonitoring-PartIV</id>
		<title>Home Network Monitoring - Part IV</title>
		<updated>2016-04-16T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<content>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;In the last post, I used the Logstash &lt;code&gt;dns&lt;/code&gt; filter to translate remote server IP addresses into recognisable domain names. In this post, I will look to perform a similar operation for local IP addresses in order to translate them into recognisable device names.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;translating local ip addresses to device names&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While in the last post we could use the &lt;code&gt;dns&lt;/code&gt; filter to perform a reverse dns lookup to resolve a remote domain name for an IP address, this is not possible with local IP addresses. Fortunately, I have two key tools that I can use to perform a similar operation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While my router behaves as a DHCP server, it has a feature that allows it to always allocate the same IP address to a given MAC address. Therefore I know a given device will always have a specific IP address.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Logstash provides the &lt;code&gt;translate&lt;/code&gt; filter which allows you to map from one value to another via a dictionary lookup.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With my routers "Bind IP to MAC" function set up, I will author a new &lt;code&gt;yaml&lt;/code&gt; file that meets the specifications outlined in the &lt;code&gt;translate&lt;/code&gt; filter &lt;a href="https://www.elastic.co/guide/en/logstash/current/plugins-filters-translate.html#plugins-filters-translate-destination"&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt;. It looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;192.168.1.3: TPLink Range Extender
192.168.1.9: Ricoh Printer
192.168.1.10: Server A
192.168.1.21: PC A
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll name this file &lt;code&gt;IPLookup.yaml&lt;/code&gt; and save it besides the &lt;code&gt;syslog.config&lt;/code&gt; file. Next I need to add additional filters to &lt;code&gt;syslog.config&lt;/code&gt; which now looks as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;input {
  tcp {
    port =&amp;gt; 5000
    type =&amp;gt; syslog
  }
  udp {
    port =&amp;gt; 5000
    type =&amp;gt; syslog
  }
}

filter {
    grok {
        match =&amp;gt; [ "message", "&amp;lt;%{POSINT:syslog_pri}&amp;gt;%{SYSLOGTIMESTAMP:syslog_timestamp} Vigor\: Local User \(MAC=%{MAC:source_mac}\): %{IP:source_address}(?::%{POSINT:source_port})? -&amp;gt; %{IP:destination_address}(?::%{POSINT:destination_port})? \((?&amp;lt;protocol&amp;gt;TCP|UDP)\)" ]
        add_tag =&amp;gt; "access"
    }
    if "access" in [tags] {
        mutate {
            add_field =&amp;gt; {
              "source_host" =&amp;gt; "%{[source_address]}"
              "destination_host" =&amp;gt; "%{[destination_address]}"
            }
        }
        dns {
            reverse =&amp;gt; [ "destination_host" ]
            action =&amp;gt; "replace"
            nameserver =&amp;gt; "192.168.1.1"
        }
        translate {
            destination =&amp;gt; "source_host"
            dictionary_path =&amp;gt; "config\IPLookup.yaml"
            fallback =&amp;gt; "%{source_address}"
            field =&amp;gt; "source_address"      
            override =&amp;gt; true   
        }
    }
}

output {
  elasticsearch {
    hosts =&amp;gt; ["192.168.1.30:9200"]
    index =&amp;gt; "syslog-%{+YYYY.MM.dd}"
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note the &lt;code&gt;translate&lt;/code&gt; filter where I lookup the &lt;code&gt;source_address&lt;/code&gt; field in the &lt;code&gt;IPLookup.yaml&lt;/code&gt; file and put the result in the &lt;code&gt;source_host&lt;/code&gt; field. If not found, the &lt;code&gt;fallback&lt;/code&gt; value instructs the filter to output the &lt;code&gt;source_address&lt;/code&gt; into the &lt;code&gt;source_host&lt;/code&gt; field. The &lt;code&gt;override&lt;/code&gt; value is set to true as the &lt;code&gt;source_host&lt;/code&gt; field is added in the &lt;code&gt;mutate&lt;/code&gt; filter above as a fail-safe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the changes to configuration in place, I once again restart Logstash. Once a syslog message has been received, I get the mapping from ElasticSearch and update it to mark the &lt;code&gt;local_host&lt;/code&gt; field as &lt;code&gt;not_analyzed&lt;/code&gt;. Then, in Kibana, I refresh the field list for the 'syslog-*' index, add 'local_host' to the 'Syslog Messages' saved search, load 'Access By Local Address' visualization and modify it to use 'local_host' rather than the 'local_address' field and save it as 'Access By Local Host'. Finally, I replace this visualization on my dashboard and get the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-DashboardWithAccessByLocalHost.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Dashboard With Access By Local Host"&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;further mappings&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I've got the translation of local IP addresses to names working, I'm going to add a few more translations for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IP Address to Operating System&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IP Address to Wired/WiFi connection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TCP and UDP Port to Protocol (using a &lt;a href="http://www.iana.org/assignments/service-names-port-numbers/service-names-port-numbers.xhtml"&gt;CSV from IANA&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With these in place, the dashboard is starting to come together:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-DashboardWithLocalPortAndOsLookups.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Dashboard With Local Port And Os Lookups"&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I showed how to display local device names rather than IP addresses by using LogStash's &lt;code&gt;translate&lt;/code&gt; filter. I then used this filter to provide further information about local device and protocols.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next post, I'll show how to add some variation to the dashboard by mapping destination locations.&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;In the last post, I used the Logstash &lt;code&gt;dns&lt;/code&gt; filter to translate remote server IP addresses into recognisable domain names. In this post, I will look to perform a similar operation for local IP addresses in order to translate them into recognisable device names.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<link href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/3DPrintingWithTheCelRobox" />
		<link rel="enclosure" type="image" href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/y3mgQk7Eo-T13uKoaK88obO48Y6pzP0KHelfDJwLdORXiP6nnbplZzVSqbrBCBPh9bTpRgyynkyjS9mY53_ZE1f0NDpBcuKTDB7Jf6_a2me30twiv6CGRB6lQjK6Lu-DKkn6LTWVHSq463duCG-820-pQKTQ_q5ifVlXN40_86622Q%253Fwidth=965&amp;height=292&amp;cropmode=none" />
		<id>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/3DPrintingWithTheCelRobox</id>
		<title>3D Printing with the CEL Robox</title>
		<updated>2016-10-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<content>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;So, I've wanted a 3D printer for a while and recently a perfect storm of events meant I finally took the plunge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had hit a wall in my MonsterPi project trying to mount a RaspberryPi in a constrained space (more on this in a subsequent post). Most of my usual hacks (you'd be amazed what you can do with a sheet of acrylic and a Meccano set) simply wouldn't cut it and I was considering abandoning the project. Without intentionally meaning to, I found myself looking at 3D printers on &lt;a href="http://www.maplin.co.uk/c/gadgets-toys-and-hobbies/3d-printers"&gt;Maplin's website&lt;/a&gt; and saw that they were selling 'used' 3D printers at quite a discount.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a quick look around for reviews I found that one of the models Maplin were selling - the &lt;a href="http://www.maplin.co.uk/p/cel-robox-3d-printer-used-b81qq"&gt;CEL Robox&lt;/a&gt; - was listed as one of the best "Plug 'n' play" printers on &lt;a href="https://www.3dhubs.com/best-3d-printer-guide#plugnplay-cel-robox"&gt;3D Hubs&lt;/a&gt;. Moreover, my local (well, 15 miles away) Maplin's store had one in stock. But there was that 'used' thing. From what I'd gathered, getting a 3D printer to print reliably is tricky at the best of times, and I was thinking of buying one that had already been used and returned or worse, didn't even work in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Too intrigued not to dig a little deeper, I gave Maplin a call. Now experience has lead me not to expect too much from Maplin's employees - at best they're well meaning but witless, at worst they think you are -  but this time proved to be an exception. The guy who answered the phone was superb (note to self: must tweet Maplin about how great this guy is). Although he initially seemed confused about not having a used model of the 3D printer in store, he checked the website to confirm availability then the store stock levels to work out what was going on. Turns out the 'used' printer they had was actually the display model and after noting that he was unsure of the history of the printer he offered to make a couple of calls to other staff to find out the condition and how much it had been used then call me back; as I said, he was excellent. As promised, he called back in 15 minutes or so having confirmed that the printer had only been used to print a few example models and had otherwise sat idle for almost a year. Unfortunately in that time it had garnered a few scratches and lost it's box and support material but, having talked to his manager, he would be able to offer a further discount on the used price if I wanted to come in a take a look at it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the store an hour later it turned out that the guy I had talked to was actually the store manager and was really going the extra mile. By the time I had turned up, he had collated replacement components (power lead, usb lead, brushes, etc) from store stock and had the printer out ready for me to inspect. Amusingly, he had his staff so well organised that, seeing a few components laying around, they had actually put them all back on the shelves so he had to go collect them all again - but I couldn't help but be impressed. Anyway, the scratches turned out to be superfluous, the offer of an additional discount very attractive and the store manager's assurances that should anything be wrong with the unit he'd ensure it was replaced no questions asked very persuasive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I bought it, brought it home and, once the baby was safely ensconced at nursery the next day, set it up and set about calibrating it. The unit itself is a thing of beauty. Bold lines and colours with smooth, solid feeling mechanical components and a general air of quality; not at all what I've come to expect from a &lt;a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/robox/robox-desktop-3d-printer-and-micro-manufacturing-p"&gt;Kickstarter funded project&lt;/a&gt;. While I was initially wary of buying a 3D printer that used a proprietary "chipped" spool for fear of a lock-in to an expensive source of filament, the integrated nature of the spool into the body of the unit and the intelligence it provides to the software - everything from how much spool is left to how much a particular model will cost to print - is fantastic. Far from other "hobbyist" 3D printers where filament projects precariously around the unit, the feed of filament to the head is completely hidden from view and loading of filament completely automated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately calibration wasn't quite as smooth and it took a long time to get the printer ready to actually try printing a model. In fact, despite repeatedly trying and following all suggestions, one of the calibration tests - the needle valve opening calibration for the fill nozzle - stoically refused to run successfully. This may have been the result of the unit sitting idle for so long or simply me not setting it up right but the failure to pass this test was extremely worrisome. Even the 'purge' material test (used to completely empty the print heads when you're planning on changing material) failed to lay down material as it should but this was mostly resolved by vigorously cleaning the print bed with the isopropyl alcohol.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, despite the needle valve opening calibration still failing, I decided to print a model to see how it would perform before deciding whether or not to return the unit. From CEL's downloadable samples, I decided to try printing the 'cargo-box' as it didn't seem to require too much filament and a small container is always useful for something. Actually loading and starting to print a model using CEL's &lt;a href="http://www.cel-robox.com/downloads/"&gt;AutoMaker&lt;/a&gt; software is ludicrously simple: start a new layout, load a model, choose the granularity of the print, go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Watching a 3D model being printed is really something to behold. Despite it taking hours "like watching a 3D printer fabricate" should really become the metaphorical antonym to "like watching paint dry"; from the initial outline of the print being laid on the print bed, to seeing a solid object emerge, the process is fascinating. Taking a virtual object modelled on your computer and seeing that object take shape and become a physical object in the real world is thrilling, with innumerable possibilities opening up with every layer of filament laid down.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short order (well, actually 'long order' but it certainly didn't feel that way) and with much amazement and relief, the print was finished perfectly. A 1.5" square, green plastic cargo-box sat inside the Robox; I had fabricated a solid object from - seemingly - nothing. Once the unit had cooled the heated print-bed and unlocked the door, I tried removing the box, entirely expecting to have to lever and peel the plastic off the bed. To my surprise it moved easily, seemingly held to the bed by nothing more than a static charge. I was further surprised by the strength of the box; given it was made from nothing more than melted strands of plastic, I absolutely expected the fabricated object to have the tensile strength of a faberge egg. Yet it was incredibly rigid and inflexible, only the tell-tale layering giving away the fact that it had been 3D printer rather than cast in an industrial manufacturing plant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://0ohhnq.dm2302.livefilestore.com/y3mzj-a64dzTwhL7kVdtCG_OooHuVEnWyP5gynRF28lVCG247INMKuJpO8E2neQaekUtsZINVLDxnr5iwvoFRVqrOysfCj5ouJTt3e9oNYAOlrvaV2V7FquQultYnqicCjLCpdtiUF1NCeS5hfzgoXL5KhtZ2iBMvDpnslKBEX86FI?width=1024&amp;amp;height=576&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="My first 3D printed object"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now it was time to see if I could use the printer for the purpose I bought it: fabricating custom components for other projects. First up was a bracket to hold a RaspberryPi and other components in a very specific configuration. &lt;a href="http://www.sketchup.com/products/sketchup-pro/new-in-2016?gclid=CIK4ks2Cy88CFc0y0wodZmwHaQ"&gt;SketchUp&lt;/a&gt; has been my go-to 3D modelling software of choice since being bought and given away by Google. It is amazingly quick and easy to use for almost everything except extremely precise components with low tolerances; i.e. exactly the kind of thing I needed to do. So I went about looking for alternatives and quickly settled on the free version of &lt;a href="https://www.rs-online.com/designspark/mechanical-software"&gt;DesignSpark Mechanical from RS Components&lt;/a&gt;. Despite some quirkiness in it's UI, it provides most of the features and ease of use of SketchUp with several digits of precision for designed components. Indeed, instead of using a mouse to try to get the exact length of an edge, you can simply enter the length you want on the keyboard; precisely the functionality I thought was missing from SketchUp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took several hours to complete the 3D model for the bracket I needed - somewhat due to DesignSpark's learning curve but mostly the precise measurements and imprecise iteration required to design a bracket that would hold all the components just so - but eventually it was ready to print. Again, friction from design software to print ready was minimal. DesignSpark is able to export in the standard STL format and AutoMaker loaded the model and positioned it on the print-bed automatically, promising to fabricate me a completely custom component for just £1.48's worth of material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I set the print going but was quickly dismayed that the first layer of the print wasn't being laid properly at the far corners of the bed, mostly due to the fact that the corners of the bed away from the tabs that hold it in place had risen slightly. Regardless, I decided to let the print continue and see if subsequent layers would adhere to the small smudge of material the print head had managed to deposit. This turned out to be the right choice as by layer three the base of the bracket was fully formed and the printer had started using the "fill" nozzle to quickly start filling out further layers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took about three hours to design and an hour and forty minutes to fabricate, but the bracket fitted perfectly and was easily strong enough to hold all the components in the configuration I needed. I was a very happy boy and immediately starting to design a subsequent bracket I needed for the same project and plan for a load of other custom bits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, if you're thinking of buying a 3D printer and can afford what is - regardless of the heavy discount - an expensive bit of technology, I would absolutely recommend going for it. The possibilities of what you can create are mind-boggling and the sensation of watching them come into existence exhilarating. Being able to fabricate components I previously had to hack together from off the shelf bits is tremendously empowering and I can unashamedly say that I am completely hooked on 3D printing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, while I have no direct experience of other 3D printers, I wouldn't hesitate to recommend CEL's Robox printer as - despite still failing the nozzle calibration - it has yet to fail a print and the software is remarkably straight forward and easy to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch this space for more adventures in 3D printing as I integrate my new found fabrication abilities into my innumerable ongoing projects. First up: MonsterPi.&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;So, I've wanted a 3D printer for a while and recently a perfect storm of events meant I finally took the plunge.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<link href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/OnTheImportanceOfDoingSomething" />
		<id>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/OnTheImportanceOfDoingSomething</id>
		<title>On The Importance of Doing Something</title>
		<updated>2015-11-16T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<content>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;I've just become a father. It's amazing and I'm loving every day, from waking up in the morning and being greeted by huge grin from my little girl to putting her to bed in the evening when she can barely keep her eyes open. My baby instantaneously became priority number one and has left little time for other passions like home programming projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, simultaneously, I have found the time since my baby was born to be some of the most productive time of my life. Since she her birth, I've spent every hour possible with her, worked regular hours - and been productive during those hours - at my day job, got an unexpectedly healthy amount of sleep and still managed to complete a significant amount of work on personal projects as well as creating and writing this blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While reflecting on why this might be, I came up with one simple, inescapable conclusion: &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs" title="ibebbs Github Profile"&gt;my Github profile&lt;/a&gt;. More specifically the "Current Streak" of contributions. You see, I am a sucker for gamification and seeing that "Current Streak" increase each day is remarkably rewarding. As such, I am finding time each day - no matter how little - to do &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previously, I'd get home in the evening, think about the projects I had to work on, realise that there probably wouldn't be enough time to make significant progress and procrastinate about it until I had more time available to "get things done properly" - which was happening increasingly rarely. Now, instead of focusing on some distant goal, I simply think about finding &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; I can do and publish to Github in whatever time I have available. It really doesn't matter what it is, as long as I get the &lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/surface/en-gb/devices/surface-pro-4" title="Microsoft Surface Pro 4"&gt;Surface&lt;/a&gt; out and start. Almost always, once I've started something, I get engrossed in it and am able to spend way more time than I thought might be available on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, I'm writing this post from the sofa in my front room having spent a wonderful evening with my other half and little girl. Not having had time to make a commit today, I decided not to get an early night and instead tucked them into their respective beds before heading back down stairs to get a start on this post. Initially I had planned simply jot down a few ideas and possibly write a sentence or two before committing to Github and retiring for the evening. Yet here I am still writing after several paragraphs (and &lt;a href="https://music.microsoft.com/album/london-grammar/if-you-wait-deluxe-edition/bz.EE99E107-0100-11DB-89CA-0019B92A3933?action=play" title="London Grammar on Groove Music"&gt;one very enjoyable album&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I probably won't finish tonight, and definitely won't publish this post until I've had time to re-read and edit it. But I've got my commit for the day and made an unexpected amount of progress on a blog post about making an unexpected amount of progress. In short, I got &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; done and that feels good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Night!&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;I've just become a father. It's amazing and I'm loving every day, from waking up in the morning and being greeted by huge grin from my little girl to putting her to bed in the evening when she can barely keep her eyes open. My baby instantaneously became priority number one and has left little time for other passions like home programming projects.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<link href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/RxWebWithTypescript" />
		<id>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/RxWebWithTypescript</id>
		<title>WebRx and Typescript</title>
		<updated>2016-03-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<content>
                                        


&lt;h1&gt;Continuing with WebRx&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="./posts/RxWeb"&gt;part 1&lt;/a&gt; of this series I showed how to set up a project structure that allows you to start using WebRx from within Visual Studio. While fairly simple, the example provides a great illustration of you how WebRx allows you to separate your view and view model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article I further develop the structure to allow you to develop your application using Typescript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;From 'app.js' to 'app.ts'&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previously we copied a chunk of JavaScript from the WebRx &lt;a href="http://webrxjs.org/docs/getting-started.html"&gt;getting started guide&lt;/a&gt; into an &lt;code&gt;app.js&lt;/code&gt; script that was directly used from within the &lt;code&gt;index.html&lt;/code&gt; file. We now want to &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Source-to-source_compiler"&gt;&lt;em&gt;transpile&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; the &lt;code&gt;app.js&lt;/code&gt; script from a Typescript file so that we can further develop the application in a structured and type-safe manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do this simply follow the following steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delete the existing &lt;code&gt;app.js&lt;/code&gt; file leaving the &lt;code&gt;js&lt;/code&gt; folder empty.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add and configure a &lt;code&gt;TypeScript JSON Configuration File&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add a &lt;code&gt;TypeScript JSON Configuration File&lt;/code&gt; to the solution as shown below&lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/RxWebWithTypescript/AddTypeScriptJsonConfigurationFile.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Add TypeScript Json Configuration File"&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Replace the &lt;code&gt;node_modules&lt;/code&gt; exclusion with &lt;code&gt;Scripts&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br&gt;
By default Visual Studio (or, more acurately, the TypeScript transpiler) with pick up all &lt;code&gt;ts&lt;/code&gt; files in the solution. As we don't want to attempt to re-transpile all the referenced typescript files we add &lt;code&gt;Scripts&lt;/code&gt; to the exclusion list. Further, as we added a reference to &lt;code&gt;WebRx&lt;/code&gt; via Nuget, our references are in the &lt;code&gt;Scripts&lt;/code&gt; folder, not &lt;code&gt;node_modules&lt;/code&gt;, so this exclusion can be removed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add an &lt;code&gt;outDir&lt;/code&gt; setting to transpile to the &lt;code&gt;js&lt;/code&gt; folder&lt;br&gt;
This setting will force the TypeScript transpiler to output the transpiled JavaScript files to the &lt;code&gt;js&lt;/code&gt; folder where they can be used by the client browser.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You should now have a &lt;code&gt;tsconfig.json&lt;/code&gt; file that looks like this:
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;{
  "compilerOptions": {
    "noImplicitAny": false,
    "noEmitOnError": true,
    "removeComments": false,
    "sourceMap": true,
    "target": "es5",
    "outDir": "js"
  },
  "exclude": [
    "Scripts",
    "wwwroot"
  ]
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol start="3"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add a &lt;code&gt;ts&lt;/code&gt; folder to the solution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add an &lt;code&gt;app.ts&lt;/code&gt; typescript file to the &lt;code&gt;ts&lt;/code&gt; folder.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add references to Rx and WebRx to the &lt;code&gt;app.ts&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;br&gt;
WebRx requires that you add an explicit reference to &lt;code&gt;rx.all.d.ts&lt;/code&gt; prior to the reference to &lt;code&gt;web.rx.d.ts&lt;/code&gt; in order for the Rx module to be brought into scope. The references should therefore be added like this:
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;/// &amp;lt;reference path="../Scripts/rx.all.d.ts"/&amp;gt;
/// &amp;lt;reference path="../Scripts/typings/web.rx.d.ts" /&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implement view / view model code&lt;br&gt;
You can now re-implement the code from &lt;code&gt;app.js&lt;/code&gt; as TypeScript virtually verbatim but do note how you get Intellisense for all the methods and properties of &lt;code&gt;wx&lt;/code&gt; module.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix compilation error with call to &lt;code&gt;wx.applyBindings&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br&gt;
The &lt;code&gt;wx.applyBindings&lt;/code&gt; method &lt;em&gt;requires&lt;/em&gt; a &lt;code&gt;model&lt;/code&gt; parameter which, in JavaScript, is defaulted but in TypeScript causes a compilation error. To resolve this, simply pass an empty object to the method.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your &lt;code&gt;app.ts&lt;/code&gt; file should now look like this:
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;/// &amp;lt;reference path="../Scripts/rx.all.d.ts"/&amp;gt;
/// &amp;lt;reference path="../Scripts/typings/web.rx.d.ts" /&amp;gt;

wx.app.component('hello', {
    viewModel: function () {
        this.firstName = 'Bart';
        this.lastName = 'Simpson';
    },
    template: 'The name is &amp;lt;span data-bind="text: firstName + \' \' + lastName"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;'
});

wx.router.state({
    name: "$",
    views: { 'main': "hello" }
});

wx.router.reload();

wx.applyBindings({});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol start="5"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compile the project and include the generated &lt;code&gt;js/app.js&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;js/app.js.map&lt;/code&gt; files into the project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hit F5 and you should again see the message 'The name is Bart Simpson' displayed in your default browser.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congratulations, you're now ready to develop your application using full Intellisense and in the comfort of the knowledge that the compiler (well, transpiler) will pick up any syntactic bugs you may inadvertently create.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always, the completed &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs/BlogProjects/tree/master/WebRxWithTypeScript"&gt;source code for this post&lt;/a&gt; can be found in the &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs/BlogProjects"&gt;BlogProjects repository&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs"&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="./posts/RxWeb"&gt;part 1&lt;/a&gt; of this series I showed how to set up a project structure that allows you to start using WebRx from within Visual Studio. While fairly simple, the example provides a great illustration of you how WebRx allows you to separate your view and view model.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<link href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/DartInVisualStudioCode" />
		<id>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/DartInVisualStudioCode</id>
		<title>Dart web development with Visual Studio Code</title>
		<updated>2017-01-17T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<content>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;Visual Studio Code is rapidly becoming my go-to editor for anything not project-oriented C#/F#. I've switched from &lt;a href="https://atom.io/"&gt;Atom&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href="(https://code.visualstudio.com/)"&gt;VSC&lt;/a&gt; for editing my (&lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/NewBlogUsingWyam"&gt;statically-generated, Markdown driven&lt;/a&gt;) blog and have used it for authoring powershell scripts, dockerfiles and much, much more. So, when I decided I wanted to write some &lt;a href="https://www.dartlang.org/"&gt;Dart&lt;/a&gt; code, it was the obvious choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why Dart?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why did I decide on Dart? Well, I had project I wanted to undertake that featured some... shock horror... dynamic web content. If that isn't enough to send chills down your spine, you've either &lt;a href="https://hackernoon.com/how-it-feels-to-learn-javascript-in-2016-d3a717dd577f#.fqoett4pt"&gt;never had to look at getting started with modern web development&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://medium.com/@pistacchio/i-m-a-web-developer-and-i-ve-been-stuck-with-the-simplest-app-for-the-last-10-days-fb5c50917df#.glf30ovv1"&gt;you've already drunk the cool-aid&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Either way, most rational people in the industry will (in the moments of clarity between writing off the last framework as dated and evangelising the next) reluctantly admit that &lt;a href="https://medium.com/@wob/the-sad-state-of-web-development-1603a861d29f#.lqu2r4xup"&gt;modern web development is a mess&lt;/a&gt;. But this is the world we live in and the best one can do is dodge the analysis paralysis and mitigate the majority of the risks. For me, this was adopting a &lt;a href="https://www.dartlang.org/guides/language/language-tour"&gt;strongly-typed modern development language&lt;/a&gt; that has a &lt;a href="https://webdev.dartlang.org/"&gt;strong web pedegry&lt;/a&gt; and just get on with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;But in Visual Studio Code?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why not? It's a great editor and already has great support for Dart courtesy of Danny Tuppeny's &lt;a href="https://marketplace.visualstudio.com/items?itemName=DanTup.DartVS-VisualStudiosupportforGooglesDart"&gt;excellent Dart extension&lt;/a&gt;. Furthermore, I try to keep my development machine as lean and clean as possible so I didn't want to have to &lt;a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/webstorm/"&gt;install an IDE specifically for Dart development&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, as you'll see, getting set up for Dart development with Visual Studio Code is very easy, doesn't require any installation (everything is "xcopy" deployed) and you can start being productive almost right away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will need the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://code.visualstudio.com/Download"&gt;Visual Studio Code&lt;/a&gt; - obviously&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://marketplace.visualstudio.com/items?itemName=DanTup.dart-code"&gt;DartVS&lt;/a&gt; - the Dart language extension for Visual Studio Code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://storage.googleapis.com/dart-archive/channels/stable/release/1.21.0/sdk/dartsdk-windows-x64-release.zip"&gt;The Dart SDK&lt;/a&gt; - the code Dart binaries and tools needed for dart development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://storage.googleapis.com/dart-archive/channels/stable/release/latest/dartium/dartium-windows-ia32-release.zip"&gt;Dartium&lt;/a&gt; - a version of Chrome (even called "Chrome.exe") with a built in Dart runtime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Download and extract the Dart SDK to a location on your HD (I use &lt;code&gt;C:\Apps&lt;/code&gt; for "manually" installed tools/applications so will be using the path &lt;code&gt;C:\Apps\dart-sdk&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Download and extract Dartium to a location on your HD (&lt;code&gt;C:\Apps\chromium&lt;/code&gt; for me).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a new directory wherever you keep your source files and name it &lt;code&gt;GettingStartedWithDart&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In this directory, create two further directories named &lt;code&gt;lib&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;web&lt;/code&gt; (this structure follows the &lt;a href="https://www.dartlang.org/tools/pub/package-layout"&gt;Pub Package Layout Conventions&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start Visual Studio Code and open the &lt;code&gt;GettingStartedWithDart&lt;/code&gt; folder. You should see something like this:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;img src="https://plt6eg-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3m_WQkZhj4Xo-vjZzyUVujyGYAM3lM7Gs84uuf59zCfPKJQzrT9d--PF8Ns9Gwm3qluxzW26f_H9OU5PZQEq37lEKy9aKY553bzGzZLNU_CBIRGUWA_9_QbE-a0WgQz284pvZY2-Voc83pjQc2h9iMUIzap8At--sCEdhJXyO6sXw?width=660&amp;amp;height=497&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:800; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Empty Project"&gt;
&lt;ol start="6"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you haven't already, install the DartVS extension by hitting &lt;code&gt;Ctrl-Shift-X&lt;/code&gt; (the keyboard shortcut for "View-&amp;gt;Extensions") and type Dart in the search box. This should show the "Dart Code" extension by "Danny Tuppeny". Click install and reload the window when complete.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As we haven't elected to add the Dart SDK to the path, we need to tell the Dart extension where it can find the SDK. This is done by editing the User Settings (&lt;code&gt;File-&amp;gt;Preferences-&amp;gt;User Settings&lt;/code&gt;) and adding the following settings:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;    "dart.sdkPath": "C:\\Apps\\dart-sdk",
    "dart.debugSdkLibraries": false,
    "dart.debugExternalLibraries": false
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;ol start="8"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Back in the Explorer view (&lt;code&gt;Ctrl-Shift-E&lt;/code&gt;) add a new file to the &lt;code&gt;web&lt;/code&gt; directory named &lt;code&gt;main.dart&lt;/code&gt;. We'll populate this file shortly but, for now, it's just so that VSC (and DartVS) realises that this is a Dart project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add another new file named &lt;code&gt;pubspec.yaml&lt;/code&gt; to the root directory. This file tells the Dart compiler (named &lt;code&gt;Pub&lt;/code&gt;) how to build your Dart project and follows a very &lt;a href="https://www.dartlang.org/tools/pub/pubspec"&gt;simply format&lt;/a&gt;. In this file add &lt;code&gt;name&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;dependencies&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;transformers&lt;/code&gt; as shown below:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;name: GettingStartedWithDart
dependencies:
transformers:
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;ol start="10"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you save this file, you should see the &lt;code&gt;Output&lt;/code&gt; panel appear showing the output of the &lt;code&gt;Pub&lt;/code&gt; command. This is a feature of the DartVS extension which runs a &lt;code&gt;pub get&lt;/code&gt; command whenever you save the &lt;code&gt;pubspec.yaml&lt;/code&gt; file. As you can probably guess from the output (shown below) the purpose of this command is to retrieve/update any dependencies you've declared in the &lt;code&gt;dependencies&lt;/code&gt; section. Also, once the &lt;code&gt;pub get&lt;/code&gt; command has run, you should see a new &lt;code&gt;pubspec.lock&lt;/code&gt; file appear in the root directory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;img src="https://plt5eg-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3mCavvhl_SorCHUuY_oZ01TMQ9jkjpMy_I48Eotp3TlC5s-TRU0JaznDIYoihtHpfFj6A3Aqwu9eEKDhOQaK7jnEO7g6UscYBqeBp5yLg_PnzxGgWQpVTwgrxkJeOw8EUet6KhgGEn2Lkm3IYfP4-K-SEXXvKT4G64DcweiAsnQ-k?width=660&amp;amp;height=497&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:800; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Get Dependencies"&gt;
&lt;ol start="11"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As we're focusing on using Dart for web development, we'll also add an HTML document we'll manipulate using Dart. To do this, simply add new file named &lt;code&gt;index.html&lt;/code&gt; to the &lt;code&gt;web&lt;/code&gt; directory and populate it with the following:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;html&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;head&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;title&amp;gt;Getting Started With Dart&amp;lt;/title&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;script type="application/dart" src="main.dart"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/head&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;body&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;h1 id="header"&amp;gt;Hmm... what should I say?&amp;lt;/h1&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;ol start="12"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At this point you should have the following layout in your project and we're ready start start writing some Dart.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;    [Source Directory]
    |-&amp;gt; [Project Name] (i.e. "GettingStartedWithDart")
    | | -&amp;gt; lib
    | | -&amp;gt; web
    | | | -&amp;gt; index.html
    | | | -&amp;gt; main.dart
    | | -&amp;gt; pubspec.lock
    | | -&amp;gt; pubspec.yaml
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;ol start="13"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the &lt;code&gt;main.dart&lt;/code&gt; file, add the following code. (Note, if you type this code rather than copy-pasting it, you'll notice the excellent intellisense features provided by VSC and implemented beautifully by Dart VS.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;import 'dart:html';

void main() {
  querySelector('#header').text = 'Ah yes... Hello World!!!';
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;ol start="14"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Right, now we have an HTML file and some Dart code and we're ready to run. While you could run this code manually from the command line, if you're intending on doing more than just this getting started guide, I'd very much recommend setting up some task runners in VSC. This is done by opening the command palette (&lt;code&gt;Ctrl-Shift-P&lt;/code&gt;) and typing &lt;code&gt;Configure Task Runner&lt;/code&gt;, which should show you the command &lt;code&gt;Tasks: Configure Task Runner&lt;/code&gt;. Select this and you will see a list of build systems VSC can automatically create a task runner for (shown below). As Dart isn't one of the predefined templates, select "Others" to create an empty Tasks file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;img src="https://plt4eg-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3mjQOmP0yb0-3KfLb34MamSLnq13qKN0jSNcEHLMIOn7u2kbunZuaN74mec-0mquSOr05it5RZC6Uov1rnpiweb1sL6a96iKFJYLWC_6hSlldbQjHriAKAa71-k_8Dop-6iLRxL38BNzOMqii4VNZVfIlFgV_Ow2hG1GtMwXjB7A4?width=660&amp;amp;height=497&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:800; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Configure Task Runner"&gt;
&lt;ol start="15"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This command should create a new file called &lt;code&gt;tasks.json&lt;/code&gt; in a new &lt;code&gt;.vscode&lt;/code&gt; directory and will contain the following json.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;{
    // See https://go.microsoft.com/fwlink/?LinkId=733558
    // for the documentation about the tasks.json format
    "version": "0.1.0",
    "command": "echo",
    "isShellCommand": true,
    "args": ["Hello World"],
    "showOutput": "always"
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;ol start="16"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you're not familiar with configuring VSC task runners, I'd very much recommend clicking the link in this file to see what the task runner is able to do and how to configure it. However, for your convenience, I have provided my configuration below:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;{
    // See https://go.microsoft.com/fwlink/?LinkId=733558
    // for the documentation about the tasks.json format
    "version": "0.1.0",
    "command": "C:\\Apps\\dart-sdk\\bin\\pub.bat",
    "isShellCommand": true,
    "args": [],
    "showOutput": "always",
    "echoCommand": true,
    "tasks": [
        {
            "taskName": "build",
            "args": [],
            "isWatching": false
         },
        {
            "taskName": "serve",
            "args": [],
            "isWatching": true
         }
    ]
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;ol start="17"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;As you will probably be able to determine, this file contains two tasks; one named &lt;code&gt;build&lt;/code&gt; and the other named &lt;code&gt;serve&lt;/code&gt;. The &lt;code&gt;build&lt;/code&gt; command compiles your code and checks for errors while the &lt;code&gt;serve&lt;/code&gt; command sets up a local web-server (by default bound to port 8080) capable of serving the content of the &lt;code&gt;web&lt;/code&gt; directory. Lets try both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Open the command palette (&lt;code&gt;Ctrl-Shift-P&lt;/code&gt;), delete the '&amp;gt;' prompt and then type &lt;code&gt;task&lt;/code&gt; followed by a space. You should see the two tasks defined above appear. Continue to &lt;code&gt;build&lt;/code&gt; and then hit return. At this point, the output pane should appear displaying the &lt;code&gt;Tasks&lt;/code&gt; output and your code should be compiled (and, transpiled into JS!). This is shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;img src="https://plt3eg-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3ma_gmHNRQHH3HaNTz8ytRLamtMwlzmi0dRSYl1aqncp0Zy-RaUW_qLGOebg_PpgRdCoYLQYFcuRWZ3FC_Y6jJ0Qw6n5rWbGxvUMzi5_yqitbOf3DrJUVAkQi9Th0JvQmzLysrJGrnhrVe7Z2eYY6uUse_0o88veVTn8eYaIZsHnw?width=660&amp;amp;height=497&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:800; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Tasks and Build output"&gt;
&lt;ol start="19"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If everything is successful, you should see the message '&lt;code&gt;Built 2 files to "build"&lt;/code&gt;'. Now we can test our Dart code by serving it through &lt;code&gt;pub server&lt;/code&gt;. To do this, start the &lt;code&gt;task serve&lt;/code&gt; task in a similar manner to the &lt;code&gt;task build&lt;/code&gt; above. As this task is an &lt;code&gt;isWatching&lt;/code&gt; command, the task won't complete when run but will emit messages to the output pane when changes occur. This is shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;With a local web-server serving out HTML file and Dart code, we can finally start to use Dartium to run the code. Note that, we're using Dartium because we'll be executing the Dart code directly (rather than the transpiled JavaScript) and Dartium has a built-in Dart runtime which allows for advanced debugging of our Dart code. Start Dartium but executing it from either command line or GUI (exists at &lt;code&gt;C:\Apps\chromium\chrome.exe&lt;/code&gt; for me) and, once started, navigate to &lt;code&gt;http://localhost:8080&lt;/code&gt; and you should see the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;img src="https://nbtqeg-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3m2wj9PACazah5vdBUyW8AOGu__v3AbjHyzU66QtsvCuHVA4Ya710e4bjVJv4GdNiXlige7q8waQcphwiH8FtLZG8eu-z7cOiBPi-vqx8KfgkYPvwVrtPIpJoCmdIDR8LmO8DIqkHSvNe6Kz5q65IoWi1DRivqqpX5YUET_9zEmS4?width=660&amp;amp;height=542&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:800; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Success!!"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congratulations, you've just run your first Dart code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If something went wrong and you don't see the header text change from 'Hmm... what should I say?' to 'Ah yes... Hello World!!!' then you can use Dartium's Developer Tools (&lt;code&gt;Ctrl-Shift-I&lt;/code&gt;) to view errors and add breakpoints so you can work out what has gone wrong. The developer tools are shown here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://nbtpeg-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3my4JbT3bsQcqBOB3NANuaB-FMf_vBHNlAc1qm5QaXuFVEWxIV1YuoIj7gu-QJZtFOgS_gHJBknLl8J_LY9shZ_YtYf8Jf0BL9T0r4NMf3dv5XXvZt0x_J0IqZ7lurmX5MJP7oyA9FMO8oMkm29BAxoQI2jV-s6dyO2APv8dvXRTM?width=660&amp;amp;height=542&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:800; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Dartium Developer Tools"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find loads more information online about the &lt;a href="https://www.dartlang.org/"&gt;Dart Language&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://webdev.dartlang.org/"&gt;Dart Web Development&lt;/a&gt;. Versions of Dart are changing rapidly (there was a minor update while writing this post!) and a thriving &lt;a href="https://www.dartlang.org/community"&gt;support community&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a (mainly) C# developer I found Dart super easy to get up to speed with and the Visual Studio Code/Dartium combo to be extremely productive. Hopefully you will too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have fun.&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;Visual Studio Code is rapidly becoming my go-to editor for anything not project-oriented C#/F#. I've switched from &lt;a href="https://atom.io/"&gt;Atom&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href="(https://code.visualstudio.com/)"&gt;VSC&lt;/a&gt; for editing my (&lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/NewBlogUsingWyam"&gt;statically-generated, Markdown driven&lt;/a&gt;) blog and have used it for authoring powershell scripts, dockerfiles and much, much more. So, when I decided I wanted to write some &lt;a href="https://www.dartlang.org/"&gt;Dart&lt;/a&gt; code, it was the obvious choice.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<link href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/ToddlerBoxReleasedToStore" />
		<link rel="enclosure" type="image" href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/y3mVAxtKFjUEGk7Hdhzjl4UZ2INnFdBbw9K-tnYZ8DYoJ-VoKxpAN6w8Ng0DFTYdSxpHY6IvL5-VwJpLkQl6qWRmMQXSExLXopz5CFuSxIbyaMLrnL2Vy3yPZlISAAknXZdT4HwiZJ55zg2UtKwucBL88-xHh6rn5Mh97yzfRsCPjI%253Fwidth=1919&amp;height=1075&amp;cropmode=none" />
		<id>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/ToddlerBoxReleasedToStore</id>
		<title>ToddlerBox Released to the XBox Store</title>
		<updated>2016-11-16T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<content>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;My little girl loves playing with the XBox controller. In fact, she'll make a beeline for it as soon as she sees it and sit for ages twiddling the thumb-sticks and mashing the buttons. So I thought it'd be great to provide some visual accompaniment to the tactile experience of playing with the controller. Furthermore, I'd been looking for an excuse to play with Win2D as part of a UWP app and this felt like a perfect opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To this end, I cracked open Visual Studio, started a blank UWP app, added a nuget reference to Win2D and started coding. Using a &lt;a href="https://microsoft.github.io/Win2D/html/T_Microsoft_Graphics_Canvas_UI_Xaml_CanvasAnimatedControl.htm"&gt;CanvasAnimatedControl&lt;/a&gt; it was simple to use the &lt;a href="https://microsoft.github.io/Win2D/html/E_Microsoft_Graphics_Canvas_UI_Xaml_CanvasAnimatedControl_Update.htm"&gt;Update&lt;/a&gt; callback to read the &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/apps/windows.gaming.input.gamepad"&gt;Gamepad&lt;/a&gt; input and then use the &lt;a href="https://microsoft.github.io/Win2D/html/E_Microsoft_Graphics_Canvas_UI_Xaml_CanvasAnimatedControl_Draw.htm"&gt;Draw&lt;/a&gt; callback to draw a series of sprites based on the values read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in, from not having used Win2D before, it took just a few hours to get a minimal app working with a variety of sprites and manipulation mechanisms. Flipping my &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-gb/windows/uwp/xbox-apps/devkit-activation"&gt;XBox into developer mode&lt;/a&gt; allowed me to deploy the app directly to the Xbox and have a play. And I must say, I was very pleased with the result:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://zphxkg.dm2302.livefilestore.com/y3mynwGeO7sZByGMtgH7TP5ykDeabNNlbyLCFHZfLu2Ml9QbQft2wq6-MeIxMukEXnVpiqZfLa_lh7h15xlStRf8Eo81_y5J-zSplYIIDh5dKAkS-j2q2wS4-GUHpOpwW5eltQ8_CLhSQNoRRJwdZWs_AhjvxhhOMdCS5PB-stLlTE?width=1024&amp;amp;height=575&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:320px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Lots of animals"&gt;
&lt;h6 style="text-align: center;" markdown="1"&gt;Lots of animals&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;img src="https://zphykg.dm2302.livefilestore.com/y3mVAxtKFjUEGk7Hdhzjl4UZ2INnFdBbw9K-tnYZ8DYoJ-VoKxpAN6w8Ng0DFTYdSxpHY6IvL5-VwJpLkQl6qWRmMQXSExLXopz5CFuSxIbyaMLrnL2Vy3yPZlISAAknXZdT4HwiZJ55zg2UtKwucBL88-xHh6rn5Mh97yzfRsCPjI?width=1024&amp;amp;height=574&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:320px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Lots of colours"&gt;
&lt;h6 style="text-align: center;" markdown="1"&gt;Lots of colours&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;img src="https://zphwkg.dm2302.livefilestore.com/y3m8XFQkqAgfzj1Yt9EqXW14XVybPwILZ0Hn_yGK2sbayqyeGZVqwSOGpT_xAJS3WwzYFeyQ4Gw66Fa-QyRpM71WpPUktEfgvgteIKAXfp9qCSW_my9s-7kb4Ys7Qz1JYRHv-k8fl1Y8xTTDpLhfY5xG2m56hT_ObFWrKxFhV-N-lw?width=1024&amp;amp;height=575&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:320px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Big..."&gt;
&lt;h6 style="text-align: center;" markdown="1"&gt;Big...&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;img src="https://zphvkg.dm2302.livefilestore.com/y3mN4YESAkR1YSr8YbSDJtqi2DGD20bBa_w5RR2cYyAm9aXKXxib1A65RnVBxraAGCEXRELh0QMYDSASbm7F8ADzvh7EizJXlz-odd9Vhvq0ccfd0yNyL4v1f2qex5ol96GP6qvxE35Fo1L-hdlu9cfo08lDWZielw6ffr-vZ92aYE?width=1024&amp;amp;height=575&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:320px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="...or small"&gt;
&lt;h6 style="text-align: center;" markdown="1"&gt;...or small&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;img src="https://zphukg.dm2302.livefilestore.com/y3mcH_fRNs467C1gL7rApW6mWiFYB-eCoUexIuW3CwX4Cb0seAy8IxNhjyiGFQx3jDrcB8ToLQJgekRDInIwMkMHQvVZ05vWCPrptx2vxkcu-KG40ldNAqOZu2ulyL7OPSGt7uuFNnZLOdtycCFVs3Tl5IWJltKR6uhEgxNW_j-4tI?width=1024&amp;amp;height=575&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:320px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="And monkeys!!!"&gt;
&lt;h6 style="text-align: center;" markdown="1"&gt;And monkeys!!!!&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real test came when I handed to the controller to my 14 month old baby girl. It took a few seconds for her to realise that what she did on the controller affected what was displayed on screen but then there was no stopping her. For three or four minutes (a record for her!!!) she sat still, mashing away on the controller and staring at the screen while I sat mesmerized by how quickly she picked it all up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd call that a win!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given this success, I made some final touches and submitted it to the store; specifically for XBox. To my amazement, it passed certification first time, within 24 hours of submission despite submitting it on a Sunday. And here it is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://1y8kkg.dm2302.livefilestore.com/y3mRbMDxeVB6f5ArIwJ6FjYCPRmwpPTp6LL2IGiIFOrFVgHzox_2HUl9lPNSq09KxXP5M3LD1E3nwgFi1a8HUCT-0dTH_VmemTLCQwHggxqy8u04C85i51eLPBj1op_n2ppnjK2zkhGDHcWWAyYvkncmNy4bqw58vumGP8BY4f9nZU?width=1024&amp;amp;height=576&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:800px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="ToddlerBox in the store"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Installing from the store and ready to entertain my little one whenever I need a break.&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;My little girl loves playing with the XBox controller. In fact, she'll make a beeline for it as soon as she sees it and sit for ages twiddling the thumb-sticks and mashing the buttons. So I thought it'd be great to provide some visual accompaniment to the tactile experience of playing with the controller. Furthermore, I'd been looking for an excuse to play with Win2D as part of a UWP app and this felt like a perfect opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<link href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/ToddlerBoxTopsTenThousandUsers" />
		<link rel="enclosure" type="image" href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/y3mVAxtKFjUEGk7Hdhzjl4UZ2INnFdBbw9K-tnYZ8DYoJ-VoKxpAN6w8Ng0DFTYdSxpHY6IvL5-VwJpLkQl6qWRmMQXSExLXopz5CFuSxIbyaMLrnL2Vy3yPZlISAAknXZdT4HwiZJ55zg2UtKwucBL88-xHh6rn5Mh97yzfRsCPjI%253Fwidth=1024&amp;height=574&amp;cropmode=none" />
		<id>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/ToddlerBoxTopsTenThousandUsers</id>
		<title>ToddlerBox Tops 10,000 Users!!</title>
		<updated>2016-12-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<content>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;Really that got out of hand fast! I had no idea so many people would be interested in letting their toddler loose on their XBox controller. In fact, there have been many things that have surprised me about this app:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Acquisition rate has increased&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I kind of expected an initial burst of acquisitions then a slow tail off but this hasn't happened. As it's only been a little over a month since ToddlerBox was released to the store, I guess there's every possibility that it's still in the "burst" stage and theres just more interest in apps of this type. Well, here's hoping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reviews have been extremely polarized&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost without exception, reviews have been 4-5 stars or 1 star. Also, while a couple of the 1 star ratings are to do with app functionality (it seems a couple of people have issues running even this basic UWP app) the overwhelming majority of 1 star ratings are due to peoples dislike of ads; because...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ads are a very risky business&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with most parents, I am extremely cautious about what my toddler is exposed to. Therefore I was extremely cautious about adding advertising as a means of revenue to ToddlerBox, regardless of how small or out of the way they were.
After completing the Ad-Mediation questions in the Windows Store and being assured that ads would be both age rated and not "tracking", I felt a lot better about the idea and decided a small banner ad on the instructions screen would be pretty harmless. Furthermore, throughout the process of adding the banner, I didn't see a single advert I would be concerned about putting in front of my child; most were simple flashing inbox icons or the like.
However, after discussing ToddlerBox with a friend, he decided to install it on his Xbox and I was very upset to see that the ads being displayed were both more intrusive and more "click-baity" than any I had seen previously. I am now investigating ways to generate some revenue from the app but without upsetting parents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The reviews shown in the store are not "all reviews"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the publisher of ToddlerBox, I get to see all reviews left about the app on the store. Due to all the previous points, the app is currently averaging about a 2.6 star rating across 50 odd reviews. However, when viewing the app in the Store on my friend's XBox, it was shown as having a 4.5 star rating from just 2 reviews. Now, while some of the reviews I can see are translated from foreign languages, most are in English and I'm therefore at a loss to explain why they're not being displayed when an XBox in the English local browses the store.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It's not just toddlers using ToddlerBox&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've had more than one review stating how good this game is to play after consuming various illicit substances ;0P&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, as described above, while acquisition rate has fluctuated on a daily basis, the overall trend in acquisition shows unexpected growth:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://bnljqq-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3msqT1msmkJ_32Jewx8Ysuoys0lC35GCLY-aQPyJ9YhR75KMswOLcznSPGOOBGhhsMRb6qK3_xh_qr3h1Xh-vFwmSog1_HoOS-Isj1lMoFPpuV42oAwJi3A5JiY-ToAirVoZDnz2gQ7N6jUed82zW83IZ_qQcbqWGw1ekaNh4wjBU?width=660&amp;amp;height=252&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:660px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Acquisitions over App Lifetime"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daily usage also shows that a healthy number of acquisitions are being used regularly, with nearly 800 people using ToddlerBox nearly 1700 times just yesterday (19th December):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://bnlkqq-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3mBC-i0nboWq0ibRyIcBhs1O2MnfOUx-OxTQZDUNHbh-eVRbfH0xP9-p9hLJqC82i1SBB5ZfpcfmTlvuZwMBD-Gt0BZZC-IvVCJOd1jzexDoiC-BV4LG7X2aOyOapkCKK6wM6WWffluiuD5MKKet6MfEIjTWNZMCpFx1FP13suiCY?width=660&amp;amp;height=249&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:660px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Daily usage"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the Xmas break is almost upon us and I will be returning my attention to ToddlerBox (yes, despite the career break, I try to spend most of my time working on 'serious' projects or study). I have a number of new features in mind for it (including the #1 requested feature of "sound!!") and will be looking to try out a couple of more features of the awesome Win2D library. It's going to be a lot of fun (for me and my little girl) and will hopefully allow ToddlerBox to reach the next major (although admittedly arbitrary) milestone of 25,000 acquisitions!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch this space...&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;Really that got out of hand fast! I had no idea so many people would be interested in letting their toddler loose on their XBox controller. In fact, there have been many things that have surprised me about this app:&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<link href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/HomeNetworkMonitoring-PartIII" />
		<id>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/HomeNetworkMonitoring-PartIII</id>
		<title>Home Network Monitoring - Part III</title>
		<updated>2016-04-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<content>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;In the last post, I configured Logstash to extracted source and destination address information from the "Client Access Log" Syslog messages sent by my router and added a number of visualizations to my Kibana dashboard which allow me to explore which local devices are access which remote servers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this is already very useful, it's almost impossible to remember which devices relate to which IP addresses on the local network, let alone the on the internet. As such, I really want the ability to translate the IP addresses (and, ideally, port numbers) into device, host or protocol names.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;translating remote ip addresses to host names&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a local device accesses a remote server it will, ordinarily, do so by resolving an IP address for a host name, for example 'google.com' resolves to the address '216.58.213.110'. On my network, my router acts as a DNS server, resolving names it knows and forwarding unresolved names to Googles DNS servers. A the results of the host name to IP address lookup are cached in the DNS server (e.g. my router) I can perform a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reverse_DNS_lookup"&gt;reverse DNS lookup&lt;/a&gt; at very little processing cost and without consuming any WAN bandwidth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual, Logstash comes with a filter that is able to perform this operation called, unsurprisingly, 'dns'. However, to provide a consistent set of fields to Kibana, it requires a couple of additional steps to ensure it functions consistently. Here is the amended &lt;code&gt;syslog.config&lt;/code&gt; with the reverse DNS lookup in place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;input {
  tcp {
    port =&amp;gt; 5000
    type =&amp;gt; syslog
  }
  udp {
    port =&amp;gt; 5000
    type =&amp;gt; syslog
  }
}

filter {
    grok {
        match =&amp;gt; [ "message", "&amp;lt;%{POSINT:syslog_pri}&amp;gt;%{SYSLOGTIMESTAMP:syslog_timestamp} Vigor\: Local User \(MAC=%{MAC:source_mac}\): %{IP:source_address}(?::%{POSINT:source_port})? -&amp;gt; %{IP:destination_address}(?::%{POSINT:destination_port})? \((?&amp;lt;protocol&amp;gt;TCP|UDP)\)" ]
        add_tag =&amp;gt; "access"
    }
    if "access" in [tags] {
        mutate {
            add_field =&amp;gt; {
              "destination_host" =&amp;gt; "%{[destination_address]}"
            }
        }
        dns {
            reverse =&amp;gt; [ "destination_host" ]
            action =&amp;gt; "replace"
            nameserver =&amp;gt; "192.168.1.1"
        }
    }
}

output {
  elasticsearch {
    hosts =&amp;gt; ["192.168.1.30:9200"]
    index =&amp;gt; "syslog-%{+YYYY.MM.dd}"
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that, when an 'access' message is successfully grokked, I add a tag to the tags array field of the message called "access". If another type of message has been received (i.e. a DNS lookup) then the grok pattern won't match and the 'access' tag will not be added to tags.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the &lt;code&gt;grok&lt;/code&gt; filter, I check to see if the tags field contains the 'access' tag and, if so, use the &lt;code&gt;mutate&lt;/code&gt; filter to copy the 'destination_address' field value into a 'destination_host' field. This is done as the &lt;code&gt;dns&lt;/code&gt; filter will replace the field value if a successful reverse DNS lookup is performed but will leave the original value (i.e. the IP address) if a reverse DNS could not be performed. This way we either get the host name or IP address in the 'destination_host' field and it's never empty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the changes to configuration in place, I restart Logstash. Then, in Kibana, I refresh the field list for the 'syslog-*' index, add 'destination_host' to the 'Syslog Messages' saved search, load 'Access By Destination Address' visualization and modify it to use 'destination_host' rather than the 'destination_address' field; and get the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-AccessByDestinationHostAnalysedVisualization.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Access By Destination Host Analysed Visualization"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While initially it looks promising, a quick look at the list of hosts being accessed shows something peculiar: the domain names have been split into their component parts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;analysis, mappings and templates&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason for the host names being split is because, by default, ElasticSearch performs 'analysis' on text strings. This analysis involves splitting the strings into discrete words which can be indexed more efficiently. Some strings however, for example domain names, should be treated as a single word and as such we need to prevent ElasticSearch from performing the analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How ElasticSearch treats various fields within a message can be controlled by modifying the index mapping. The current mapping for the 'syslog' index can be retrieved by a REST call to the address 'http://[ElasticSearchHost]:9200/syslog-2016.04.12/_mapping'. This returns:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;{
    "syslog-2016.04.12": {
        "mappings": {
            "syslog": {
                "properties": {
                    "@@timestamp": {
                        "type": "date",
                        "format": "strict_date_optional_time||epoch_millis"
                    },
                    "@@version": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "destination_address": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "destination_host": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "destination_port": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "host": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "message": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "protocol": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "source_address": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "source_mac": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "source_port": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "syslog_pri": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "syslog_timestamp": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "tags": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "type": {
                        "type": "string"
                    }
                }
            }
        }
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to prevent ElasticSearch from analysing the 'destination_host' field, we need to add an 'index' key with the value 'not_analyzed'. Even though things have been mostly working correctly so far, I can save quite a bit of storage and processing time by marking almost all of the string fields as 'not_analyzed'. This is shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;{
    "syslog-2016.04.12": {
        "mappings": {
            "syslog": {
                "properties": {
                    "@@timestamp": {
                        "type": "date",
                        "format": "strict_date_optional_time||epoch_millis"
                    },
                    "@@version": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "destination_address": {
                        "type": "string",
                        "index" : "not_analyzed"
                    },
                    "destination_host": {
                        "type": "string",
                        "index" : "not_analyzed"
                    },
                    "destination_port": {
                        "type": "integer"
                    },
                    "host": {
                        "type": "string",
                        "index" : "not_analyzed"
                    },
                    "message": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "protocol": {
                        "type": "string",
                        "index" : "not_analyzed"
                    },
                    "source_address": {
                        "type": "string",
                        "index" : "not_analyzed"
                    },
                    "source_mac": {
                        "type": "string",
                        "index" : "not_analyzed"
                    },
                    "source_port": {
                        "type": "integer"
                    },
                    "syslog_pri": {
                        "type": "integer"
                    },
                    "syslog_timestamp": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "tags": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "type": {
                        "type": "string"
                    }
                }
            }
        }
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, while I could write this mapping directly to the ElasticSearch index, as the index is date-based, I'd have to resend the mapping manually everyday. Instead, I am going to create a mapping template that will match an index name based on pattern and automatically apply the template. This is done by crafting a PUT call to the ElasticSearch '_template' endpoint with the specific template name. In short, the following mapping template is posted to &lt;code&gt;http://[ElasticSearch:9200]/_templates/syslog_template&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;{
        "template": "syslog-*",
        "mappings": {
            "syslog": {
                "properties": {
                    "@@timestamp": {
                        "type": "date",
                        "format": "strict_date_optional_time||epoch_millis"
                    },
                    "@@version": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "destination_address": {
                        "type": "string",
                        "index" : "not_analyzed"
                    },
                    "destination_host": {
                        "type": "string",
                        "index" : "not_analyzed"
                    },
                    "destination_port": {
                        "type": "integer"
                    },
                    "host": {
                        "type": "string",
                        "index" : "not_analyzed"
                    },
                    "message": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "protocol": {
                        "type": "string",
                        "index" : "not_analyzed"
                    },
                    "source_address": {
                        "type": "string",
                        "index" : "not_analyzed"
                    },
                    "source_mac": {
                        "type": "string",
                        "index" : "not_analyzed"
                    },
                    "source_port": {
                        "type": "integer"
                    },
                    "syslog_pri": {
                        "type": "integer"
                    },
                    "syslog_timestamp": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "tags": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "type": {
                        "type": "string"
                    }
                }
            }
        }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this in place I need to delete todays syslog index so that it is recreated, using the mapping above, when the first syslog message is received. Once this has been done, the visualization looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-AccessByDestinationHostNotAnalysedVisualization.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Access By Destination Host Not-Analysed Visualization"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nice!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I showed how to display host names for accessed servers rather than IP addresses. I also covered how to update ElasticSearch mapping such that field 'analysis' can be prevented and host names kept together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next post, I'll show how to translate local device IP addresses in to device names.&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;In the last post, I configured Logstash to extracted source and destination address information from the "Client Access Log" Syslog messages sent by my router and added a number of visualizations to my Kibana dashboard which allow me to explore which local devices are access which remote servers.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<link href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/AcheivementUnlocked" />
		<id>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/AcheivementUnlocked</id>
		<title>Achievement Unlocked!</title>
		<updated>2016-08-11T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<content>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;So, I'm currently working on a project in which I've decided to employ the &lt;a href="http://martinfowler.com/bliki/CQRS.html"&gt;CQRS&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href="http://martinfowler.com/eaaDev/EventNarrative.html"&gt;ES&lt;/a&gt; architectural combo. Given the system is event sourced, I required read models built from the domain events and, conveniently, had blogged about doing this as one of my &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/ReactiveReadModels"&gt;first posts&lt;/a&gt; on this blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was very satisfying to be able to refer back to that blog post to re-familiarize with the pattern and I must say that so far everything is working beautifully. Stay tuned for a future post on using RX to implement a CQRS/ES application in a reactive manner.&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;So, I'm currently working on a project in which I've decided to employ the &lt;a href="http://martinfowler.com/bliki/CQRS.html"&gt;CQRS&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href="http://martinfowler.com/eaaDev/EventNarrative.html"&gt;ES&lt;/a&gt; architectural combo. Given the system is event sourced, I required read models built from the domain events and, conveniently, had blogged about doing this as one of my &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/ReactiveReadModels"&gt;first posts&lt;/a&gt; on this blog.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<link href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/ASmartHome-Part1" />
		<id>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/ASmartHome-Part1</id>
		<title>A SmartHome... NoT - Part I</title>
		<updated>2018-01-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<content>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;I moved house a couple of months back to, what my partner likes to describe as, our "forever home". As such, I was keen to start looking into home monitoring / automation again as I knew things had progressed significantly since I last considered such things and I was keen to see what could be done. After lots of investigation I believe I have found the basis of a home automation solution which meets my current needs, should be extensible moving forward and which does not compromise the securty or privacy of my home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is, I hope, the first in a series that discuss the various devices and software I use to monitor and automate my home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Private by design&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly a word on privacy. While "smart devices" are everywhere nowadays, they almost all require connection to the internet and, often, a subscription to a "cloud" service. I wrote about &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/MonsterPi"&gt;this before&lt;/a&gt; and expressed my desire for smart devices to "drop the 'Inter' from IoT and expand the 'net' to become a 'Network of Things', or NoT" which could optionally be bridged to the internet if desired. To quote myself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've long loved the idea of home automation. From X10 and LightwaveRF through to modern Bluetooth and Wifi connected devices, I have played with dozens of technologies in search of home automation nirvana. But recently I have watched with growing bewilderment at the incredible number of "cloud-connected" home automation devices being released and the eagerness with which they're snapped up by naive consumers hungry to control everything from the carefree comfort of their iPhone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You see, while you can buy a myriad of IoT devices off the shelf nowadays, they nearly all come with some form of "cloud-service" that is necessary in order for the device to work as sold. As the more wily of reader will no doubt be aware, this exposes your home network to innumerable &lt;a href="https://it.slashdot.org/story/16/10/03/1359200/source-code-for-iot-botnet-mirai-which-took-down-krebs-on-security-website-with-ddos-attack-released"&gt;security concerns&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://it.slashdot.org/story/16/08/08/1449221/hackers-make-the-first-ever-ransomware-for-smart-thermostats"&gt;potential abuses&lt;/a&gt; and an &lt;a href="https://tech.slashdot.org/story/16/01/14/1347243/nest-thermostat-bug-leaves-owners-without-heating"&gt;external point of failure&lt;/a&gt; that cannot be closed/fixed without sacrificing some or all of the functionality of the new fangled device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I wrote post, the market for internet connected home automation devices has exploded... as have the concerns around the &lt;a href="(https://gizmodo.com/amazon-agrees-to-hand-over-data-in-echo-murder-case-1793039360)"&gt;privacy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.bleepingcomputer.com/news/government/germany-preparing-law-for-backdoors-in-any-type-of-modern-device/"&gt;security&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://torrentfreak.com/piracy-notices-can-mess-with-your-thermostat-isp-warns-171224/"&gt;functionality&lt;/a&gt; (or &lt;a href="https://gizmodo.com/yes-your-amazon-echo-is-an-ad-machine-1821712916"&gt;unwanted functionality&lt;/a&gt;) of the devices. I am &lt;a href="http://uk.businessinsider.com/consumers-holding-off-on-smart-home-gadgets-thanks-to-privacy-fears-2017-11?r=US&amp;amp;IR=T"&gt;not alone&lt;/a&gt; in being sufficiently concerned by these issues that I choose the devices I allow on my home network very carefully and &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/tags/monitoring"&gt;monitor them closely&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, the list of "off-the-shelf" devices I would feel comfortable having on my home network is very short and, until recently, I was resigned to having to build these devices myself using &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Single-board_computer"&gt;single board computers&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ESP8266"&gt;Wifi connected microcontrollers&lt;/a&gt;. That is until a family of devices came to my attention that originated from the most unlikely of places...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Mi Smart Home&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China isn't the first country that comes to mind when you think about privacy yet, with the release of the &lt;a href="https://xiaomi-mi.com/mi-smart-home/"&gt;"Mi Smart Home"&lt;/a&gt; family of devices, the Chinese electronics manufacturer &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Xiaomi"&gt;Xiaomi Inc&lt;/a&gt; seems to have delivered a smart-device eco-system that is privacy-friendly... albeit somewhat tacitly as we will see below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Mi Smart family consists of a number of small, battery powered Zigbee devices such as &lt;a href="https://xiaomi-mi.com/sockets-and-sensors/xiaomi-mi-temperature-humidity-sensor/"&gt;temperature and humidity sensors&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://xiaomi-mi.com/sockets-and-sensors/xiaomi-mi-door-window-sensors/"&gt;door / window sensors&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://xiaomi-mi.com/sockets-and-sensors/xiaomi-mi-occupancy-sensor/"&gt;movement sensors&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.gearbest.com/alarm-systems/pp_610096.html"&gt;various switches&lt;/a&gt;. Oh... and a curious &lt;a href="https://xiaomi-mi.com/sockets-and-sensors/xiaomi-mi-smart-home-cube-white/"&gt;'cube' controller&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These devices connect to your internal Wifi network via a &lt;a href="https://xiaomi-mi.com/mi-smart-home/xiaomi-mi-gateway-2/"&gt;Gateway device&lt;/a&gt;. In addition to providing the Zigbee to Wifi bridge, this gateway also provides an ambient light sensor, a very useful RGB light and a umm... not so useful speaker. This is all packaged in a small, round, 30 gram device about 8 centimeters in diameter and 3 cenitmeters deep. Frustratingly the gateway only comes with the Chinese/Australian type I plug so you need an adapter to use it in the UK which adds significantly to the depth (although I've taken to using a &lt;a href="https://www.gearbest.com/plugs-sockets/pp_1168562.html"&gt;convenient extension lead&lt;/a&gt; instead).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To set up the Wifi Gateway device and add sensors, you have to install the &lt;a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.xiaomi.smarthome&amp;amp;hl=en_GB"&gt;Xiaomi Mi Home app&lt;/a&gt; which, to be frank, is a privacy nightmare. The list of permissions it needs is quite incredible:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Version 5.1.1 can access:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Device &amp;amp; app history
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;retrieve running apps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identity
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;find accounts on the device&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;add or remove accounts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Calendar
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;read calendar events plus confidential information&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;add or modify calendar events and send emails to guests without owners' knowledge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contacts
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;find accounts on the device&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;read your contacts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;modify your contacts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Location
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;approximate location (network-based)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;precise location (GPS and network-based)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SMS
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;read your text messages (SMS or MMS)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;receive text messages (SMS)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;send SMS messages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Phone
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;directly call phone numbers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reroute outgoing calls&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;read call log&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;read phone status and identity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;write call log&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Photos / Media / Files
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;read the contents of your USB storage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;modify or delete the contents of your USB storage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Storage
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;read the contents of your USB storage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;modify or delete the contents of your USB storage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Camera
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;take pictures and videos&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Microphone
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;record audio&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wi-Fi connection information
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;view Wi-Fi connections&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Device ID &amp;amp; call information
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;read phone status and identity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Other
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;download files without notification&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;interact across users&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;full licence to interact across users&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;transmit infrared&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;modify secure system settings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;read Home settings and shortcuts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;write Home settings and shortcuts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;view network connections&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;create accounts and set passwords&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;read battery statistics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pair with Bluetooth devices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;access Bluetooth settings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;send sticky broadcast&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;change network connectivity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;allow Wi-Fi Multicast reception&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;connect and disconnect from Wi-Fi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;disable your screen lock&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;control flashlight&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;full network access&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;change your audio settings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;control Near-Field Communication&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;read sync settings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;run at startup&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;draw over other apps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;use accounts on the device&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;control vibration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;prevent device from sleeping&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;modify system settings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;toggle sync on and off&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;install shortcuts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;uninstall shortcuts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scary huh! How can I possibly claim these devices are privacy friendly when you've basically just given a Chinese company permission to do pretty much anything it likes with your phone's hardware and data? Well, notice how I said you need the app to "set up the Wifi Gateway device and add sensors". Once they're setup you no longer need the app and, furthermore, once "local network functions" are enabled (more on this in a second) neither the gateway nor sensors need internet access to function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, how to go about using these sensors in a privacy friendly way?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Preparation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get set up with these devices without compromising your privacy, you will need:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A dedicated VLAN and Wifi network for "smart home" devices&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recommend putting any 3rd party "smart" devices in an isolated environment within which you can easily enable or disable internet access. To do this I am using the VLAN feature of my Draytek 2860 router which involves  creating a second VLAN on my network, enabling "Inter-LAN' routing so I could access the VLAN from my existing subnet and, finally, adding firewall rules to prevent devices on this VLAN from accessing the internet / other vlans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A clean Android device&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had an old Android phone laying around on which I performed a hard-reset and wiped all user-data. With a clean device I could then install the app without worrying about sharing anything private with Xiaomi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Installation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, install the Xiaomi Mi Home app on your clean Android device. On first run after installation you will be prompted for a region and asked to sign in. In order to use all the Mi Smart devices, you &lt;strong&gt;must&lt;/strong&gt; select "Mainland China" for your region (this doesn't affect the language in the app) following which you can just create a new account to sign in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the app is installed you can plug in a gateway. This results in a nice flashing yellow ring of light around the device... and a harsh female voice babbling Chinese at an almost intolerable volume;  basically an audio and visual indication that the gateway is in "pairing" mode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go ahead and pair the gateway to the app following the walk-through &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nkFF284OFRE"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. At this point it's a good idea to also install any additional "sub devices" you have (i.e. the various Zigbee sensors) which can be done by following &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TiAgeg5P1T4"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; walkthrough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, in order to use the gateway and sensors without the app and/or internet access, it is necessary to enable "local network functions". This can be done from the app by following the instructions &lt;a href="https://www.domoticz.com/wiki/Xiaomi_Gateway_(Aqara)"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Quite why Xiaomi decided to hide what its possible the killer feature of these devices behind a "secret" button I've no idea... fortunately it's an open secret and Xiaomi don't seem to be making any effort to conceal it further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all the above done, feel free to junk the app and disable internet access from the "smart device" subnet / ip range.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Usage&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once 'local network functions' have been enabled, each Gateway uses the multicast address &lt;code&gt;224.0.0.50&lt;/code&gt; to broadcast UDP messages on port &lt;code&gt;9898&lt;/code&gt; from the gateway and sub-devices. The gateway publishes a "heartbeat" messages every 10-15 seconds or so meaning you can easily determine everything is working by spinning up Wireshark (on a device connected to the "smart device" subnet) filtering out anything that isn't a UDP message (&lt;code&gt;ip.proto == "udp"&lt;/code&gt;) and looking for messages from the gateway IP address. You should eventually see something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/posts/Heartbeat.png" alt="Wireshark Heartbeat capture" class="img-responsive" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; margin-top: 4px; margin-bottom: 4px"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you can see these messages you can start interacting with the gateway and devices using various commands. For example, to get a list of the sub-devices from a gateway you can send a 'get_id_list' command using a UDP packet container this string (as ASCII encoded binary) to the gateway's IP address, again on port &lt;code&gt;9898&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;{"cmd":"get_id_list"}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will result in a &lt;code&gt;get_id_list_ack&lt;/code&gt; response containing a list of &lt;code&gt;sid&lt;/code&gt; (aka 'simple' id) values for devices registered with the gateway (including the gateway sensor/status itself)  as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;{"cmd":"get_id_list_ack","sid":"7811dcb06972","token":"L0DI4IiFAvAgInyL","data":"[\"158d0001a200f5\",\"158d0001c1cdfb\"]"}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You're then able to retrieve the device status using the &lt;code&gt;read&lt;/code&gt; command for each &lt;code&gt;sid&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;{"cmd":"read","sid":"7811dcb06972"}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which will return a &lt;code&gt;read_ack&lt;/code&gt; response containing device specific information in the 'data' property. For example, if you send a &lt;code&gt;read&lt;/code&gt; command specifying the &lt;code&gt;sid&lt;/code&gt; of the gateway you will receive something like the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;{"cmd":"read_ack","model":"gateway","sid":"7811dcb06972","short_id":0,"data":"{\"rgb\":0,\"illumination\":1292,\"proto_version\":\"1.0.9\"}"}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, when the status of a sensor changes (for example a door sensor opens or closes) a &lt;code&gt;report&lt;/code&gt; message is broadcast as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;{"cmd":"report","model":"magnet","sid":"158d0001c1cdfb","short_id":56258,"data":"{\"status\":\"open\"}"}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Here's one I made earlier...&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used the above information to create a small application for listening to and interacting with the gateway and devices. Mostly out of interest, I used &lt;a href="https://dotnet.github.io/orleans/"&gt;Microsoft's Orleans framework&lt;/a&gt; to create a console application which wraps up the interaction with various devices into strongly typed agents (also an agent approach seemed to nicely mirror the segregated nature of the devices themselves).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn't take this too far as I subsequently decided to use an "off-the-shelf" system for interacting with the Xiaomi devices (the subject of my next "smart home" post) but it's a decent proof-of-concept. I've published the source in a &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs/MiOrleans"&gt;repository on Github&lt;/a&gt;; feel free to have a play and drop me a line with any questions you might have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next post I'll disucss the off-the-shelf system I'm now using to privately interact with the Xiaomi devices.&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;I moved house a couple of months back to, what my partner likes to describe as, our "forever home". As such, I was keen to start looking into home monitoring / automation again as I knew things had progressed significantly since I last considered such things and I was keen to see what could be done. After lots of investigation I believe I have found the basis of a home automation solution which meets my current needs, should be extensible moving forward and which does not compromise the securty or privacy of my home.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<link href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/EndOfStreak" />
		<id>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/EndOfStreak</id>
		<title>Breaking News - Forgot to commit</title>
		<updated>2015-12-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<content>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;After 41 days of continuous commits to Github, yesterday I forgot. What's really annoying is that I actually spent a long time working yesterday but found myself battling a stupid limitation of VisualStates in UWP apps (blog post incoming) and didn't have anything finished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ho-hum. 41 days was a pretty good streak and it was inevitably going to end over the Xmas period. New Year's resolution: Beat it!&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;After 41 days of continuous commits to Github, yesterday I forgot. What's really annoying is that I actually spent a long time working yesterday but found myself battling a stupid limitation of VisualStates in UWP apps (blog post incoming) and didn't have anything finished.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<link href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/UWPCommunityToolkitv1_1" />
		<id>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/UWPCommunityToolkitv1_1</id>
		<title>UWP Community Toolkit v1.1 Released</title>
		<updated>2016-10-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<content>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;Shortly after my blog post about &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/UsingHyperlinkInMVVM"&gt;Using a Hyperlink in MVVM&lt;/a&gt; a group of developers at Microsoft collated and released the &lt;a href="https://blogs.windows.com/buildingapps/2016/08/17/introducing-the-uwp-community-toolkit/#pRVgJbZbTBMHPyGG.97"&gt;UWP Community Toolkit&lt;/a&gt;. They were actively asking for contributions and, given the self contained nature of the Hyperlink extension, it seemed like a natural fit for the toolkit so I decided to try contributing it via pull request.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The toolkit's contribution guidelines and conventions closely matched my own coding style so I had to change very little of the code in my article but did have to add XML summary blocks to each public class and members. With that done I could add the class to the &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs/UWPCommunityToolkit/tree/dev/Microsoft.Toolkit.Uwp/Helpers"&gt;Helpers folder on the dev branch of my fork of the toolkit&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://github.com/Microsoft/UWPCommunityToolkit/pull/226"&gt;issue a pull request&lt;/a&gt;. I was also asked to produce some documentation and a sample for the class which was then pulled into the document repo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest, as they say, is history. &lt;a href="https://blogs.windows.com/buildingapps/2016/10/05/announcing-uwp-community-toolkit-1-1/#1QBL3lQjtLbY537i.97"&gt;Version 1.1 of the toolkit released&lt;/a&gt; with yours truly in the &lt;a href="https://github.com/Microsoft/UWPCommunityToolkit/releases/"&gt;list of contributors&lt;/a&gt;. It's a small contribution but I really think the toolkit is a promising project and absolutely intend to contribute further in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the mean time, well done to all the maintainers of, and contributors to, the toolkit on this important milestone.&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;Shortly after my blog post about &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/UsingHyperlinkInMVVM"&gt;Using a Hyperlink in MVVM&lt;/a&gt; a group of developers at Microsoft collated and released the &lt;a href="https://blogs.windows.com/buildingapps/2016/08/17/introducing-the-uwp-community-toolkit/#pRVgJbZbTBMHPyGG.97"&gt;UWP Community Toolkit&lt;/a&gt;. They were actively asking for contributions and, given the self contained nature of the Hyperlink extension, it seemed like a natural fit for the toolkit so I decided to try contributing it via pull request.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<link href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/TheYearInReview" />
		<id>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/TheYearInReview</id>
		<title>The Year In Review</title>
		<updated>2017-01-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<content>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;Saturday morning, having realized that we had no commitments or prior engagements until the following Tuesday, my partner and I decided to go on a trip. We rapidly packed bags for ourselves and our little girl, threw them in the van and set off with no set destination other than "the south-west". We ended up staying in a small farm on Exmoor and having a terrific time walking on the moor and visiting nearby sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Other than the liberty of being able to just "get away", this weekend was notable as the previous week marked exactly one year since I left full-time employment.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in July, following an epic road-trip around Europe with my girls, I wrote &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/WotNoBlogPosts"&gt;a long blog post&lt;/a&gt; about the trip and my plans for the future. These plans centred on taking the rest of the year off as a career-break and using this time to support my family while investigating/evaluating emerging technologies in the .NET ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, six months on, it's time to look back over the last year and perform a retrospective; what went well, what could have been better and what should be changed moving forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: This is a long, detailed post with a lot of information/reflection about the previous year. As such I have published it as a MVP (Minimal Viable Post) and will iterate additional information into the post in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A Timeline&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To aid the retrospective process, I spent last week learning &lt;a href="https://www.dartlang.org/"&gt;Dart&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.pixijs.com/"&gt;Pixi.js&lt;/a&gt; in order to create a timeline visualization of the year. I'm not going to go into the process of making this visualization here as I want to focus on the retrospective, however I will be writing a "making of" follow-up post as the process was both very interesting and thoroughly enjoyable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below you can see the visualization; a timeline covering the entirity of last year and showing the various aspects of my behaviour / productivity on a day-by-day basis. In order to fit into the horizontal space available in most browsers/platforms, the timeline is scaled-down along the horizontal axis. As this obscures much of the data, the timeline was designed to allow you to use your mouse or finger to interactively zoom in and and pan across the it. Give it a go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the following sections I will discuss the various datasets displayed along with a summary of what they represent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script defer="" src="../Content/Scripts/timeline.dart.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div id="timeline"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;State&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This timeline represents my primary oocupation at any given time. From a high-level, last year can be broadly split into two halves, travelling for the first half and working for the latter. However, the detail is more telling so the timeline has been further split into seven disctinct states:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Employment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My last day of employment was Friday 15th January, 2016. I had worked at my previous company for over four years and very much enjoyed my time there. Unfortunately an &lt;a href="http://www.daedtech.com/top-heavy-department-growth/"&gt;internal power struggle&lt;/a&gt; resulted in a change of senior management and a move away the progressive development methodologes which had made the company such a great place to work. This, to me, signalled that it was time to move on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Sabatical&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I considered the couple of months following ending full time employment as a sabatical; time to reflect, get my affairs in order and spend time with my young family before  considering how to move forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this time my daughter was just 4 months old so this presented a great opportunity to support my partner and engage with my baby. Having also taken 6 weeks of &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/shared-parental-leave-and-pay/overview"&gt;Shared Parental Leave&lt;/a&gt; the previous year, this meant that, of her first six months of life, I'd been able to spend almost four with her. I feel incredibly fortunate to be in a situation where this is could be the case. The first few months of a baby's life are incredibly tough for both the parents and the baby and I'm very happy that I was able to be with my girls throughout this time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was towards the end of this period that my partner and I decided to capitalise on our unique situation and put the remainder of her maternity leave to use by taking our little girl on a road-trip around Europe. The implications of this decision were to dominate and, to a large degree, consume the entirity of the next three months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Preparation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having made the decision to spend a significant amount of time touring Europe, with an 8 month old baby no less, it became apparent that there would be a whole lot of preparation required to make this happen. In March we decided to buy a Nissan Elgrand E51 Rider Autech (shown below) and April onwards was spent preparing it for our trip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://zdfcta-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3mRDVqstf6XsjN73biGoYnN5s-SzVcHx9pEdYl2S_wM803HpiosWK5Skxm-kskeHTMkahk_PIdejAp70x14KCaOwmZb6OvAvAig8uqI4bdBs2Pb_lAUsm-O_2lO8krW_18ReDVMLXqVkJWUGUSJ-d80bOIi8ciWIgyxDzL5fw4qF4?width=1796&amp;amp;height=1347&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:800; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Nissan Elgrand E51 Rider Autech"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This preparation was complex, with numerous requirements, constraints and learning curves across a variety of disciplines... but also a whole lot of fun. On our return I wrote a &lt;a href="http://elgrandoc.uk/forum/index.php?threads/touring-europe-in-an-elgrand-part-i-to-v.3311"&gt;very long post&lt;/a&gt; for the &lt;a href="http://elgrandoc.uk/forum/index.php"&gt;Elgrand Owners Club&lt;/a&gt; which detailed all the work I had done on the van. While the post took a significant amount of time to write, the forums were invaluable in providing the information I needed to do the work in the first place so I thought it was worth investing this time in case the post helped someone else in the same manner. To this day, the post is still one of the most viewed and commented on posts in the forum. It's well worth a read a read if you have time; if not, here are some pictures of the work instead:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://mkakza-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3mTMvumgbiWf4cuNId6rdQdXFkrZEMe891yFE3uaLIn1eWi8gsAGfCe6dwKUZjSfNqkfJHNpdzXf60mJIb2RH1HlQ1ku-6IEk5IPtKNoDHcJnVFi1_AIGA-TvxRXvplxSaxmqN385ks_cd0YZ2dxxdpU3ylY7UlYPW2uP9sp8Sr9A?width=660&amp;amp;height=371&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:800; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Cargo frame"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://dotw7g-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3mAeFtD-P9o5iDeydmal4JBd-518YT4V1-WPcdo33zt8xDn7vLENvSjzaMzFf5U52ZKreB49IRMJTdoMGXtxtSsLYUdF0mPvkYh-6ts_sihIt3aWMgd2hHlmkIzm-twj54_tTlpRJm2Xi3B58mGjSM_ZxF-aAQcQq842NpEBTlOVE?width=660&amp;amp;height=371&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:800; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Electrics box"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://adlakq-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3mw8fNegXFskURlkB2qFnfOJA7BsmrmPW7hx3Xyflhqwi52YIR8NEdSqz-acBvO6cTO2X5Atjj6U2uTFjGiLhTofbHGbteqx1B1MxGWouRBLO1WF1lTUCVMLbsUJmwFy2jPKb84N9xG_-1YuOmhqovFb59UuxMYxasZ0yyVDJgAtY?width=660&amp;amp;height=371&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:800; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Electrics fitted"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://plsn1w-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3mt5MSkFV_zVYge_IQZeDn02BvYd2ngjLePZYmte7YKsEIpa-e_n6BRgS0YFM5F1fge5qaJX5aAVLsyfhxVQo11B13NwfQ1hIQy47gdIcoBCjIWPPklSUKFIG59c2SXhfEaH0_xILPK35Awxm2RTs8bWvsLtkMtNTNs4V3t4qKXSw?width=660&amp;amp;height=371&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:800; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Cargo fitted"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://mhrszq-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3m5m7EX2zp-dMeKdwNa-8RMrBapeb5hhLCpRCj8bfI277ok0RZOs7Rv3GAdXQRiTsVfE6L-skEtFtkcgoi8Nf5qo1vxuw4aSoLPyMgXr5kHtDZQ-D5Sp1Lz2_-FoBNl8Zcj9bO531eW6_WFtu_Z0SE_QiDH2CWFp_-6hFL3fljt74?width=660&amp;amp;height=371&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:800; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Cable routed"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During this time I learned a lot about carpentry, electronics and engineering... but I almost didn't. Prior to undertaking the work, I had looked to find a conversion specialist who would do the work for me but most either only provided pattern-part conversions or were too busy to undertake a bespoke project. Well, "necessity being the mother of invention", I set to it and, in retrospect, am extremely glad I did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite barely having used an electric drill previously and never having dabbled in 240v electronics, I enjoyed every aspect of the work and am immensely proud of it. We didn't experience a single issue with my work while we were away and, even if we had, it was extremely comforting knowing that I could have resolved the issue in the field if I'd had to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should a similar challenge ever present itself again, I would certainly look at taking it on and, furthermore, would encourage others to do so also as you undoubtedly &lt;a href="https://hbr.org/2016/07/if-youre-not-outside-your-comfort-zone-you-wont-learn-anything"&gt;learn a lot more when working outside of your comfort zone&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Touring Europe&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the prep done - well, as much as was possible in the time available - we left home on May 20th and didn't return again until July 17; totaling just over 8 weeks on the road. In this time we traveled &lt;strong&gt;in excess of 8000 miles and visited 22 countries&lt;/strong&gt; seeing numerous friends en-route and making many more in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it was all the prep or perhaps we were just lucky but the trip went off without a hitch and everyone - including our little girl - had an amazing time. Both &lt;a href="https://bigspune.wordpress.com/"&gt;my partner&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/WotNoBlogPosts"&gt;I&lt;/a&gt; blogged about the trip - for ourselves as much for any potential reader - and, six months on, are still reflecting on what a fantastic adventure it was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without a shadow of a doubt, and even when considering the week's of preparation before leaving, this trip was time well spent. My partner and I learned a lot about each other ("hey, we &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; spend several weeks in a confined space together, 24/7") and our daughter and have accumulated memories that will last a lifetime. We have already talked about doing another similar trip in the future and have begun planning shorter breaks around the UK as a stop-gap until an opportunity for a new adventure comes along.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Study&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon my return, I came across a code for a free &lt;a href="https://borntolearn.mslearn.net/b/weblog/posts/sign-up-to-take-the-beta-exam-for-developing-mobile-apps-70-357-today"&gt;Microsoft beta exam about mobile application development&lt;/a&gt;. As I was interested in UWP app development and had already taken loads of these beta exams in previous years, I decided to sit the exam even though the code was only valid for a few weeks after signing up, which left very little time to study!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Experiential_learning"&gt;learn&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://psycnet.apa.org/journals/bdb/17/1/1.pdf&amp;amp;productCode=pa"&gt;best&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.virgin.com/richard-branson/you-learn-by-doing-and-by-falling-over"&gt;by&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://news.uchicago.edu/article/2015/04/29/learning-doing-helps-students-perform-better-science"&gt;doing&lt;/a&gt; my study focused on writing a UWP app that incorporated as many of the &lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/learning/exam-70-357.aspx"&gt;examined technical aspects&lt;/a&gt; as possible. While the methodologies I used for this app were relatively new (i.e. CQRS/ES) the learning curve for this exam really came from some of the unique aspects of UWP app development such as designing for multiple devices/screen sizes, using &lt;a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/ef/core/"&gt;new persistence technologies&lt;/a&gt; and leveraging the huge new API surface available to UWP apps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to an awful dashboard implementation which &lt;a href="https://borntolearn.mslearn.net/b/weblog/posts/more-tips-about-beta-exams-what-to-expect-when-you-39-re-expecting-your-beta-results-that-is"&gt;causes much confusion for students who sit beta exams&lt;/a&gt;, I am still unsure as to whether I passed this exam or not. My dashboard has not changed to say I have passed the exam but I have not received a summary sheet from Microsoft with my scores nor am I able to access them from my MCP dashboard. In short, the current beta exam process is extremely poor and much worse than it was five or six years ago when I took (and passed) around a dozen such beta exams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless, time spent on this study was a huge win. I learned a lot about a platform which is becoming increasingly prevalent in the Windows ecosystem. UWP apps are able to run on everything from Raspberry Pi to Hololens, and I have since deployed/released UWP apps for Raspberry Pi, Mobile (phone/table), PC and XBox. Indeed, after completing the exam, I continued to develop my UWP study app over the next few months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Holiday&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Across the year, I allocated around 40 days (including bank-holidays and weekends) as non-work days (aka holiday). This included snowboarding with friends, trips abroad, visiting relatives and a long festive break over Xmas. Although more than the holiday allowance at most full time jobs (depending on how it's allocated), I feel this represents a fairly decent split between work and play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;OneCog.Solutions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once life had returned to normal following our tour of Europe and taking the Microsoft beta exam, I decided to work on a few projects that were interesting to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, this was continuing my investigation of UWP, initially to &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/CqrsEsMvvmRxEfSqlUwpPcl"&gt;flesh out&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/store/p/littlelittle/9nblggh51b1b"&gt;release&lt;/a&gt; the UWP app I had written while studying for the UWP exam but then to also evaluate UWP as a &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/MonsterPi"&gt;platform for IoT devices&lt;/a&gt;. I then proceeded to broaden my area of investigation into &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/DockerAndKafka"&gt;non-Microsoft technologies&lt;/a&gt; and even into areas that, while still technical, were &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/3DPrintingWithTheCelRobox"&gt;not directly involved with software development&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During this time I endeavored to keep an up-to-date public profile. Through a &lt;a href="https://trello.com/b/KoTWuFUi/public-board"&gt;public Trello board&lt;/a&gt;, products I had released (&lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-gb/store/p/littlelittle/9nblggh51b1b"&gt;LittleLittle&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-gb/store/p/toddlerbox/9nblggh3zr4l"&gt;ToddlerBox&lt;/a&gt;), posts to &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/"&gt;my blog&lt;/a&gt; and contributions to both &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs"&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/users/628821/ibebbs"&gt;StackOverflow&lt;/a&gt; I tried to make sure as much of my time as possible was surfaced publicly. Indeed, having become extremely delivery-oriented since first drinking the agile (&lt;a href="https://medium.com/swlh/agile-is-the-new-waterfall-f7baef5d026d#.jpmks6gi4"&gt;lower-case 'a'&lt;/a&gt;) kool-aid several years ago, I feel the public-facing nature of these interactions substituted as a form of delivery; or, in Agile parlance, became my &lt;a href="https://www.agilealliance.org/glossary/definition-of-done/"&gt;"definition of done"&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While, in retrospect, I had hoped to have investigated many more technologies than I actually managed during this time, overall I would consider this time well spent. In addition to releasing two applications to the Windows Store and contributing to several public Github projects (more on this later) I managed to rack up over 1000 rep on StackOverflow in just a couple of months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, during this time, I didn't achieve my primary goal; namely finding a project that could potentially be grown into a marketable product and form the basis of a company. While there were no shortage of ideas and there still remain a couple of "coals in the fire", I don't think I've yet found the gap in the market I'm looking for. One slight positive note here is that I have, at the very least, determined a couple of markets I'm very keen on investigating further and in which I'd like to work in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this visualization I have employed step count (vertical bars), weight (yellow line with dotted yellow representing ideal weight) and fat-mass (red line with dotted red representing ideal fat-mass) as a (very rough) approximation of health. While, in theory, I should have had more leisure time available to exercise over the course of the year, in real terms I found that I did far less than expected. This was due to a number of factors:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My previous employer, being a company that revolves around football, had regular football matches/tournaments between company staff which were of a very high standard. I played in as many of these as possible and, once I left, I very much missed the exercise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My commute to work each day involved a (voluntary) walk from St Pancras station to Camden Lock - and back again - every day. This constituted 30 minutes/5000 steps of valuable exercise each day that was no longer necessary when I started working from home.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I ran a football team for my village that played in the local Bedfordshire league. Unfortunately, due to lack of players this team folded at the end of last season leaving me entirely bereft of football for the majority of the year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At punching-weight, I aim to be 11st and 15% fat-mass. This used to be a fairly common occurrence while playing football regularly but, as can be seen, I've not managed to get back into a similar condition this year. Fortunately, I &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; managed to avoid devolving into a complete bucket of lard thanks to several things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Parenthood - As any parent will tell you, being a parent is both exhausting and relentless. While previously I would undertake very little exercise in the evening, nowadays I expend a significant amount of energy each evening running around after my daughter. While not often recognised, this constitutes a fairly high level of activity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Preparation for Touring Europe - During this time I did &lt;strong&gt;a lot&lt;/strong&gt; of very physical work. From lugging construction materials and tools around to disassembling and reassembling the van, the average day was extremely active, especially when compared to sitting in an office chair for eight hours.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;European Tour - as can be seen from the step count, although a great deal of time was spent driving, our time away involved a lot of other activity. This activity (particularly loading and unloading the van each day!) provided a lot of exercise and helped keep me fit over the summer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Swimming - In a desperate attempt to remain in some sort of shape, I have recently started swimming semi-regularly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In retrospect, something that came as no surprise but for which I failed to anticipate the true impact, was the effect of not exercising on my state of mind and general happiness. Having always been an active and optimistic individual, I completely underestimated the tight correlation between these two characteristics. Mid-November saw me at my least active and, as I've come to realise, my least productive/focused (as evidenced by the sudden surge in StackOverflow rep!). Fortunately I try be somewhat self-reflective and, recognising that my diminished level of activity might be a possible cause for a perceived lack of progress, I decided to start swimming again as a means to address this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, while I'm still not exercise as much as I would like, I at least feel like my activity levels are sufficient to allow me to focus on projects and achieve my deliverables. Moving forward I very much hope to re-establish the village football team in time for next season or join another team such that I get at least a couple of games a month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Finances&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In counterpoint to the Health visualization described above, the Finances visualization shows a relative interpretation of my financial health across the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of the year, when considering a career-break, I tried to calculate a monthly "burn-rate" (i.e. total out-goings per month). Given I was not planning to change my lifestyle at all and my partner and I had already planned a number of holidays, I arrived at a rough estimate of £3k per month. This was affordable and, while it would put a dent in my savings, wouldn't leave me worrying about money at the end of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through-out the year there were a number of factors that further affected my finances:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Touring Europe in the van cost significantly more than I estimated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My daughter's nursery care was cheaper than expected since moving her from four days a week to three (instead having an additional 'daddy-day-care' day).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While I typically spend a significant amount on computer hardware, this year I required very little but for a relatively cheap new server.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, looking back across the year (and excluding large one-off payments like buying the van) it seems my burn-rate was closer to £2k, one third less than I had planned. This coupled with receiving returns on previous investments meant I actually ended the year significantly better off than I started it. While this definitely wouldn't be the case were I to continue the career-break for a second year, it is very reassuring to know that I could, should I decide to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Github contributions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Across the year - although predominantly in the last few months - I made 368 commits to Github. These were spread across a couple of dozen repositories but mostly focused on the (private) repository for &lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-gb/store/p/littlelittle/9nblggh51b1b"&gt;LittleLittle&lt;/a&gt; and my (statically generated &amp;amp; github-pages hosted) &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs/ibebbs.github.io"&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;. Additionally, I contributed to several open source repositories, most notably the &lt;a href="https://github.com/Microsoft/UWPCommunityToolkit"&gt;UWP Community Toolkit&lt;/a&gt; (1000 stars) and &lt;a href="https://github.com/beto-rodriguez/Live-Charts"&gt;Live-Charts&lt;/a&gt; (875 stars).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given 2016 was a leap-year, 368 commits in 366 days averages (just!) over one a day. Overall I'm quite pleased with this level of commitment and the quantity of work it represents, especially considering the amount of time this year spent not working. Additionally, for the last three months of this year, my partner and I have both elected to work four-day weeks as we felt it represented a better balance between parental and nursery care for our daughter. For me this meant Thursdays became "daddy-day-care" so that I could take my daughter swimming - something we both really enjoy - but which adversely affected my productivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving forward I intend to start publishing much more of my work to public repositories including regular updates to my &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs/Spikes"&gt;"Spikes"&lt;/a&gt; repository which contains investigative projects and examples for solutions to various StackOverflow questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;StackOverflow&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talking of StackOverflow questions, the next visualization shows StackOverflow Reputation accumulation across the year (light blue line) with gains shown day-by-day (dark blue boxes). While I predominantly consider it a distraction, I really enjoy answering questions on StackOverflow, probably due to the awesome &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gamification"&gt;gamification&lt;/a&gt; employed on the &lt;a href="http://stackexchange.com/"&gt;StackExchange&lt;/a&gt; sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there is a low level of fairly constant reputation gain, most of the gains came in short bursts. As discussed above, I attribute this losing focus on my main projects due to inactivity. Still, there are far worse forms of procrastination than helping people and I consider this a relatively good use of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am currently endeavoring to get the 'Fanatic' badge (visit StackOverflow for 100 days consecutively) but trying not to let it get in the way of other work. This usually means only answering questions when I can quickly point the asker in the right direction but I will occasionally field a more challenging question when it's &lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/tagged/system.reactive"&gt;something I'm particularly interested in&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Blog posts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the course of the year I have written and published 22 blog posts - totaling nearly 24,000 words - across a range of subjects including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3D PRINTING (1) APACHE KAFKA (1) APACHE ZOOKEEPER (1) ATTACHED PROPERTY (1) BDD (1) BEHAVIORAL (1) BLOG (3) CAREER BREAK (1) CLIENT-SIDE FRAMEWORK (2) CQRS (1) DART (1) DATAFLOW (1) DOCKER (1) DVD RIPPING (1) EF (1) ELASTIC STACK (4) ELASTICSEARCH (4) EVENT SOURCING (1) EVENTS (1) EVENTSOURCING (1) FUTURE (1) GITHUB (2) GROWTH (1) HYPERLINK (1) IOT (1) JAVASCRIPT (2) JS (1) KIBANA (4) LITTLELITTLE (1) LOGSTASH (4) MAPLIN (1) MONITORING (4) MVVM (1) NANOSERVER (1) NETWORKING (4) PARENTHOOD (1) PATTERNS (1) PRODUCTIVITY (1) RASPBERRYPI (1) REACTIVE (7) REST (1) ROBOX (1) RX (7) SQL (1) STATE MACHINES (1) SVG (1) SYSLOG (4) TESTING (1) TODDLERBOX (3) TOOLKIT (2) TPL (2) TRAVEL (1) TYPESCRIPT (1) UWP (7) VISUAL STUDIO (2) VISUAL STUDIO CODE (1) WEBRX (2) WINDOWS SERVER 2016 (1) WYAM (1) XAML (2) XBOX (3)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This content garners an average of around 110 unique visitors and 400 page views every month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of these posts - &lt;a href="https://blogs.msdn.microsoft.com/dotnet/2016/09/07/the-week-in-net-972016/"&gt;"The absolute easiest way to use SVG icons in UWP apps"&lt;/a&gt; was featured in &lt;a href="https://blogs.msdn.microsoft.com/dotnet/2016/09/07/the-week-in-net-972016/"&gt;"The week in .NET – 9/7/2016"&lt;/a&gt;. Furthermore, blog posts I have shared with people on other platforms (i.e. StackOverflow, MSDN, etc) have been understood and well received.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in, I think I've added some valuable content to my blog this last year but feel like I should have tried harder to increase it's reach. While writing these blog posts inevitably takes a considerably amount of time, I intend to continue making as many new posts as possible, hopefully across an increased range of subjects and - by submitting to various aggregation blogs - with increased readership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Commitments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This timeline displays any days I had expected to work yet was unable to for a variety of reasons. Over the course of the year this accounted for 42 days, mostly the Thursdays that have become my "daddy-day-care" day and during which I take my daughter swimming. While these "commitments" would have been worked around had I been in full-time employment, the flexibility of working when I can as opposed to when I have to has undoubtedly led to a greater degree of motiviation and concentration when I am in front of the computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given this fairly comprehensive look back across the year, it's time to perform the retrospective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What went well?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were numerous wins across the year including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Getting to spend the year with my partner and baby which included spending two months traveling Europe in a camper-van.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Releasing applications to the Windows Store for phone, tablet, PC and XBox.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Furthering the breadth of my technical knowledge of various platforms, technologies and methodologies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adding a significant amount of content to my blog.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contributing to numerous repositories on Github including several for popular open-source projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increasing my StackOverflow Reputation level by answering questions on a variety of subjects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fully realising the importance of exercise on productivity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Completing the year in better financial health than I had expected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What didn't go so well?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that, despite taking a career break, I continued to be productive in a variety of ways, I don't feel like too many things went badly this year. However there are a few things I would have liked to have achieved but didn't such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not finding the "market gap" or having the "killer idea" I had hoped to translate into a start-up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not investigating as many technologies as I had hoped across the course of the year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lacking a significant amount of exercise and thereby loosing focus and momentum for ongoing projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shying away from increasing the exposure of my blog content via news aggregators, social media, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What needs to change moving forward&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I gave myself the year to come up with the "killer idea" but didn't manage it so now it's time to change tack. In the coming months I will be starting to look for contract work which, ideally, I can do remotely. Fortunately there is no pressure for me to return to work so I can be quite picky about the roles I take. The ideal contract would ideally feature one or all of the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;UWP/WPF&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rx/Streaming technologies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;.NET Core&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IoT&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;NoSQL datastores&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CQRS/ES&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ideally in the following markets:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Baby/Toddler/Child care/entertainment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Social Justice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Agriculture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Renewable Energy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automotive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Economics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, given the large number of &lt;a href="https://blog.rjmetrics.com/2014/04/30/the-big-opportunities-in-the-unknown-unknowns/"&gt;"unknown unknowns"&lt;/a&gt;, perhaps there are other technologies / markets I've not encountered yet that would be equally enthralling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the mean time, I will continue to investigate other interesting technologies and release updates to my existing products as appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding family life, well, in this respect I hope to continue the extremely rewarding work/life balance my partner and I have achieved over the last year. This could be difficult once the demands of external deadlines become a reality again but it's something I would be extremely reluctant to change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;In conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's been an amazing year and one I will remember for a long time. Regardless of what I end up doing, it is my aim to take another career break in the not too distant future in which I will endeavor to repeat the successes of this year, remedy the failures and remind myself that it's good to look up from the computer from time to time.&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;Saturday morning, having realized that we had no commitments or prior engagements until the following Tuesday, my partner and I decided to go on a trip. We rapidly packed bags for ourselves and our little girl, threw them in the van and set off with no set destination other than "the south-west". We ended up staying in a small farm on Exmoor and having a terrific time walking on the moor and visiting nearby sites.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<link href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/ASentimentalAnalysisOfRedDwarfPartII" />
		<id>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/ASentimentalAnalysisOfRedDwarfPartII</id>
		<title>A sentiment(al) analysis of why Red Dwarf is no longer funny</title>
		<updated>2017-04-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<content>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;I've recently been working on a project that required some natural language processing. After a surprisingly brief search I came upon the &lt;a href="https://stanfordnlp.github.io/CoreNLP/"&gt;Stanford CoreNLP&lt;/a&gt; suite of tools and after playing with their &lt;a href="http://corenlp.run/"&gt;online demo&lt;/a&gt; was astounded at the capabilities it provided. Furthermore, it was free, could be run such that it provided a basic HTTP API and came packaged with everything it needed save a copy of the JRE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having recently &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/DockerAndKafka"&gt;enjoyed a lot of success&lt;/a&gt; running &lt;a href="https://zookeeper.apache.org/"&gt;various&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://kafka.apache.org/"&gt;JAVA&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://neo4j.com/product/"&gt;services&lt;/a&gt; inside a &lt;a href="https://www.docker.com/"&gt;Docker container&lt;/a&gt; running &lt;a href="https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/windows-server-docs/get-started/getting-started-with-nano-server"&gt;Windows Nano Server&lt;/a&gt;, I decided to see if CoreNLP could be run like this too. Copying my previous &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs/Docker/blob/master/Nanoserver-Zookeeper/Build.ps1"&gt;build script&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs/Docker/blob/master/Nanoserver-CoreNLP/Build.ps1"&gt;amending it&lt;/a&gt; to build a &lt;a href="https://hub.docker.com/r/ibebbs/nanonlp/"&gt;container running CoreNLP&lt;/a&gt; was ludicrously easy and in no time I had a local API I could hit to perform all the natural language processing I needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, while the project I was working on mainly required the &lt;a href="https://stanfordnlp.github.io/CoreNLP/ner.html"&gt;"Named Entity Recognition"&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://stanfordnlp.github.io/CoreNLP/openie.html"&gt;"Open IE"&lt;/a&gt; annotators, I was intrigued to see that CoreNLP also included a basic &lt;a href="https://stanfordnlp.github.io/CoreNLP/sentiment.html"&gt;Sentiment&lt;/a&gt; annotator. Given that I had written part one of this post back in January, had noted at the time how much I'd like to do sentiment analysis on the transcripts of Red Dwarf, and that I hadn't written a blog post since, I decided to take some time out and perform the sentiment analysis so that I could write this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again employing &lt;a href="https://jupyter.org/"&gt;Project Jupyter&lt;/a&gt; hosted on &lt;a href="https://notebooks.azure.com/"&gt;Azure Notebooks&lt;/a&gt; and using &lt;a href="http://fsharp.org/"&gt;F#&lt;/a&gt; coupled with &lt;a href="https://fslab.org/"&gt;FsLab&lt;/a&gt; as my primary language and toolkit, I had a lot of fun performing the analysis. Like last time, you can find the &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs/RedDwarfAnalysis/blob/master/SentimentAnalysisWithCoreNLP.ipynb"&gt;full notebook&lt;/a&gt; and source material in my &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs/RedDwarfAnalysis"&gt;Github repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: As before, Github provides a "limited rendering only" so, to see all the charts running correctly you need to use the 'nbviewer' link shown below to see a full rendering of the notepad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://mvpfyw-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3mppldGfaYEhvWkV7mdUw26-lP3SOzlMTGFbf8slchIfjBL57IH-GrJev6ai_rISiHBKrom7Abg9YFjfhZ1ArOFT7a7mh4gJuGq-CErv1dun48GQC_BdhMV08fh6hbw400d9nHSEXJ0jA2nPBIrpOPNrOz0I3lVY1tu_L656ylQKg?width=660&amp;amp;height=283&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:660; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Open external view with nbviewer"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best bit of all (note: spoilers ahead!) is that it seems my original conclusion may indeed have been wrong... or at least mis-attributed.&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;I've recently been working on a project that required some natural language processing. After a surprisingly brief search I came upon the &lt;a href="https://stanfordnlp.github.io/CoreNLP/"&gt;Stanford CoreNLP&lt;/a&gt; suite of tools and after playing with their &lt;a href="http://corenlp.run/"&gt;online demo&lt;/a&gt; was astounded at the capabilities it provided. Furthermore, it was free, could be run such that it provided a basic HTTP API and came packaged with everything it needed save a copy of the JRE.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<link href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/HomeNetworkMonitoring-PartII" />
		<id>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/HomeNetworkMonitoring-PartII</id>
		<title>Home Network Monitoring - Part II</title>
		<updated>2016-04-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<content>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;In part one of this series I set up my home router to send a variety of Syslog messages to LogStash which then forwarded these messages to ElasticSearch for indexing and querying by Kibana in a simplistic dashboard. In this post, I'm going to start parsing out some of the details of the Syslog messages to start giving us a clearer idea about which devices on my local network are opening sessions with remote servers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;message types&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My router sends a number of different messages types; everything from router/dsl bandwidth information to the firewall log as can be seen below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/DrayTek-Syslog.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="DrayTek Syslog Administration"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, I'm really only interested in the 'User Access Log' which tells us when a local device resolves an IP address for a domain name or accesses a remote server. This log constitutes a number of message types such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;TCP / UDP access
This message is sent by the router when a device on the local network accesses a remote server via TCP or UDP. It looks like this: &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;150&amp;gt;Apr 10 16:55:38 Vigor: Local User (MAC=00-00-00-00-00-00): 192.168.1.205:64281 -&amp;gt; 5.10.110.36:80 (TCP)Web&lt;/code&gt;. From this type of message I am interested in parsing out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Syslog timestamp&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Syslog username&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Source Mac Address&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Source IP Address&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Destination IP Address&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Protocol&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;DNS lookup
This message is sent by the router when a device on the local network resolves an IP address for a remote server DNS nane. It looks like this: &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;150&amp;gt;Apr 10 18:52:49 Vigor: Local User (MAC=00-00-00-00-00-00): 192.168.1.62 DNS -&amp;gt; 192.168.1.1 inquire a.root-servers.net&lt;/code&gt;. From this type of message I am interested in parsing out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Syslog timestamp&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Syslog username&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Source Mac Address&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Source IP Address&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Domain being resolved&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I'll focus on enriching the incoming message with information from the access message but will move on to parsing multiple message types in a future post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;parsing access messages&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Logstash provides a great tool for parsing messages: the 'grok' filter. As explained in &lt;a href="https://www.elastic.co/guide/en/logstash/current/plugins-filters-grok.html"&gt;the documentation&lt;/a&gt; 'grok' allows you to 'Parse arbitrary text and structure it. This tool is perfect for syslog logs, apache and other webserver logs, mysql logs, and in general, any log format that is generally written for humans and not computer consumption.'&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This filter applies a regular expression like patterns to a field in the incoming message and, if matched successfully, adds each matched expression to the message being processed as a new field. The fields to capture are defined in the format &lt;code&gt;%{SYNTAX:SEMANTIC}&lt;/code&gt; where the &lt;code&gt;SYNTAX&lt;/code&gt; element is a known pattern (see below) or a regular expression and the &lt;code&gt;SEMANTIC&lt;/code&gt; is a name of the field to capture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Logstash ships with over 120 known &lt;code&gt;SYNTAX&lt;/code&gt; patterns and these patterns can be supplemented by adding new pattern files to a specific directory. However, the default patterns supplied cover nearly all common scenarios and allow almost all the pertinent information in the TCP access message above to be parsed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, by just using the default patterns, I can write the expression&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;%{POSINT:syslog_pri}&amp;gt;%{SYSLOGTIMESTAMP:syslog_timestamp} Vigor\: Local User \(MAC=%{MAC:source_mac}\): %{IP:source_address}(?::%{POSINT:source_port})? -&amp;gt; %{IP:destination_address}(?::%{POSINT:destination_port})?
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which gives us the following additional fields in the message:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;|field|value|
|-----|-----|
|source_address|192.168.1.205|
|source_port|64281|
|source_mac|00-00-00-00-00-00|
|syslog_pri|150|
|syslog_timestamp|Apr·10·16:55:38|
|destination_address|5.10.110.36|
|destination_port|80|&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neat huh! I'd also like to know whether the access message is TCP or UDP so I'm going to add a custom regular expression to the end of the pattern to parse the protocol string out of the message. In full the pattern is now:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;%{POSINT:syslog_pri}&amp;gt;%{SYSLOGTIMESTAMP:syslog_timestamp} Vigor\: Local User \(MAC=%{MAC:source_mac}\): %{IP:source_address}(?::%{POSINT:source_port})? -&amp;gt; %{IP:destination_address}(?::%{POSINT:destination_port})? \((?&amp;lt;protocol&amp;gt;TCP|UDP)\)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This would result in the following fields available in the message:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;|field|value|
|-----|-----|
|source_address|192.168.1.205|
|source_port|64281|
|source_mac|00-00-00-00-00-00|
|syslog_pri|150|
|syslog_timestamp|Apr·10·16:55:38|
|destination_address|5.10.110.36|
|destination_port|80|
|&lt;strong&gt;protocol&lt;/strong&gt;|&lt;strong&gt;TCP&lt;/strong&gt;|&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NOTE: You can use &lt;a href="http://grokconstructor.appspot.com/"&gt;Grok Constructor&lt;/a&gt; to help you perfect your grok expressions prior to trying them in Logstash&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;adding the grok filter to logstash&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, now I know how to extract all the information I'm interested in from the access message, I need to get Logstash to actually do it. This is done by adding a &lt;code&gt;grok&lt;/code&gt; filter to the &lt;code&gt;filter { }&lt;/code&gt; section of the &lt;code&gt;syslog.config&lt;/code&gt; file authored in the previous post as shown here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;input {
  tcp {
    port =&amp;gt; 5000
    type =&amp;gt; syslog
  }
  udp {
    port =&amp;gt; 5000
    type =&amp;gt; syslog
  }
}

filter {
    grok {
      match =&amp;gt; [ "message", "&amp;lt;%{POSINT:syslog_pri}&amp;gt;%{SYSLOGTIMESTAMP:syslog_timestamp} Vigor\: Local User \(MAC=%{MAC:source_mac}\): %{IP:source_address}(?::%{POSINT:source_port})? -&amp;gt; %{IP:destination_address}(?::%{POSINT:destination_port})? \((?&amp;lt;protocol&amp;gt;TCP|UDP)\)" ]
    }
}

output {
  elasticsearch {
    hosts =&amp;gt; ["192.168.1.30:9200"]
    index =&amp;gt; "syslog-%{+YYYY.MM.dd}"
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice the grok section in which we specify a 'match' field. This field takes an array of two strings; the first string is the field containing the text to match and the second is the pattern to match the text to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once this is added to the &lt;code&gt;syslog.config&lt;/code&gt; file and Logstash restarted, these new fields should be being written to ElasticSearch. The easiest way to see if this is working is to return to Kibana and, from the 'Settings/Indices' area, click the 'syslog-*' pattern on the left and then click the orange 'Refresh field list' button and the field list appears like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-RefreshSyslogIndex.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Refresh Syslog Index"&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;exploring network access information&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the additional fields are available to Kibana, I can start exploring the data to learn about which devices on my network are access which remote servers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do this I first need to add the new fields to the 'Syslog Messages' saved search. This can be done by navigating to the 'Discover' page, loading the 'Syslog Messages' search (using the 'Load Saved Search' button in the top right of the screen), adding the new fields and re-saving it. This is shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-AddingNewFieldsToSyslogMessagesSavedSearch.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Adding New Fields To Syslog Messages Saved Search"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm now able to add some very interesting new visualizations to our dashboard such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Number of access by each local device&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Number of access by port&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Number of access to each remote server&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Number of access by protocol&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll only run through adding the first visualization is they're all very similar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I navigate to the 'Visualization' area and click the 'New Visualization' button. I want to see the number of accesses being made by each device as a fraction of the whole so will use a donut chart. This is done by selecting 'Pie chart' from the "Create new Visualization" menu and selecting our 'Syslog Messages' saved search in the "Select a search source" menu. Once this is done, I get a pie chart with a single section as shown here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-NewPieChartVisualization.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana New Pie Chart Visualization"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then need to select the 'Split Slices' bucket type, choose 'Terms' as the aggregation type and finally select 'source_address' as the field on which to aggregate (i.e. count) unique terms. Applying this to the pie-chart (using the 'Apply' button) results in the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-SplitSlicePieChartUsingSourceAddress.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Split Slice Pie Chart Using Source  ddres s"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll  then  turn  this into a donut chart by ticking the 'Donut' check box from the 'Options' area as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-SplitSliceDonutChartUsingSourceAddress.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Split Slice Donut Chart Using Source Address"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I'll use the same process for adding donut charts for each of the other metrics outlined above and add all the charts to my dashboard giving me the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-DashboardWithAccessCharts.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Dashboard With Access Charts"&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I showed how to extract structured information from unstructured text data in our source message. I then showed how this can be used within Kibana to highlight which devices on the local network are accessing which remote servers, on which ports and using which protocols.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next post, I'll examine how to further enhance the information we've extracted from the access messages to make it easier to relate ip address to actual devices on the network and out in the world.&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;In part one of this series I set up my home router to send a variety of Syslog messages to LogStash which then forwarded these messages to ElasticSearch for indexing and querying by Kibana in a simplistic dashboard. In this post, I'm going to start parsing out some of the details of the Syslog messages to start giving us a clearer idea about which devices on my local network are opening sessions with remote servers.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
</feed>epartment-growth/"&gt;internal power struggle&lt;/a&gt; resulted in a change of senior management and a move away the progressive development methodologes which had made the company such a great place to work. This, to me, signalled that it was time to move on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Sabatical&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I considered the couple of months following ending full time employment as a sabatical; time to reflect, get my affairs in order and spend time with my young family before  considering how to move forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this time my daughter was just 4 months old so this presented a great opportunity to support my partner and engage with my baby. Having also taken 6 weeks of &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/shared-parental-leave-and-pay/overview"&gt;Shared Parental Leave&lt;/a&gt; the previous year, this meant that, of her first six months of life, I'd been able to spend almost four with her. I feel incredibly fortunate to be in a situation where this is could be the case. The first few months of a baby's life are incredibly tough for both the parents and the baby and I'm very happy that I was able to be with my girls throughout this time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was towards the end of this period that my partner and I decided to capitalise on our unique situation and put the remainder of her maternity leave to use by taking our little girl on a road-trip around Europe. The implications of this decision were to dominate and, to a large degree, consume the entirity of the next three months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Preparation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having made the decision to spend a significant amount of time touring Europe, with an 8 month old baby no less, it became apparent that there would be a whole lot of preparation required to make this happen. In March we decided to buy a Nissan Elgrand E51 Rider Autech (shown below) and April onwards was spent preparing it for our trip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://zdfcta-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3mRDVqstf6XsjN73biGoYnN5s-SzVcHx9pEdYl2S_wM803HpiosWK5Skxm-kskeHTMkahk_PIdejAp70x14KCaOwmZb6OvAvAig8uqI4bdBs2Pb_lAUsm-O_2lO8krW_18ReDVMLXqVkJWUGUSJ-d80bOIi8ciWIgyxDzL5fw4qF4?width=1796&amp;amp;height=1347&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:800; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Nissan Elgrand E51 Rider Autech"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This preparation was complex, with numerous requirements, constraints and learning curves across a variety of disciplines... but also a whole lot of fun. On our return I wrote a &lt;a href="http://elgrandoc.uk/forum/index.php?threads/touring-europe-in-an-elgrand-part-i-to-v.3311"&gt;very long post&lt;/a&gt; for the &lt;a href="http://elgrandoc.uk/forum/index.php"&gt;Elgrand Owners Club&lt;/a&gt; which detailed all the work I had done on the van. While the post took a significant amount of time to write, the forums were invaluable in providing the information I needed to do the work in the first place so I thought it was worth investing this time in case the post helped someone else in the same manner. To this day, the post is still one of the most viewed and commented on posts in the forum. It's well worth a read a read if you have time; if not, here are some pictures of the work instead:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://mkakza-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3mTMvumgbiWf4cuNId6rdQdXFkrZEMe891yFE3uaLIn1eWi8gsAGfCe6dwKUZjSfNqkfJHNpdzXf60mJIb2RH1HlQ1ku-6IEk5IPtKNoDHcJnVFi1_AIGA-TvxRXvplxSaxmqN385ks_cd0YZ2dxxdpU3ylY7UlYPW2uP9sp8Sr9A?width=660&amp;amp;height=371&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:800; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Cargo frame"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://dotw7g-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3mAeFtD-P9o5iDeydmal4JBd-518YT4V1-WPcdo33zt8xDn7vLENvSjzaMzFf5U52ZKreB49IRMJTdoMGXtxtSsLYUdF0mPvkYh-6ts_sihIt3aWMgd2hHlmkIzm-twj54_tTlpRJm2Xi3B58mGjSM_ZxF-aAQcQq842NpEBTlOVE?width=660&amp;amp;height=371&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:800; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Electrics box"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://adlakq-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3mw8fNegXFskURlkB2qFnfOJA7BsmrmPW7hx3Xyflhqwi52YIR8NEdSqz-acBvO6cTO2X5Atjj6U2uTFjGiLhTofbHGbteqx1B1MxGWouRBLO1WF1lTUCVMLbsUJmwFy2jPKb84N9xG_-1YuOmhqovFb59UuxMYxasZ0yyVDJgAtY?width=660&amp;amp;height=371&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:800; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Electrics fitted"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://plsn1w-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3mt5MSkFV_zVYge_IQZeDn02BvYd2ngjLePZYmte7YKsEIpa-e_n6BRgS0YFM5F1fge5qaJX5aAVLsyfhxVQo11B13NwfQ1hIQy47gdIcoBCjIWPPklSUKFIG59c2SXhfEaH0_xILPK35Awxm2RTs8bWvsLtkMtNTNs4V3t4qKXSw?width=660&amp;amp;height=371&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:800; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Cargo fitted"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://mhrszq-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3m5m7EX2zp-dMeKdwNa-8RMrBapeb5hhLCpRCj8bfI277ok0RZOs7Rv3GAdXQRiTsVfE6L-skEtFtkcgoi8Nf5qo1vxuw4aSoLPyMgXr5kHtDZQ-D5Sp1Lz2_-FoBNl8Zcj9bO531eW6_WFtu_Z0SE_QiDH2CWFp_-6hFL3fljt74?width=660&amp;amp;height=371&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:800; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Cable routed"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During this time I learned a lot about carpentry, electronics and engineering... but I almost didn't. Prior to undertaking the work, I had looked to find a conversion specialist who would do the work for me but most either only provided pattern-part conversions or were too busy to undertake a bespoke project. Well, "necessity being the mother of invention", I set to it and, in retrospect, am extremely glad I did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite barely having used an electric drill previously and never having dabbled in 240v electronics, I enjoyed every aspect of the work and am immensely proud of it. We didn't experience a single issue with my work while we were away and, even if we had, it was extremely comforting knowing that I could have resolved the issue in the field if I'd had to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should a similar challenge ever present itself again, I would certainly look at taking it on and, furthermore, would encourage others to do so also as you undoubtedly &lt;a href="https://hbr.org/2016/07/if-youre-not-outside-your-comfort-zone-you-wont-learn-anything"&gt;learn a lot more when working outside of your comfort zone&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Touring Europe&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the prep done - well, as much as was possible in the time available - we left home on May 20th and didn't return again until July 17; totaling just over 8 weeks on the road. In this time we traveled &lt;strong&gt;in excess of 8000 miles and visited 22 countries&lt;/strong&gt; seeing numerous friends en-route and making many more in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it was all the prep or perhaps we were just lucky but the trip went off without a hitch and everyone - including our little girl - had an amazing time. Both &lt;a href="https://bigspune.wordpress.com/"&gt;my partner&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/WotNoBlogPosts"&gt;I&lt;/a&gt; blogged about the trip - for ourselves as much for any potential reader - and, six months on, are still reflecting on what a fantastic adventure it was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without a shadow of a doubt, and even when considering the week's of preparation before leaving, this trip was time well spent. My partner and I learned a lot about each other ("hey, we &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; spend several weeks in a confined space together, 24/7") and our daughter and have accumulated memories that will last a lifetime. We have already talked about doing another similar trip in the future and have begun planning shorter breaks around the UK as a stop-gap until an opportunity for a new adventure comes along.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Study&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon my return, I came across a code for a free &lt;a href="https://borntolearn.mslearn.net/b/weblog/posts/sign-up-to-take-the-beta-exam-for-developing-mobile-apps-70-357-today"&gt;Microsoft beta exam about mobile application development&lt;/a&gt;. As I was interested in UWP app development and had already taken loads of these beta exams in previous years, I decided to sit the exam even though the code was only valid for a few weeks after signing up, which left very little time to study!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Experiential_learning"&gt;learn&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://psycnet.apa.org/journals/bdb/17/1/1.pdf&amp;amp;productCode=pa"&gt;best&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.virgin.com/richard-branson/you-learn-by-doing-and-by-falling-over"&gt;by&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://news.uchicago.edu/article/2015/04/29/learning-doing-helps-students-perform-better-science"&gt;doing&lt;/a&gt; my study focused on writing a UWP app that incorporated as many of the &lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/learning/exam-70-357.aspx"&gt;examined technical aspects&lt;/a&gt; as possible. While the methodologies I used for this app were relatively new (i.e. CQRS/ES) the learning curve for this exam really came from some of the unique aspects of UWP app development such as designing for multiple devices/screen sizes, using &lt;a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/ef/core/"&gt;new persistence technologies&lt;/a&gt; and leveraging the huge new API surface available to UWP apps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to an awful dashboard implementation which &lt;a href="https://borntolearn.mslearn.net/b/weblog/posts/more-tips-about-beta-exams-what-to-expect-when-you-39-re-expecting-your-beta-results-that-is"&gt;causes much confusion for students who sit beta exams&lt;/a&gt;, I am still unsure as to whether I passed this exam or not. My dashboard has not changed to say I have passed the exam but I have not received a summary sheet from Microsoft with my scores nor am I able to access them from my MCP dashboard. In short, the current beta exam process is extremely poor and much worse than it was five or six years ago when I took (and passed) around a dozen such beta exams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless, time spent on this study was a huge win. I learned a lot about a platform which is becoming increasingly prevalent in the Windows ecosystem. UWP apps are able to run on everything from Raspberry Pi to Hololens, and I have since deployed/released UWP apps for Raspberry Pi, Mobile (phone/table), PC and XBox. Indeed, after completing the exam, I continued to develop my UWP study app over the next few months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Holiday&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Across the year, I allocated around 40 days (including bank-holidays and weekends) as non-work days (aka holiday). This included snowboarding with friends, trips abroad, visiting relatives and a long festive break over Xmas. Although more than the holiday allowance at most full time jobs (depending on how it's allocated), I feel this represents a fairly decent split between work and play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;OneCog.Solutions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once life had returned to normal following our tour of Europe and taking the Microsoft beta exam, I decided to work on a few projects that were interesting to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, this was continuing my investigation of UWP, initially to &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/CqrsEsMvvmRxEfSqlUwpPcl"&gt;flesh out&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/store/p/littlelittle/9nblggh51b1b"&gt;release&lt;/a&gt; the UWP app I had written while studying for the UWP exam but then to also evaluate UWP as a &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/MonsterPi"&gt;platform for IoT devices&lt;/a&gt;. I then proceeded to broaden my area of investigation into &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/DockerAndKafka"&gt;non-Microsoft technologies&lt;/a&gt; and even into areas that, while still technical, were &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/3DPrintingWithTheCelRobox"&gt;not directly involved with software development&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During this time I endeavored to keep an up-to-date public profile. Through a &lt;a href="https://trello.com/b/KoTWuFUi/public-board"&gt;public Trello board&lt;/a&gt;, products I had released (&lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-gb/store/p/littlelittle/9nblggh51b1b"&gt;LittleLittle&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-gb/store/p/toddlerbox/9nblggh3zr4l"&gt;ToddlerBox&lt;/a&gt;), posts to &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/"&gt;my blog&lt;/a&gt; and contributions to both &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs"&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/users/628821/ibebbs"&gt;StackOverflow&lt;/a&gt; I tried to make sure as much of my time as possible was surfaced publicly. Indeed, having become extremely delivery-oriented since first drinking the agile (&lt;a href="https://medium.com/swlh/agile-is-the-new-waterfall-f7baef5d026d#.jpmks6gi4"&gt;lower-case 'a'&lt;/a&gt;) kool-aid several years ago, I feel the public-facing nature of these interactions substituted as a form of delivery; or, in Agile parlance, became my &lt;a href="https://www.agilealliance.org/glossary/definition-of-done/"&gt;"definition of done"&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While, in retrospect, I had hoped to have investigated many more technologies than I actually managed during this time, overall I would consider this time well spent. In addition to releasing two applications to the Windows Store and contributing to several public Github projects (more on this later) I managed to rack up over 1000 rep on StackOverflow in just a couple of months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, during this time, I didn't achieve my primary goal; namely finding a project that could potentially be grown into a marketable product and form the basis of a company. While there were no shortage of ideas and there still remain a couple of "coals in the fire", I don't think I've yet found the gap in the market I'm looking for. One slight positive note here is that I have, at the very least, determined a couple of markets I'm very keen on investigating further and in which I'd like to work in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this visualization I have employed step count (vertical bars), weight (yellow line with dotted yellow representing ideal weight) and fat-mass (red line with dotted red representing ideal fat-mass) as a (very rough) approximation of health. While, in theory, I should have had more leisure time available to exercise over the course of the year, in real terms I found that I did far less than expected. This was due to a number of factors:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My previous employer, being a company that revolves around football, had regular football matches/tournaments between company staff which were of a very high standard. I played in as many of these as possible and, once I left, I very much missed the exercise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My commute to work each day involved a (voluntary) walk from St Pancras station to Camden Lock - and back again - every day. This constituted 30 minutes/5000 steps of valuable exercise each day that was no longer necessary when I started working from home.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I ran a football team for my village that played in the local Bedfordshire league. Unfortunately, due to lack of players this team folded at the end of last season leaving me entirely bereft of football for the majority of the year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At punching-weight, I aim to be 11st and 15% fat-mass. This used to be a fairly common occurrence while playing football regularly but, as can be seen, I've not managed to get back into a similar condition this year. Fortunately, I &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; managed to avoid devolving into a complete bucket of lard thanks to several things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Parenthood - As any parent will tell you, being a parent is both exhausting and relentless. While previously I would undertake very little exercise in the evening, nowadays I expend a significant amount of energy each evening running around after my daughter. While not often recognised, this constitutes a fairly high level of activity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Preparation for Touring Europe - During this time I did &lt;strong&gt;a lot&lt;/strong&gt; of very physical work. From lugging construction materials and tools around to disassembling and reassembling the van, the average day was extremely active, especially when compared to sitting in an office chair for eight hours.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;European Tour - as can be seen from the step count, although a great deal of time was spent driving, our time away involved a lot of other activity. This activity (particularly loading and unloading the van each day!) provided a lot of exercise and helped keep me fit over the summer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Swimming - In a desperate attempt to remain in some sort of shape, I have recently started swimming semi-regularly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In retrospect, something that came as no surprise but for which I failed to anticipate the true impact, was the effect of not exercising on my state of mind and general happiness. Having always been an active and optimistic individual, I completely underestimated the tight correlation between these two characteristics. Mid-November saw me at my least active and, as I've come to realise, my least productive/focused (as evidenced by the sudden surge in StackOverflow rep!). Fortunately I try be somewhat self-reflective and, recognising that my diminished level of activity might be a possible cause for a perceived lack of progress, I decided to start swimming again as a means to address this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, while I'm still not exercise as much as I would like, I at least feel like my activity levels are sufficient to allow me to focus on projects and achieve my deliverables. Moving forward I very much hope to re-establish the village football team in time for next season or join another team such that I get at least a couple of games a month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Finances&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In counterpoint to the Health visualization described above, the Finances visualization shows a relative interpretation of my financial health across the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of the year, when considering a career-break, I tried to calculate a monthly "burn-rate" (i.e. total out-goings per month). Given I was not planning to change my lifestyle at all and my partner and I had already planned a number of holidays, I arrived at a rough estimate of £3k per month. This was affordable and, while it would put a dent in my savings, wouldn't leave me worrying about money at the end of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through-out the year there were a number of factors that further affected my finances:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Touring Europe in the van cost significantly more than I estimated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My daughter's nursery care was cheaper than expected since moving her from four days a week to three (instead having an additional 'daddy-day-care' day).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While I typically spend a significant amount on computer hardware, this year I required very little but for a relatively cheap new server.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, looking back across the year (and excluding large one-off payments like buying the van) it seems my burn-rate was closer to £2k, one third less than I had planned. This coupled with receiving returns on previous investments meant I actually ended the year significantly better off than I started it. While this definitely wouldn't be the case were I to continue the career-break for a second year, it is very reassuring to know that I could, should I decide to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Github contributions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Across the year - although predominantly in the last few months - I made 368 commits to Github. These were spread across a couple of dozen repositories but mostly focused on the (private) repository for &lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-gb/store/p/littlelittle/9nblggh51b1b"&gt;LittleLittle&lt;/a&gt; and my (statically generated &amp;amp; github-pages hosted) &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs/ibebbs.github.io"&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;. Additionally, I contributed to several open source repositories, most notably the &lt;a href="https://github.com/Microsoft/UWPCommunityToolkit"&gt;UWP Community Toolkit&lt;/a&gt; (1000 stars) and &lt;a href="https://github.com/beto-rodriguez/Live-Charts"&gt;Live-Charts&lt;/a&gt; (875 stars).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given 2016 was a leap-year, 368 commits in 366 days averages (just!) over one a day. Overall I'm quite pleased with this level of commitment and the quantity of work it represents, especially considering the amount of time this year spent not working. Additionally, for the last three months of this year, my partner and I have both elected to work four-day weeks as we felt it represented a better balance between parental and nursery care for our daughter. For me this meant Thursdays became "daddy-day-care" so that I could take my daughter swimming - something we both really enjoy - but which adversely affected my productivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving forward I intend to start publishing much more of my work to public repositories including regular updates to my &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs/Spikes"&gt;"Spikes"&lt;/a&gt; repository which contains investigative projects and examples for solutions to various StackOverflow questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;StackOverflow&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talking of StackOverflow questions, the next visualization shows StackOverflow Reputation accumulation across the year (light blue line) with gains shown day-by-day (dark blue boxes). While I predominantly consider it a distraction, I really enjoy answering questions on StackOverflow, probably due to the awesome &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gamification"&gt;gamification&lt;/a&gt; employed on the &lt;a href="http://stackexchange.com/"&gt;StackExchange&lt;/a&gt; sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there is a low level of fairly constant reputation gain, most of the gains came in short bursts. As discussed above, I attribute this losing focus on my main projects due to inactivity. Still, there are far worse forms of procrastination than helping people and I consider this a relatively good use of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am currently endeavoring to get the 'Fanatic' badge (visit StackOverflow for 100 days consecutively) but trying not to let it get in the way of other work. This usually means only answering questions when I can quickly point the asker in the right direction but I will occasionally field a more challenging question when it's &lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/tagged/system.reactive"&gt;something I'm particularly interested in&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Blog posts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the course of the year I have written and published 22 blog posts - totaling nearly 24,000 words - across a range of subjects including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3D PRINTING (1) APACHE KAFKA (1) APACHE ZOOKEEPER (1) ATTACHED PROPERTY (1) BDD (1) BEHAVIORAL (1) BLOG (3) CAREER BREAK (1) CLIENT-SIDE FRAMEWORK (2) CQRS (1) DART (1) DATAFLOW (1) DOCKER (1) DVD RIPPING (1) EF (1) ELASTIC STACK (4) ELASTICSEARCH (4) EVENT SOURCING (1) EVENTS (1) EVENTSOURCING (1) FUTURE (1) GITHUB (2) GROWTH (1) HYPERLINK (1) IOT (1) JAVASCRIPT (2) JS (1) KIBANA (4) LITTLELITTLE (1) LOGSTASH (4) MAPLIN (1) MONITORING (4) MVVM (1) NANOSERVER (1) NETWORKING (4) PARENTHOOD (1) PATTERNS (1) PRODUCTIVITY (1) RASPBERRYPI (1) REACTIVE (7) REST (1) ROBOX (1) RX (7) SQL (1) STATE MACHINES (1) SVG (1) SYSLOG (4) TESTING (1) TODDLERBOX (3) TOOLKIT (2) TPL (2) TRAVEL (1) TYPESCRIPT (1) UWP (7) VISUAL STUDIO (2) VISUAL STUDIO CODE (1) WEBRX (2) WINDOWS SERVER 2016 (1) WYAM (1) XAML (2) XBOX (3)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This content garners an average of around 110 unique visitors and 400 page views every month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of these posts - &lt;a href="https://blogs.msdn.microsoft.com/dotnet/2016/09/07/the-week-in-net-972016/"&gt;"The absolute easiest way to use SVG icons in UWP apps"&lt;/a&gt; was featured in &lt;a href="https://blogs.msdn.microsoft.com/dotnet/2016/09/07/the-week-in-net-972016/"&gt;"The week in .NET – 9/7/2016"&lt;/a&gt;. Furthermore, blog posts I have shared with people on other platforms (i.e. StackOverflow, MSDN, etc) have been understood and well received.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in, I think I've added some valuable content to my blog this last year but feel like I should have tried harder to increase it's reach. While writing these blog posts inevitably takes a considerably amount of time, I intend to continue making as many new posts as possible, hopefully across an increased range of subjects and - by submitting to various aggregation blogs - with increased readership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Commitments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This timeline displays any days I had expected to work yet was unable to for a variety of reasons. Over the course of the year this accounted for 42 days, mostly the Thursdays that have become my "daddy-day-care" day and during which I take my daughter swimming. While these "commitments" would have been worked around had I been in full-time employment, the flexibility of working when I can as opposed to when I have to has undoubtedly led to a greater degree of motiviation and concentration when I am in front of the computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given this fairly comprehensive look back across the year, it's time to perform the retrospective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What went well?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were numerous wins across the year including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Getting to spend the year with my partner and baby which included spending two months traveling Europe in a camper-van.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Releasing applications to the Windows Store for phone, tablet, PC and XBox.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Furthering the breadth of my technical knowledge of various platforms, technologies and methodologies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adding a significant amount of content to my blog.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contributing to numerous repositories on Github including several for popular open-source projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increasing my StackOverflow Reputation level by answering questions on a variety of subjects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fully realising the importance of exercise on productivity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Completing the year in better financial health than I had expected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What didn't go so well?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that, despite taking a career break, I continued to be productive in a variety of ways, I don't feel like too many things went badly this year. However there are a few things I would have liked to have achieved but didn't such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not finding the "market gap" or having the "killer idea" I had hoped to translate into a start-up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not investigating as many technologies as I had hoped across the course of the year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lacking a significant amount of exercise and thereby loosing focus and momentum for ongoing projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shying away from increasing the exposure of my blog content via news aggregators, social media, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What needs to change moving forward&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I gave myself the year to come up with the "killer idea" but didn't manage it so now it's time to change tack. In the coming months I will be starting to look for contract work which, ideally, I can do remotely. Fortunately there is no pressure for me to return to work so I can be quite picky about the roles I take. The ideal contract would ideally feature one or all of the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;UWP/WPF&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rx/Streaming technologies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;.NET Core&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IoT&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;NoSQL datastores&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CQRS/ES&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ideally in the following markets:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Baby/Toddler/Child care/entertainment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Social Justice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Agriculture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Renewable Energy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automotive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Economics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, given the large number of &lt;a href="https://blog.rjmetrics.com/2014/04/30/the-big-opportunities-in-the-unknown-unknowns/"&gt;"unknown unknowns"&lt;/a&gt;, perhaps there are other technologies / markets I've not encountered yet that would be equally enthralling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the mean time, I will continue to investigate other interesting technologies and release updates to my existing products as appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding family life, well, in this respect I hope to continue the extremely rewarding work/life balance my partner and I have achieved over the last year. This could be difficult once the demands of external deadlines become a reality again but it's something I would be extremely reluctant to change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;In conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's been an amazing year and one I will remember for a long time. Regardless of what I end up doing, it is my aim to take another career break in the not too distant future in which I will endeavor to repeat the successes of this year, remedy the failures and remind myself that it's good to look up from the computer from time to time.&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;Saturday morning, having realized that we had no commitments or prior engagements until the following Tuesday, my partner and I decided to go on a trip. We rapidly packed bags for ourselves and our little girl, threw them in the van and set off with no set destination other than "the south-west". We ended up staying in a small farm on Exmoor and having a terrific time walking on the moor and visiting nearby sites.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<link href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/3DPrintingWithTheCelRobox" />
		<link rel="enclosure" type="image" href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/y3mgQk7Eo-T13uKoaK88obO48Y6pzP0KHelfDJwLdORXiP6nnbplZzVSqbrBCBPh9bTpRgyynkyjS9mY53_ZE1f0NDpBcuKTDB7Jf6_a2me30twiv6CGRB6lQjK6Lu-DKkn6LTWVHSq463duCG-820-pQKTQ_q5ifVlXN40_86622Q%253Fwidth=965&amp;height=292&amp;cropmode=none" />
		<id>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/3DPrintingWithTheCelRobox</id>
		<title>3D Printing with the CEL Robox</title>
		<updated>2016-10-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<content>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;So, I've wanted a 3D printer for a while and recently a perfect storm of events meant I finally took the plunge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had hit a wall in my MonsterPi project trying to mount a RaspberryPi in a constrained space (more on this in a subsequent post). Most of my usual hacks (you'd be amazed what you can do with a sheet of acrylic and a Meccano set) simply wouldn't cut it and I was considering abandoning the project. Without intentionally meaning to, I found myself looking at 3D printers on &lt;a href="http://www.maplin.co.uk/c/gadgets-toys-and-hobbies/3d-printers"&gt;Maplin's website&lt;/a&gt; and saw that they were selling 'used' 3D printers at quite a discount.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a quick look around for reviews I found that one of the models Maplin were selling - the &lt;a href="http://www.maplin.co.uk/p/cel-robox-3d-printer-used-b81qq"&gt;CEL Robox&lt;/a&gt; - was listed as one of the best "Plug 'n' play" printers on &lt;a href="https://www.3dhubs.com/best-3d-printer-guide#plugnplay-cel-robox"&gt;3D Hubs&lt;/a&gt;. Moreover, my local (well, 15 miles away) Maplin's store had one in stock. But there was that 'used' thing. From what I'd gathered, getting a 3D printer to print reliably is tricky at the best of times, and I was thinking of buying one that had already been used and returned or worse, didn't even work in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Too intrigued not to dig a little deeper, I gave Maplin a call. Now experience has lead me not to expect too much from Maplin's employees - at best they're well meaning but witless, at worst they think you are -  but this time proved to be an exception. The guy who answered the phone was superb (note to self: must tweet Maplin about how great this guy is). Although he initially seemed confused about not having a used model of the 3D printer in store, he checked the website to confirm availability then the store stock levels to work out what was going on. Turns out the 'used' printer they had was actually the display model and after noting that he was unsure of the history of the printer he offered to make a couple of calls to other staff to find out the condition and how much it had been used then call me back; as I said, he was excellent. As promised, he called back in 15 minutes or so having confirmed that the printer had only been used to print a few example models and had otherwise sat idle for almost a year. Unfortunately in that time it had garnered a few scratches and lost it's box and support material but, having talked to his manager, he would be able to offer a further discount on the used price if I wanted to come in a take a look at it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the store an hour later it turned out that the guy I had talked to was actually the store manager and was really going the extra mile. By the time I had turned up, he had collated replacement components (power lead, usb lead, brushes, etc) from store stock and had the printer out ready for me to inspect. Amusingly, he had his staff so well organised that, seeing a few components laying around, they had actually put them all back on the shelves so he had to go collect them all again - but I couldn't help but be impressed. Anyway, the scratches turned out to be superfluous, the offer of an additional discount very attractive and the store manager's assurances that should anything be wrong with the unit he'd ensure it was replaced no questions asked very persuasive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I bought it, brought it home and, once the baby was safely ensconced at nursery the next day, set it up and set about calibrating it. The unit itself is a thing of beauty. Bold lines and colours with smooth, solid feeling mechanical components and a general air of quality; not at all what I've come to expect from a &lt;a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/robox/robox-desktop-3d-printer-and-micro-manufacturing-p"&gt;Kickstarter funded project&lt;/a&gt;. While I was initially wary of buying a 3D printer that used a proprietary "chipped" spool for fear of a lock-in to an expensive source of filament, the integrated nature of the spool into the body of the unit and the intelligence it provides to the software - everything from how much spool is left to how much a particular model will cost to print - is fantastic. Far from other "hobbyist" 3D printers where filament projects precariously around the unit, the feed of filament to the head is completely hidden from view and loading of filament completely automated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately calibration wasn't quite as smooth and it took a long time to get the printer ready to actually try printing a model. In fact, despite repeatedly trying and following all suggestions, one of the calibration tests - the needle valve opening calibration for the fill nozzle - stoically refused to run successfully. This may have been the result of the unit sitting idle for so long or simply me not setting it up right but the failure to pass this test was extremely worrisome. Even the 'purge' material test (used to completely empty the print heads when you're planning on changing material) failed to lay down material as it should but this was mostly resolved by vigorously cleaning the print bed with the isopropyl alcohol.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, despite the needle valve opening calibration still failing, I decided to print a model to see how it would perform before deciding whether or not to return the unit. From CEL's downloadable samples, I decided to try printing the 'cargo-box' as it didn't seem to require too much filament and a small container is always useful for something. Actually loading and starting to print a model using CEL's &lt;a href="http://www.cel-robox.com/downloads/"&gt;AutoMaker&lt;/a&gt; software is ludicrously simple: start a new layout, load a model, choose the granularity of the print, go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Watching a 3D model being printed is really something to behold. Despite it taking hours "like watching a 3D printer fabricate" should really become the metaphorical antonym to "like watching paint dry"; from the initial outline of the print being laid on the print bed, to seeing a solid object emerge, the process is fascinating. Taking a virtual object modelled on your computer and seeing that object take shape and become a physical object in the real world is thrilling, with innumerable possibilities opening up with every layer of filament laid down.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short order (well, actually 'long order' but it certainly didn't feel that way) and with much amazement and relief, the print was finished perfectly. A 1.5" square, green plastic cargo-box sat inside the Robox; I had fabricated a solid object from - seemingly - nothing. Once the unit had cooled the heated print-bed and unlocked the door, I tried removing the box, entirely expecting to have to lever and peel the plastic off the bed. To my surprise it moved easily, seemingly held to the bed by nothing more than a static charge. I was further surprised by the strength of the box; given it was made from nothing more than melted strands of plastic, I absolutely expected the fabricated object to have the tensile strength of a faberge egg. Yet it was incredibly rigid and inflexible, only the tell-tale layering giving away the fact that it had been 3D printer rather than cast in an industrial manufacturing plant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://0ohhnq.dm2302.livefilestore.com/y3mzj-a64dzTwhL7kVdtCG_OooHuVEnWyP5gynRF28lVCG247INMKuJpO8E2neQaekUtsZINVLDxnr5iwvoFRVqrOysfCj5ouJTt3e9oNYAOlrvaV2V7FquQultYnqicCjLCpdtiUF1NCeS5hfzgoXL5KhtZ2iBMvDpnslKBEX86FI?width=1024&amp;amp;height=576&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="My first 3D printed object"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now it was time to see if I could use the printer for the purpose I bought it: fabricating custom components for other projects. First up was a bracket to hold a RaspberryPi and other components in a very specific configuration. &lt;a href="http://www.sketchup.com/products/sketchup-pro/new-in-2016?gclid=CIK4ks2Cy88CFc0y0wodZmwHaQ"&gt;SketchUp&lt;/a&gt; has been my go-to 3D modelling software of choice since being bought and given away by Google. It is amazingly quick and easy to use for almost everything except extremely precise components with low tolerances; i.e. exactly the kind of thing I needed to do. So I went about looking for alternatives and quickly settled on the free version of &lt;a href="https://www.rs-online.com/designspark/mechanical-software"&gt;DesignSpark Mechanical from RS Components&lt;/a&gt;. Despite some quirkiness in it's UI, it provides most of the features and ease of use of SketchUp with several digits of precision for designed components. Indeed, instead of using a mouse to try to get the exact length of an edge, you can simply enter the length you want on the keyboard; precisely the functionality I thought was missing from SketchUp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took several hours to complete the 3D model for the bracket I needed - somewhat due to DesignSpark's learning curve but mostly the precise measurements and imprecise iteration required to design a bracket that would hold all the components just so - but eventually it was ready to print. Again, friction from design software to print ready was minimal. DesignSpark is able to export in the standard STL format and AutoMaker loaded the model and positioned it on the print-bed automatically, promising to fabricate me a completely custom component for just £1.48's worth of material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I set the print going but was quickly dismayed that the first layer of the print wasn't being laid properly at the far corners of the bed, mostly due to the fact that the corners of the bed away from the tabs that hold it in place had risen slightly. Regardless, I decided to let the print continue and see if subsequent layers would adhere to the small smudge of material the print head had managed to deposit. This turned out to be the right choice as by layer three the base of the bracket was fully formed and the printer had started using the "fill" nozzle to quickly start filling out further layers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took about three hours to design and an hour and forty minutes to fabricate, but the bracket fitted perfectly and was easily strong enough to hold all the components in the configuration I needed. I was a very happy boy and immediately starting to design a subsequent bracket I needed for the same project and plan for a load of other custom bits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, if you're thinking of buying a 3D printer and can afford what is - regardless of the heavy discount - an expensive bit of technology, I would absolutely recommend going for it. The possibilities of what you can create are mind-boggling and the sensation of watching them come into existence exhilarating. Being able to fabricate components I previously had to hack together from off the shelf bits is tremendously empowering and I can unashamedly say that I am completely hooked on 3D printing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, while I have no direct experience of other 3D printers, I wouldn't hesitate to recommend CEL's Robox printer as - despite still failing the nozzle calibration - it has yet to fail a print and the software is remarkably straight forward and easy to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch this space for more adventures in 3D printing as I integrate my new found fabrication abilities into my innumerable ongoing projects. First up: MonsterPi.&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;So, I've wanted a 3D printer for a while and recently a perfect storm of events meant I finally took the plunge.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
</feed>         }
                    else if (@@event is Event.AddBillingAddress)
                    {
                        ...
                    }
                    ...
                    else
                    {
                        throw new ArgumentException("Unknown message type");
                    }
                }
            );
        }
    );
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... which is not type safe, has very little compile time checking, requires a fall-through exception and, quite frankly, is horrible. I'm sure with Rx we can do something better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, lets look at this from a functional perspective. The action we want to perform when receiving each type of event can be considered to be a function in the form of &lt;code&gt;Func&amp;lt;TReadModel, TEvent, TReadModel&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;. This is very similar to the third parameter of the &lt;code&gt;Observable.Scan&lt;/code&gt; function with the problem being that we have multiple types of &lt;code&gt;TEvent&lt;/code&gt;. If only there was a way to produce a generic function that would operate correctly across all the event types.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, by leaning on a concept from functional languages, this might be possible. &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Partial_application" title="Partial Application definition from wikipedia"&gt;Partial application&lt;/a&gt; has been available in C# - via &lt;a href="http://csharpindepth.com/Articles/Chapter5/Closures.aspx" title="C# in Depth - The Beauty Of Closures"&gt;closures&lt;/a&gt; - since lambdas were introduced and allows you to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;fix a number of arguments to a function, producing another function of smaller arity. Given a function f:(X * Y * Z) -&amp;gt; N , we might fix (or 'bind') the first argument, producing a function of type (f){partial}:(Y * Z) -&amp;gt; N . Evaluation of this function might be represented as f{partial}(2, 3). Note that the result of partial function application in this case is a function that takes two arguments&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So is there some way we can leverage this to remove the &lt;code&gt;TEvent&lt;/code&gt; argument from the function? Absolutely, by making the observable emit a &lt;em&gt;stream of partial functions&lt;/em&gt; in the form &lt;code&gt;Func&amp;lt;ReadModel,ReadModel&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; which can then be applied to the read model as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;public IObservable&amp;lt;ReadModel&amp;gt; For(Guid id)
{
    if (id == null) throw new ArgumentNullException("id");

    return Observable.Create&amp;lt;ReadModel&amp;gt;(
        async observer =&amp;gt;
        {
            Service.AccountInfo accountInfo = await _accountService.GetAccountInfoAsync(id);

            IObservable&amp;lt;Func&amp;lt;ReadModel, ReadModel&amp;gt;&amp;gt; mutators = Observable.Merge(
                _bus.GetEvent&amp;lt;Event.AccountNameChanged&amp;gt;().Where(@@event =&amp;gt; id.Equals(@@event.AccountId)).Select(Functions.Apply),
                _bus.GetEvent&amp;lt;Event.AddBillingAddress&amp;gt;().Where(@@event =&amp;gt; id.Equals(@@event.AccountId)).Select(Functions.Apply),
                _bus.GetEvent&amp;lt;Event.RemoveBillingAddress&amp;gt;().Where(@@event =&amp;gt; id.Equals(@@event.AccountId)).Select(Functions.Apply),
                _bus.GetEvent&amp;lt;Event.OrderInvoiced&amp;gt;().Where(@@event =&amp;gt; id.Equals(@@event.AccountId)).Select(Functions.Apply),
                _bus.GetEvent&amp;lt;Event.OrderDispatched&amp;gt;().Where(@@event =&amp;gt; id.Equals(@@event.AccountId)).Select(Functions.Apply)
            );

            return mutators.Scan(accountInfo.ToReadModel(), (readModel, mutator) =&amp;gt; mutator(readModel)).Subscribe(observer);
        }
    );
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here the &lt;code&gt;Functions.Apply&lt;/code&gt; is an overloaded method for each of the event types. For example, the method for &lt;code&gt;Event.AccountNameChanged&lt;/code&gt; is implemented as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;public static Func&amp;lt;ReadModel, ReadModel&amp;gt; Apply(Event.AccountNameChanged @@event)
{
    return readModel =&amp;gt; readModel.WithAccountName(@@event.AccountName);
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This method takes the event to be processed as a parameter and returns a function in the form &lt;code&gt;Func&amp;lt;ReadModel,ReadModel&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; that closes over the parameter and calls the &lt;code&gt;WithAccountName&lt;/code&gt; extension method when executed. A similar pattern is followed for all the other event types.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we have projected and merged all the event streams into a single &lt;code&gt;IObservable&amp;lt;Func&amp;lt;ReadModel, ReadModel&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; we can use the scan function to iteratively apply each function to the cumulative read model instance and emit the result after each event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pretty neat huh!&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;If you're starting out with &lt;a href="http://docs.geteventstore.com/introduction/event-sourcing-basics/" title="Event Sourcing Basics at GetEventStore"&gt;Event Sourcing&lt;/a&gt; you're probably looking for the ability to project events into &lt;a href="http://cqrs.nu/tutorial/cs/03-read-models" title="CQRS tutorial - Read Models"&gt;read models&lt;/a&gt; that can be used by the views in your application. Today I'd like to share a neat little mechanism I've established for building read model in C# by employing a strongly typed yet functional approach.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
</feed>prompr, this can be done as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get the Nano2Docker powershell module&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This module is available in my Docker repository on Github and can be downloaded directly using the following command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;Invoke-WebRequest -OutFile Nano2Docker.psm1 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/ibebbs/Docker/master/Nano2Docker/Nano2Docker.psm1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then installed using:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;Import-Module Nano2Docker.psm1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;ol start="2"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prepare a base NanoServer image&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process of downloading docker and applying updates can be extremely slow. Therefore we first create a reusable base NanoServer image that has docker installed and updates applied. This is done using the command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;Initialize-Nano2DockerImage -MediaPath &amp;lt;Drive letter for Windows Server 2016&amp;gt; -BuildPath &amp;lt;Path to a build location&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if your Windows Server 2016 media is mounted in the 'G' drive and you want to build the new Nano2Docker image in the 'C:\Nano2Docker' folder, you'd use the command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;Initialize-Nano2DockerImage -MediaPath G: -BuildPath "C:\Nano2Docker"
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The command provides defaults download locations for docker and required updates but these can be overriden using the &lt;code&gt;-DockerUrl&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;-UpdateUrl&lt;/code&gt; parameters repsectively. Furthermore, if you already have an '.msu' file downloaded you can save a lot of time by providing this to the command using the &lt;code&gt;-UpdateFile&lt;/code&gt; parameter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you run this command, you will be prompted for Administrator credentials for the new Nano2Docker image. Either enter them when prompted or supply a &lt;code&gt;SecureString&lt;/code&gt; value to the &lt;code&gt;-Password&lt;/code&gt; argument (which is usually done using the &lt;code&gt;Get-Credentials&lt;/code&gt; commandlet).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When this command completes - which can take a while - you will find a 'Nano2Docker.vhdx' file in the BuildPath directory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3. Create a VM using the new NanoServer image&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can now use the &lt;code&gt;New-Nano2Docker&lt;/code&gt; commandlet to quickly create new VM docker hosts. The command is used as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;New-Nano2Docker -MediaPath &amp;lt;Drive letter for Windows Server 2016&amp;gt; -ImagePath &amp;lt;Path to a previously created Nano2Docker.vhdx&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using our previous example, the command would be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;New-Nano2Docker -MediaPath G: -ImagePath "C:\Nano2Docker\Nano2Docker.vhdx"
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This command will copy the base image to the VM path (defaults to 'C:\Users\Public\Documents\Hyper-V\Virtual Hard Disks'), provision a new, local, Hyper-V VM named 'Nano2Docker' with reasonable resources (4 cores / 2Gb of dynamic ram) and attached to the first available virtual switch.
Obviously, each of these characteristics can be changed using the appropriate arguments - use &lt;code&gt;Get-Help New-Nano2Docker&lt;/code&gt; to list the available arguments. You will again be asked to an Administrator password for the new VM which can be entered during creation or specified as a parameter to the commandlet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the new VM has been created, it will be started and the script will wait for NanoServer to start correctly. Once started, the IP address of the new VM is displayed and it should be immediately possible to use docker to communicate with the docker daemon on the VM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Scripting the deployment of a Docker Swarm&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given it was now trivial to create docker hosts, I wrote a final commandlet which leverages previous commandlets to provision an entire docker swarm. This is done using the &lt;code&gt;New-Nano2DockerSwarm&lt;/code&gt; commandlet as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;New-Nano2DockerSwarm -MediaPath &amp;lt;Drive letter for Windows Server 2016&amp;gt; -ImagePath &amp;lt;Path to a previously created Nano2Docker.vhdx&amp;gt; -VMPath &amp;lt;Path to a location to store swarm host VMs&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, using our previous example and wanting to store new VM images in the 'C:\Nano2Docker\VMs' directory, the command would be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;New-Nano2DockerSwarm -MediaPath G: -ImagePath "C:\Nano2Docker\Nano2Docker.vhdx" -VMPath "C:\Nano2Docker\VMs"
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This command defaults to creating a single manager node and three worker nodes named 'n2d-mngr-0' and 'n2d-wrkr-0/1/2' respectively. All nodes will have already been joined to the swarm in the appropriate capacity and ready for services to be deployed using docker or docker-compose.
Again, the number of manager and worked nodes as well as the name prefix for each node can be changed via the appropriate arguments (use &lt;code&gt;Get-Help New-Nano2DockerSwarm&lt;/code&gt; to list the arguments).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Roundup&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've successfully used this script to provision multiple docker hosts and docker swarms but it's worthwhile noting that it can be a bit finickity with directories. If you can an error saying it couldn't find a directory then simply create it first. I really ought to fix up the script (improvements via PR gratefully accepted) but I'm now a bit busy deploying services to my swarm :0)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore I've successfully used nodes created by this script to provision a hybrid swarm (see the 'Mixed OS clusters section &lt;a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/virtualization/windowscontainers/manage-containers/swarm-mode"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) of boot2docker and nano2docker images. With the appropriate labels on the nodes, it is possible to use docker-compose to automatically deploy images to the correct hosts while retaining all the benefits of overlay networking.&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;While my current contract doesn't leave much time for personal projects, I have made some progress on my current project (details on exactly what this is to follow). In fact, some of the smaller, peripheral services have their primary use-cases functionally complete and are ready for deployment and I am now faced with the question: Deployment to where?&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
</feed>