<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>Ian Bebbington</title>
		<link>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/</link>
		<description>IObservable&lt;Opinion&gt;</description>
		<copyright>2017</copyright>
		<pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2017 12:07:10 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2017 12:07:10 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Home Network Monitoring - Part I</title>
			<link>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/HomeNetworkMonitoring-PartI</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;Home networks are becoming increasingly complex. It is no longer just geeks and techies who have pervasive WiFi through-out their home to which a myriad of devices connect and communicate. When things go wrong or, worse still, the network is compromised by rouge hardware or software it's extremely difficult to work out what has happened and where to start troubleshooting the issue.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<guid>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/HomeNetworkMonitoring-PartI</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;Home networks are becoming increasingly complex. It is no longer just geeks and techies who have pervasive WiFi through-out their home to which a myriad of devices connect and communicate. When things go wrong or, worse still, the network is compromised by rouge hardware or software it's extremely difficult to work out what has happened and where to start troubleshooting the issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next few posts, I'm going to be showing how I used free and open-source software to build a home network monitoring solution that allows me to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Monitor the devices on my networks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Monitor my network connectivity and utilisation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Monitor which devices are connecting to which remote sites.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These posts will use the following components:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An internet router capable of sending Syslog messages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A mid-spec (i.e. dual-core 2Ghz) server with plenty of storage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Java Runime Environment installed on the server&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ElasticSearch stack consisting of:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Logstash (I will be using v2.4.1)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ElasticSearch (I will be using v2.4.1)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kibana (I will be using v4.5.0)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;the router&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the core of my solution is a router that supports writing &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syslog"&gt;Syslog&lt;/a&gt; messages to a Syslog server. While once a rarity, this functionality is becoming increasingly prevalent in home / SOHO routers. Personally I use a &lt;a href="http://www.draytek.co.uk/products/business/vigor-2830"&gt;DrayTek Vigor 2830&lt;/a&gt;, a versatile and - most importantly - extremely reliable router that can be purchased for just over £100 in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the router administration web interface, you can set the router to write a variety of Syslog messages to a Syslog server by specifying the servers IP address. This can be seen below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/DrayTek-Syslog.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="DrayTek Vigor Syslog Settings"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I simply tick all the boxes and add the IP address of the PC hosting the Syslog server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;the syslog server&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we have a router that is sending connectivity information via Syslog, we need a service running on a server that is capable of receiving these messages. For this I am using Elastic's &lt;a href="https://www.elastic.co/products/logstash"&gt;Logstash&lt;/a&gt; to receive the syslog messages and enrich them before forwarding them to an indexed store.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Logstash is an extremely versatile tool capable of consuming data from a variety of sources. A configuration file is used to set up a pipeline of inputs, operations (known as filters) and outputs which can do some truly fantastic things. If you're new to Logstash it might be worthwhile giving the ("Getting Started")[https://www.elastic.co/guide/en/logstash/current/getting-started-with-logstash.html] guide a quick read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start with, we'll get Logstash to simply accept Syslog input from a given port and write it to the console. To do this, simply &lt;a href="https://www.elastic.co/downloads/logstash"&gt;download Logstash&lt;/a&gt; and extract it to a directory on the PC. Next, open notepad and copy paste the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;input {
  tcp {
    port =&amp;gt; 5000
    type =&amp;gt; syslog
  }
  udp {
    port =&amp;gt; 5000
    type =&amp;gt; syslog
  }
}

filter {
}

output {
  stdout {
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Save this file named 'Syslog.config' and, from a command prompt, start Logstash with the following command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[LogStashDirectory]\bin\logstash.bat agent -f [ConfigFilePath]\Syslog.config&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If all goes well, you should see Logstash start receiving Syslog messages from the router which should appear something like the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;io/console not supported; tty will not be manipulated
Settings: Default pipeline workers: 2
Pipeline main started
2016-04-08T13:52:21.903Z 192.168.1.1 &amp;lt;150&amp;gt;Apr  8 14:51:59 Vigor: Local User (MAC=ZZ-ZZ-ZZ-ZZ-ZZ-ZZ): 192.168.1.62 DNS -&amp;gt; 192.168.1.1 inquire a.root-servers.net
2016-04-08T13:52:22.528Z 192.168.1.1 &amp;lt;150&amp;gt;Apr  8 14:51:59 Vigor: Local User (MAC=ZZ-ZZ-ZZ-ZZ-ZZ-ZZ): 192.168.1.51 DNS -&amp;gt; 192.168.1.1 inquire api-global.netflix.com
2016-04-08T13:52:22.528Z 192.168.1.1 &amp;lt;150&amp;gt;Apr  8 14:51:59 Vigor: Local User (MAC=ZZ-ZZ-ZZ-ZZ-ZZ-ZZ): 192.168.1.51 DNS -&amp;gt; 213.120.234.54 inquire api-global.netflix.com
2016-04-08T13:52:22.903Z 192.168.1.1 &amp;lt;150&amp;gt;Apr  8 14:52:00 Vigor: Local User (MAC=ZZ-ZZ-ZZ-ZZ-ZZ-ZZ): 192.168.1.62 DNS -&amp;gt; 192.168.1.1 inquire a.root-servers.net
2016-04-08T13:52:24.356Z 192.168.1.1 &amp;lt;150&amp;gt;Apr  8 14:52:01 Vigor: Local User (MAC=ZZ-ZZ-ZZ-ZZ-ZZ-ZZ): 192.168.1.100 DNS -&amp;gt; 192.168.1.1 inquire sls.update.microsoft.com
2016-04-08T13:52:24.356Z 192.168.1.1 &amp;lt;150&amp;gt;Apr  8 14:52:01 Vigor: Local User (MAC=ZZ-ZZ-ZZ-ZZ-ZZ-ZZ): 192.168.1.100 DNS -&amp;gt; 213.120.234.54 inquire sls.update.microsoft.com
2016-04-08T13:52:24.356Z 192.168.1.1 &amp;lt;158&amp;gt;Apr  8 14:52:01 Vigor: Load_balance 192.168.1.100 --(DNS)--&amp;gt; 213.120.234.54 go WAN1
2016-04-08T13:52:24.731Z 192.168.1.1 &amp;lt;150&amp;gt;Apr  8 14:52:01 Vigor: Local User (MAC=ZZ-ZZ-ZZ-ZZ-ZZ-ZZ): 192.168.1.100:53432 -&amp;gt; 157.56.77.138:443 (TCP)
2016-04-08T13:52:24.731Z 192.168.1.1 &amp;lt;158&amp;gt;Apr  8 14:52:01 Vigor: Load_balance 192.168.1.100 --(BAL)--&amp;gt; 157.56.77.138 go WAN1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're not receiving Syslog messages try the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ensure to check the firewall settings on the server you're using. You need to allow incomming TCP and UDP connections on port 5000.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attempt to telnet to port 5000 on the Syslog server. If Logstash is running correctly, you should be able to connect and see anything you sent from Telnet mirrored in the Logstash console window.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you're still unable to see any output, try using a network analysis too like &lt;a href="https://www.wireshark.org/"&gt;Wireshark&lt;/a&gt; to see if your router is actually sending any messages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;the syslog store&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we're able to receive Syslog messages, we need to store and index them. For this, we will use ElasticSearch. Simply &lt;a href="https://www.elastic.co/downloads/elasticsearch"&gt;download ElasticSearch&lt;/a&gt;, extract it to a directory and start it. If necessary you can change the directory used to store  ElasticSearch data or the interface/port on which ElasticSearch listens for incomming connections by modifying the &lt;code&gt;config\ElasticSearch.yml&lt;/code&gt; file. Modifying this file is pretty straight forward but for help the &lt;a href="https://www.elastic.co/guide/en/elasticsearch/reference/current/index.html"&gt;ElasticSearch documentation&lt;/a&gt; is available online and very thorough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, rather than having to manually start ElasticSearch everytime you want to use it, you can easily install it as a Windows service simply - as I have done - by issuing the following commands from a command prompt:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;[PathToElasticSearch]\bin\service.bat install
[PathToElasticSearch]\bin\service.bat start
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ElasticSearch should no be running. You can check this calling REST methods on ElasticSearch's web interface; by default on port 9200. In a browser, simple enter &lt;code&gt;http://[server-ip]:9200&lt;/code&gt; and you should see something like the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;"name" : "Shellshock",
"cluster_name" : "cluster",
"version" : {
  "number" : "2.3.1",
  "build_hash" : "bd980929010aef404e7cb0843e61d0665269fc39",
  "build_timestamp" : "2016-04-04T12:25:05Z",
  "build_snapshot" : false,
  "lucene_version" : "5.5.0"
},
"tagline" : "You Know, for Search"
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NOTE: You will be using the REST API extensively in future steps so I suggest finding a toolset that make querying and posting to REST endpoints easier. I use the excellent &lt;a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/postman/fhbjgbiflinjbdggehcddcbncdddomop?hl=en"&gt;&lt;code&gt;Postman&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Chrome application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With ElasticSearch running, we now need to modify Logstash to forward Syslog messages to ElasticSearch for indexing. As both tools are part of the Elastic Stack, this is every bit as easy as you might expect it to be. Simply open the &lt;code&gt;syslog.config&lt;/code&gt; file we created earler and change it to the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;input {
  tcp {
    port =&amp;gt; 5000
    type =&amp;gt; syslog
  }
  udp {
    port =&amp;gt; 5000
    type =&amp;gt; syslog
  }
}

filter {
}

output {
  elasticsearch {
    hosts =&amp;gt; ["[ElasticSearchServer-NameOrIPAddress]:9200"]
    index =&amp;gt; "syslog-%{+YYYY.MM.dd}"
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this in place, restart the Logstart service and, instead of writing received messages to the console, they will be stored in ElasticSearch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;the dashboard&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we have syslog messages in a central store, we will look how to set up a simple (for now) dashboard that lets us see a minimally useful feature: the number of Syslog messages being received over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to do this, we will be using ElasticSearch's Kibana tool to query messages from ElasticSearch and display a histogram of messages on a dashboard. To get started, simply download and extract Kibana to a directory on the server. Kibana comes with a default configuration that allows it to run correctly when co-located on the same server as ElasticSearch. If you are not running Kibana on the same server as ElasticSearch, you will need to modify the Kibana configuration file as described in the &lt;a href="https://www.elastic.co/guide/en/kibana/current/index.html"&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start Kibana, simply open a command prompt and execute the following command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[PathToKibana]\bin\Kibana.bat&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should see something like the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;log   [15:51:32.912] [info][status][plugin:kibana] Status changed from uniniti
alized to green - Ready
log   [15:51:32.975] [info][status][plugin:elasticsearch] Status changed from
uninitialized to yellow - Waiting for Elasticsearch
log   [15:51:33.006] [info][status][plugin:kbn_vislib_vis_types] Status change
d from uninitialized to green - Ready
log   [15:51:33.022] [info][status][plugin:markdown_vis] Status changed from u
ninitialized to green - Ready
log   [15:51:33.037] [info][status][plugin:metric_vis] Status changed from uni
nitialized to green - Ready
log   [15:51:33.053] [info][status][plugin:spyModes] Status changed from unini
tialized to green - Ready
log   [15:51:33.068] [info][status][plugin:statusPage] Status changed from uni
nitialized to green - Ready
log   [15:51:33.068] [info][status][plugin:table_vis] Status changed from unin
itialized to green - Ready
log   [15:51:33.100] [info][listening] Server running at http://0.0.0.0:5601
log   [15:51:38.131] [info][status][plugin:elasticsearch] Status changed from
yellow to yellow - No existing Kibana index found
log   [15:51:41.053] [info][status][plugin:elasticsearch] Status changed from
yellow to green - Kibana index ready
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Kibana started, use a browser to navigate to the Kibana web interface, typically on port 5601.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NOTE: If you are connected to Kibana from another PC, you will need to open firewall port 5602 on the server to allow connections to Kibana.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a short pause while Kibana is initialised, you should see the following screen:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-InitialIndex.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Initial Index Settings"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This screen allows you to add an index to Kibana that it can query messages in order to discover, visualise and ultimately produce a dashboard from information stored in the index. It is currently set to examine an index called &lt;code&gt;logstash-*&lt;/code&gt; and shows a disable button at the bottom of the screen containing the text 'Unable to fetch mapping. Do you have indices matching the pattern' as we do not have a logstash index stored in ElasticSearch. We want Kibana to query our Syslog index so we change the 'Index name or pattern' to &lt;code&gt;Syslog-*&lt;/code&gt; and, shortly after changing this value, we should see the button at the bottom change to 'Create' as shown here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-SyslogIndex.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Syslog Index Settings"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Kibana has defaulted to the correct timestamp field (more on this later) you can simply click the 'Create' button to add the index to Kibana.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After creating the index, you are taken to a screen that allows you modify how Kibana displays the fields within the index as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-SyslogIndexMapping.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Syslog Index Mapping"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We do not need to change anything here so can immediately start 'discovering' information in our Syslog index by clicking the 'Discover' tab as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-DiscoverSyslog.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Discover Syslog"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we're able to see the detail of the Syslog messages stored within the Syslog index on ElasticSearch. However, for now the messages are just strings so there's not a great deal we can do with them other than count them to produce a histogram of messages over time. To do this, we
first want to add the fields of the index we're interested in (just timestamp, host, message and type for now) to the selected fields area as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-SelectSyslogFields.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Select Syslog Fields"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we have the fields we're interested in selected, we save them as a new search by clicking the 'Save Search' button in the top right of the window as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-SaveSyslogSearch.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Save Syslog Search"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the search is saved, we can proceed straight to the 'Visualise' tab to create the histogram as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-VisualiseSyslogAsVerticalBarChart.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Visualise Syslog As Vertical Bar Chart"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To create a histogram, we use a "Vertical bar chart". Note it's description:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goto chart for oh-so-many needs. Great for time and non-time data. Stacked or grouped, exact numbers or percentages. If you are not sure which chart you need, you could do worse than to start here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So lets start here by clicking this option and selecting 'From a saved search' as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-VisualiseFromSavedSearch.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Visualise From Saved Search"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you select the 'Syslog Messages' save search you will immediately be taken to the Visualization screen with a vertical bar chart showing a single bar with the total count of all messages. Here we want to customise the visualisation to display the count of messages over time so we first need to define the X-axis as a 'Date Histogram' as shown below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-VisualiseDateHistogram.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Visualise Date Histogram"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With these settings in place, click the 'Apply Changes' button and you should immediately see a chart of the count of syslog messages over time. Note that Kibana has automatically selected an appropriate resolution of column grouping (messages 'per 30 seconds' in the example above) but that this can be changed later if required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, we want to add this chart to a new dashboard so we can have it available to us at a moments notice. To do this, we first save our visualization by clicking the 'Save Visuaization' button as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-VisualiseSaveSyslogMessagesOverTime.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Visualise Save Syslog Messages Over Time"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next we navigate to the 'Dashboard' tab and click the '+' button as prompted. Again, we selected the visualization we just saved as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-DashboardAddVisualization.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Dashboard Add Visualization"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the "Syslog Messages Over Time" visualization added, we make it a usable size by dragging the resize control (button right corner of the visualization) to extend the visualization across the width of the window as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-DashboardSizeVisualization.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Dashboard Size Visualization"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, to make it easier to see the messages the histogram refers to, we'll add a table of related Syslog messages onto our dashboard below the histogram. To do this, click the '+' button, selected 'Searches' and then our 'Syslog Messages' search. When the table is added to the dashboard, make it a similar size as the histogram as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-DashboardWithSearch.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Dashboard With Search"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once done, we need to save the dashboard so we can reload it any time we need it. Simply click the 'Save Dashboard' button as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-DashboardSaveSyslogMessages.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Dashboard Save Syslog Messages"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once saved you can bookmark the page and get back to your dashboard any time you like. Furthermore, once saved, you can monkey with the dashboard (explore the data by highlighting various areas of the chart, change time frames, set autorefresh etc) as much as you like knowing you can return to saved version any time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I have outlined how to use a Syslog capable router to send Syslog messages to Logstash and have Logstash store these messages in ElasticSearch for querying. Furthermore we then created a dashboard in which we can explore the number of Syslog messages we received over various timeframes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next post we'll increase the granularity of the messages we store so that we can start creating more interesting dashboard.&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>A Rip Storing Time</title>
			<link>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/ARipStoringTime</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;From a youth of misspent money, I have a moderately large DVD collection. Some 600 movies in half a dozen DVD racks take a disproportionately large space in my dining room. This year, my partner and I  decided to host Xmas dinner for the family, meaning a dining table that could host a dozen was in order and... well, you can see where this is heading. The DVDs had to go.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<guid>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/ARipStoringTime</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;From a youth of misspent money, I have a moderately large DVD collection. Some 600 movies in half a dozen DVD racks take a disproportionately large space in my dining room. This year, my partner and I  decided to host Xmas dinner for the family, meaning a dining table that could host a dozen was in order and... well, you can see where this is heading. The DVDs had to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, even though I barely watch them anymore, there are still a couple of amazing films in my collection that aren't available from the (far too changeable) online streaming services and, as such, I was reluctant to simply banish them all to the attic. Instead, I decided to undertake the monumental task of ripping them all to HDD before boxing them all up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Software&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are innumerable software solutions for ripping and transcoding DVD's... if you want to do one at a time. As you can probably appreciate, this wasn't a possibility for me or I'd still be ripping discs well into the New Year (not to mention through the Xmas dinner I'm actually doing this for). So a more, 'roll-your-own' solution was required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A bit of googling revealed &lt;a href="http://lifehacker.com/autorip-rips-dvds-and-blu-rays-as-soon-as-you-insert-th-477274988"&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; which described a mechanism for ripping discs as soon as you put them into the drive. While it was still targetting people who wanted to rip discs one at a time, it did point me towards the two pieces of software I did ultimately use:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.makemkv.com/"&gt;MakeMKV&lt;/a&gt; - for ripping the entire contents of the DVD and,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://handbrake.fr/"&gt;Handbrake&lt;/a&gt; - for transcoding source files into compressed H.264 format.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both these utilities come with CLI interfaces (details &lt;a href="http://www.makemkv.com/developers/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://handbrake.fr/docs/en/latest/cli/cli-options.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; respectively) allowing them to be automated. Furthermore, MakeMKV can run multiple instances allowing you to do your drive ripping (the long slow process) in parallel from multiple drives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Hardware&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd been intending to buy a new server for my home to be used as a Docker host because my current server is so old it simply doesn't support the required virtualization instructions. I'd had my eye on the &lt;a href="http://www.ebuyer.com/714837-dell-poweredge-t20-3708-xeon-e3-1225v3-3-2-ghz-4gb-ram-1tb-hdd-tower-t20-3708"&gt;Dell T20 Xeon E3&lt;/a&gt; but was waiting for it to drop back below the £200 (after cashback) mark. However, realising I could (temporarily) use it as a DVD ripping machine, I decided to bite the bullet and bought the T20 with an additional 4Gb of RAM for £324 (less 2% Quidco and £80 cashback).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It arrived a couple of days later and I must say I'm impressed. It's a lot of machine for the money, well built, has a copious number of USB sockets and is surprisingly fast. I installed Windows Server 2016 on this as it's the OS I intend to use for the Docker host and I thought it'd be a good practice run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To this I added the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 x 1Tb internal HDDs - configured as RAID-0 providing a fast destination for the drive rips.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4 x USB DVD-ROM drives - drives for ripping from - a couple I already had plus a &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/dp/B01B8U7JW2/ref=pe_385721_51767431_TE_dp_1"&gt;couple from Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 x 4Tb external USB HDD - destination for transcoded rips&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in, it's quite a monster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Putting it together&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike most of the out of the box software I'd found, I needed software that would do the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wait for a disc to be inserted in one of the drives&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Determine that the disc is actually a DVD video&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rip the disc to a destination folder based on the volume label of the DVD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Allow up to four concurrent rip operations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Queue ripped folders for transcoding allowing only a single transcoding operation to run at a time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the transcoded movie to the external drive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there may be software out there that does this, a couple of evening's googling didn't reveal it so, I decided a DIY job was in order. Besides, I thought the multiple producer/single consumer nature of the multiple rips/single transcoding would be a great fit for playing with &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/hh228603%28v=vs.110%29.aspx?f=255&amp;amp;MSPPError=-2147217396"&gt;Dataflow&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In relatively short order, I created &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs/DriveRipper"&gt;DriveRipper&lt;/a&gt;... and it's worked pretty well. I've been happily ripping four DVD's at a time, averaging around 12-15 DVD's an hour, with only a few small problems:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Because Dataflow enforces order of tasks throughout the pipeline (one if it's biggest strengths!) a slow rip or drive can hold up transcoding such that a queue builds up. Not a massive problem as the encoding process on the Xeon is actually pretty rapid (averaging 450fps) so it catches up with the relatively slow ripping process (about 20 minutes per disc) with ease.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some DVD's - particularly the old ones - are single sided or low quality or lack additional material or all of the above. This means that the contents of the disc is less than the 4.2Gb cut off I used for determining that a particular disc is likely to be a DVD. This can be sorted with a simple code change but I dediced to put these discs to one side for now and come back to them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some DVD's - again, particularly the olds ones - don't have a rational volume name; using terms like 'e19245' or, even worse, 'DVDVideo'. This has meant that, after the transcoding is complete, I need to rename the folders so that the contents don't get overwritten by a subsequent rip.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far I'm 150 DVD's through and just been told that the new dining room furniture is being delivered Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rip little machine, rip like wind!! Oh, wait...&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>3D Printing with the CEL Robox</title>
			<link>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/3DPrintingWithTheCelRobox</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;So, I've wanted a 3D printer for a while and recently a perfect storm of events meant I finally took the plunge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<enclosure url="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/y3mgQk7Eo-T13uKoaK88obO48Y6pzP0KHelfDJwLdORXiP6nnbplZzVSqbrBCBPh9bTpRgyynkyjS9mY53_ZE1f0NDpBcuKTDB7Jf6_a2me30twiv6CGRB6lQjK6Lu-DKkn6LTWVHSq463duCG-820-pQKTQ_q5ifVlXN40_86622Q%253Fwidth=965&amp;height=292&amp;cropmode=none" length="0" type="image" />
			<guid>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/3DPrintingWithTheCelRobox</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;So, I've wanted a 3D printer for a while and recently a perfect storm of events meant I finally took the plunge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had hit a wall in my MonsterPi project trying to mount a RaspberryPi in a constrained space (more on this in a subsequent post). Most of my usual hacks (you'd be amazed what you can do with a sheet of acrylic and a Meccano set) simply wouldn't cut it and I was considering abandoning the project. Without intentionally meaning to, I found myself looking at 3D printers on &lt;a href="http://www.maplin.co.uk/c/gadgets-toys-and-hobbies/3d-printers"&gt;Maplin's website&lt;/a&gt; and saw that they were selling 'used' 3D printers at quite a discount.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a quick look around for reviews I found that one of the models Maplin were selling - the &lt;a href="http://www.maplin.co.uk/p/cel-robox-3d-printer-used-b81qq"&gt;CEL Robox&lt;/a&gt; - was listed as one of the best "Plug 'n' play" printers on &lt;a href="https://www.3dhubs.com/best-3d-printer-guide#plugnplay-cel-robox"&gt;3D Hubs&lt;/a&gt;. Moreover, my local (well, 15 miles away) Maplin's store had one in stock. But there was that 'used' thing. From what I'd gathered, getting a 3D printer to print reliably is tricky at the best of times, and I was thinking of buying one that had already been used and returned or worse, didn't even work in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Too intrigued not to dig a little deeper, I gave Maplin a call. Now experience has lead me not to expect too much from Maplin's employees - at best they're well meaning but witless, at worst they think you are -  but this time proved to be an exception. The guy who answered the phone was superb (note to self: must tweet Maplin about how great this guy is). Although he initially seemed confused about not having a used model of the 3D printer in store, he checked the website to confirm availability then the store stock levels to work out what was going on. Turns out the 'used' printer they had was actually the display model and after noting that he was unsure of the history of the printer he offered to make a couple of calls to other staff to find out the condition and how much it had been used then call me back; as I said, he was excellent. As promised, he called back in 15 minutes or so having confirmed that the printer had only been used to print a few example models and had otherwise sat idle for almost a year. Unfortunately in that time it had garnered a few scratches and lost it's box and support material but, having talked to his manager, he would be able to offer a further discount on the used price if I wanted to come in a take a look at it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the store an hour later it turned out that the guy I had talked to was actually the store manager and was really going the extra mile. By the time I had turned up, he had collated replacement components (power lead, usb lead, brushes, etc) from store stock and had the printer out ready for me to inspect. Amusingly, he had his staff so well organised that, seeing a few components laying around, they had actually put them all back on the shelves so he had to go collect them all again - but I couldn't help but be impressed. Anyway, the scratches turned out to be superfluous, the offer of an additional discount very attractive and the store manager's assurances that should anything be wrong with the unit he'd ensure it was replaced no questions asked very persuasive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I bought it, brought it home and, once the baby was safely ensconced at nursery the next day, set it up and set about calibrating it. The unit itself is a thing of beauty. Bold lines and colours with smooth, solid feeling mechanical components and a general air of quality; not at all what I've come to expect from a &lt;a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/robox/robox-desktop-3d-printer-and-micro-manufacturing-p"&gt;Kickstarter funded project&lt;/a&gt;. While I was initially wary of buying a 3D printer that used a proprietary "chipped" spool for fear of a lock-in to an expensive source of filament, the integrated nature of the spool into the body of the unit and the intelligence it provides to the software - everything from how much spool is left to how much a particular model will cost to print - is fantastic. Far from other "hobbyist" 3D printers where filament projects precariously around the unit, the feed of filament to the head is completely hidden from view and loading of filament completely automated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately calibration wasn't quite as smooth and it took a long time to get the printer ready to actually try printing a model. In fact, despite repeatedly trying and following all suggestions, one of the calibration tests - the needle valve opening calibration for the fill nozzle - stoically refused to run successfully. This may have been the result of the unit sitting idle for so long or simply me not setting it up right but the failure to pass this test was extremely worrisome. Even the 'purge' material test (used to completely empty the print heads when you're planning on changing material) failed to lay down material as it should but this was mostly resolved by vigorously cleaning the print bed with the isopropyl alcohol.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, despite the needle valve opening calibration still failing, I decided to print a model to see how it would perform before deciding whether or not to return the unit. From CEL's downloadable samples, I decided to try printing the 'cargo-box' as it didn't seem to require too much filament and a small container is always useful for something. Actually loading and starting to print a model using CEL's &lt;a href="http://www.cel-robox.com/downloads/"&gt;AutoMaker&lt;/a&gt; software is ludicrously simple: start a new layout, load a model, choose the granularity of the print, go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Watching a 3D model being printed is really something to behold. Despite it taking hours "like watching a 3D printer fabricate" should really become the metaphorical antonym to "like watching paint dry"; from the initial outline of the print being laid on the print bed, to seeing a solid object emerge, the process is fascinating. Taking a virtual object modelled on your computer and seeing that object take shape and become a physical object in the real world is thrilling, with innumerable possibilities opening up with every layer of filament laid down.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short order (well, actually 'long order' but it certainly didn't feel that way) and with much amazement and relief, the print was finished perfectly. A 1.5" square, green plastic cargo-box sat inside the Robox; I had fabricated a solid object from - seemingly - nothing. Once the unit had cooled the heated print-bed and unlocked the door, I tried removing the box, entirely expecting to have to lever and peel the plastic off the bed. To my surprise it moved easily, seemingly held to the bed by nothing more than a static charge. I was further surprised by the strength of the box; given it was made from nothing more than melted strands of plastic, I absolutely expected the fabricated object to have the tensile strength of a faberge egg. Yet it was incredibly rigid and inflexible, only the tell-tale layering giving away the fact that it had been 3D printer rather than cast in an industrial manufacturing plant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://0ohhnq.dm2302.livefilestore.com/y3mzj-a64dzTwhL7kVdtCG_OooHuVEnWyP5gynRF28lVCG247INMKuJpO8E2neQaekUtsZINVLDxnr5iwvoFRVqrOysfCj5ouJTt3e9oNYAOlrvaV2V7FquQultYnqicCjLCpdtiUF1NCeS5hfzgoXL5KhtZ2iBMvDpnslKBEX86FI?width=1024&amp;amp;height=576&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="My first 3D printed object"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now it was time to see if I could use the printer for the purpose I bought it: fabricating custom components for other projects. First up was a bracket to hold a RaspberryPi and other components in a very specific configuration. &lt;a href="http://www.sketchup.com/products/sketchup-pro/new-in-2016?gclid=CIK4ks2Cy88CFc0y0wodZmwHaQ"&gt;SketchUp&lt;/a&gt; has been my go-to 3D modelling software of choice since being bought and given away by Google. It is amazingly quick and easy to use for almost everything except extremely precise components with low tolerances; i.e. exactly the kind of thing I needed to do. So I went about looking for alternatives and quickly settled on the free version of &lt;a href="https://www.rs-online.com/designspark/mechanical-software"&gt;DesignSpark Mechanical from RS Components&lt;/a&gt;. Despite some quirkiness in it's UI, it provides most of the features and ease of use of SketchUp with several digits of precision for designed components. Indeed, instead of using a mouse to try to get the exact length of an edge, you can simply enter the length you want on the keyboard; precisely the functionality I thought was missing from SketchUp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took several hours to complete the 3D model for the bracket I needed - somewhat due to DesignSpark's learning curve but mostly the precise measurements and imprecise iteration required to design a bracket that would hold all the components just so - but eventually it was ready to print. Again, friction from design software to print ready was minimal. DesignSpark is able to export in the standard STL format and AutoMaker loaded the model and positioned it on the print-bed automatically, promising to fabricate me a completely custom component for just £1.48's worth of material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I set the print going but was quickly dismayed that the first layer of the print wasn't being laid properly at the far corners of the bed, mostly due to the fact that the corners of the bed away from the tabs that hold it in place had risen slightly. Regardless, I decided to let the print continue and see if subsequent layers would adhere to the small smudge of material the print head had managed to deposit. This turned out to be the right choice as by layer three the base of the bracket was fully formed and the printer had started using the "fill" nozzle to quickly start filling out further layers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took about three hours to design and an hour and forty minutes to fabricate, but the bracket fitted perfectly and was easily strong enough to hold all the components in the configuration I needed. I was a very happy boy and immediately starting to design a subsequent bracket I needed for the same project and plan for a load of other custom bits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, if you're thinking of buying a 3D printer and can afford what is - regardless of the heavy discount - an expensive bit of technology, I would absolutely recommend going for it. The possibilities of what you can create are mind-boggling and the sensation of watching them come into existence exhilarating. Being able to fabricate components I previously had to hack together from off the shelf bits is tremendously empowering and I can unashamedly say that I am completely hooked on 3D printing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, while I have no direct experience of other 3D printers, I wouldn't hesitate to recommend CEL's Robox printer as - despite still failing the nozzle calibration - it has yet to fail a print and the software is remarkably straight forward and easy to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch this space for more adventures in 3D printing as I integrate my new found fabrication abilities into my innumerable ongoing projects. First up: MonsterPi.&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>A sentiment(al) analysis of why Red Dwarf is no longer funny</title>
			<link>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/ASentimentalAnalysisOfRedDwarf</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I had a lot of fun playing with &lt;a href="http://jupyter.org/"&gt;Project Jupyter&lt;/a&gt;. For those that aren't aware of this project, it's an effort to provide a workspace for performing repeatable experimentation with data. In short it mixes markdown editing capabilities with a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Read%E2%80%93eval%E2%80%93print_loop"&gt;REPL&lt;/a&gt; environment for a large number of languages. From the website:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<guid>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/ASentimentalAnalysisOfRedDwarf</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I had a lot of fun playing with &lt;a href="http://jupyter.org/"&gt;Project Jupyter&lt;/a&gt;. For those that aren't aware of this project, it's an effort to provide a workspace for performing repeatable experimentation with data. In short it mixes markdown editing capabilities with a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Read%E2%80%93eval%E2%80%93print_loop"&gt;REPL&lt;/a&gt; environment for a large number of languages. From the website:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"a web application that allows you to create and share documents that contain live code, equations, visualizations and explanatory text. Uses include: data cleaning and transformation, numerical simulation, statistical modeling, machine learning and much more"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After having my interest tweaked by the &lt;a href="https://try.jupyter.org/"&gt;browser version&lt;/a&gt; I bit the bullet and spent ages downloading and installing the &lt;a href="http://jupyter.org/install.html"&gt;full version&lt;/a&gt; to a virtual machine. It's a Python based web-app so requires quite a bit of setup and unfortunately I found the documentation to be a bit sparse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so it was that while trying to work out how to install the &lt;a href="https://github.com/fsprojects/IfSharp"&gt;FSharp module&lt;/a&gt; I came across &lt;a href="https://notebooks.azure.com/"&gt;Azure Notebooks&lt;/a&gt;. This is a free, Azure hosted version of Jupyter that has almost all the features of a local installation but with none of the faff. After quickly spinning up a new notebook here I didn't even look back at the local installation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A Jupyter [Data] Mining Core Project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As per the title and lead of this post, I decided to use Jupyter to have a little fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in September, while grinding my way through &lt;a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0094535/episodes?season=11&amp;amp;ref_=tt_eps_sn_11"&gt;season 11 of Red Dwarf&lt;/a&gt;, I began to wonder why it wasn't as funny as it used to be. Had the writing deteriorated? Were the actors past it? Or were these elements still as great as they used to be and it was me who had changed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started thinking about ways this could be investigated such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using IMDB rating as a measure of humour in each episode of Red Dwarf&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Performing semantic analysis of episode's transcript to see if the sentiment had changed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using word-count to determine whether there was a correlation between character participation and overall humour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, it was a funny notion and provided a pleasant distraction from the &lt;a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt5218266"&gt;pretty awful episode&lt;/a&gt; of Red Dwarf I was watching at the time. I added it to my "ideas" list in &lt;a href="https://trello.com/b/KoTWuFUi/public-board"&gt;Trello&lt;/a&gt;, finished the episode and went to bed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, when I came across Project Jupyter, I knew it'd be a great medium for performing this investigation so shifted the analysis from "Ideas" to "In progress" and got cracking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Data Science using F#&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, while in relation to this investigation I use the term "data science" to basically mean "munging a few numbers and drawing a few graphs", I do think F# makes a fantastic language for the discipline in general. It has some incredible mechanisms for &lt;a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/articles/fsharp/tutorials/type-providers/"&gt;acquiring&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://fsharpforfunandprofit.com/posts/the-option-type/"&gt;cleaning&lt;/a&gt; data as well as for &lt;a href="http://www.quanttec.com/fparsec/"&gt;parsing natural language&lt;/a&gt;. Couple this with it's concise, functional, elegant language and the ability to leverage components from the entire breadth of .NET ecosystem and you have quite a significant offering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Azure Notebooks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Azure implementation of Project Jupyter is first class and, for now at least, totally free. Getting started is as simple as logging in with Microsoft credentials and then clicking 'Add notebook'. Being an MS implementation, I used Edge to edit the notebook and found the experience extremely robust, especially given it's a "Preview" program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact I experience just two issues while authoring my notebook:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data Store - It's not currently possible to upload or store data within the Azure notebook library (despite having functionality to do this in the web-interface). Instead you need to host your data on one of a small number of whitelisted sites. Fortunately Github is one of these sites so this doesn't prove to be much of an issue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Packages - While Azure Notebooks provides access to a large number of packages "out-of-the-box" (i.e. FSharp.Data, XPlot.Plotly, etc) it can be tricky to add/use other packages. For example, I wanted to use the XPlot.GoogleCharts package (as it provided trendline capabilities) and ended up having to write a custom display printer for it to work (due to an &lt;a href="https://github.com/fsprojects/IfSharp/issues/118"&gt;open issue&lt;/a&gt; on Github).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from these issues, authoring and scripting F# in an Azure Notebook was almost as fast as using &lt;a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/articles/fsharp/tutorials/fsharp-interactive/"&gt;"F# Interactive"&lt;/a&gt;. It even provides Intellisense capabilities but, in practice, these are usually too slow to be of actual use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Sharing Notebooks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From Azure Notebooks you're able to download your notebook as a native ".ipynb" file (in fact this is encouraged as MS reserves the right to remove unused notebooks after 60 days). You can then share this file to other people who have Jupyter installed or, preferably, commit it to a repository in Github which has excellent support for Jupyter Notebooks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find my notebook "A sentiment(al) analysis of why Red Dwarf is no longer funny (to me)" &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs/RedDwarfAnalysis/blob/master/Investigation.ipynb"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. As you will see when you click the link, Github not only shows you the static parts of the notebook but actually tries to spin up a kernel and execute the code parts too. This is a "limited rendering only" so Github also provides a link to open the notebook in 'nbviewer' &lt;a href="http://nbviewer.jupyter.org/github/ibebbs/RedDwarfAnalysis/blob/2712285e1f9c69fc347bdfe6404792101eaea5f1/Investigation.ipynb"&gt;web-app&lt;/a&gt;. This link is shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://mvpfyw-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3mppldGfaYEhvWkV7mdUw26-lP3SOzlMTGFbf8slchIfjBL57IH-GrJev6ai_rISiHBKrom7Abg9YFjfhZ1ArOFT7a7mh4gJuGq-CErv1dun48GQC_BdhMV08fh6hbw400d9nHSEXJ0jA2nPBIrpOPNrOz0I3lVY1tu_L656ylQKg?width=660&amp;amp;height=283&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:660; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Open external view with nbviewer"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The analysis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had timeboxed my investigation into Project Jupyter and therefore didn't get round to performing an actual sentiment anaylsis of the content of each episode. However I did manage to do the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Programmatically download episode information from several sources in JSON format and use &lt;a href="http://fsharp.github.io/FSharp.Data/library/JsonValue.html"&gt;JsonValue&lt;/a&gt; to dynamically query these sources&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scrape demographically categorized rating information from IMDB and use &lt;a href="http://fsharp.github.io/FSharp.Data/reference/fsharp-data-htmldocument.html"&gt;HtmlDocument&lt;/a&gt; to parse the data into strong types&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Resolve issue with rendering XPlot.GoogleCharts charts within the notebook and use these charts to provide an interactive visualisation of the decline in rating of Red Dwarf across time and demographic categories.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This provided a fair stab at correlating episode rating with the overall decline in Red Dwarf's humourousness but is a long way short of any form of "data science". It was both enlightening and a lot of fun doing this small project and I will certainly consider Azure Notebooks as a valuable tool in my toolbox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should I find the time, I would certainly like to return to this project and use &lt;a href="http://www.quanttec.com/fparsec/"&gt;FParsec&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://azure.microsoft.com/en-gb/services/cognitive-services/text-analytics/"&gt;Azure Text Analytics&lt;/a&gt; to perform an actual sentiment analysis. Hopefully it'll overturn, or at least help justify, my somewhat disturbing conclusion!&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Reactive Behaviors</title>
			<link>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/ReactiveBehaviors</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;I am a firm believer in the notion "&lt;a href="http://slides.com/robwormald/everything-is-a-stream#/" title="Everything is a stream - Rob Wormald"&gt;Everything&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/staltz/868e7e9bc2a7b8c1f754" title="The introduction to Reactive Programming you've been missing - andrestaltz"&gt;is&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://weareadaptive.com/blog/2014/05/05/everything-is-a-stream/" title="Reactive Trader 2: Everything is a Stream - Matt Barrett"&gt;a&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://colintheshots.com/blog/?p=85" title="Be Reactive - Colintheshots"&gt;stream&lt;/a&gt;". After all, at it's root what is a computer program but a stream of instructions toggling the state of transistors on the CPU die. As such, I have been gradually moving away from traditional imperative coding and embracing a declarative approach to implementing behavior.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<guid>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/ReactiveBehaviors</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2015 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;I am a firm believer in the notion "&lt;a href="http://slides.com/robwormald/everything-is-a-stream#/" title="Everything is a stream - Rob Wormald"&gt;Everything&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/staltz/868e7e9bc2a7b8c1f754" title="The introduction to Reactive Programming you've been missing - andrestaltz"&gt;is&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://weareadaptive.com/blog/2014/05/05/everything-is-a-stream/" title="Reactive Trader 2: Everything is a Stream - Matt Barrett"&gt;a&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://colintheshots.com/blog/?p=85" title="Be Reactive - Colintheshots"&gt;stream&lt;/a&gt;". After all, at it's root what is a computer program but a stream of instructions toggling the state of transistors on the CPU die. As such, I have been gradually moving away from traditional imperative coding and embracing a declarative approach to implementing behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting with the UI, my &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs/Caliburn.Micro.Reactive.Extensions" title="Caliburn.Micro.Reactive.Extensions Github Repository"&gt;Reactive Extensions for Caliburn Micro&lt;/a&gt; allowed me to escape the scourge of state variables and property change non-sense and have read-model changes update the view or user input changes update the view model in a declarative fashion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this in place, I sort of stumbled onto a pattern I quite liked and gradually developed into a pattern I am now referring to as "Reactive Behaviors". To explain this pattern, lets take a basic example of a log in page for an application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, in WPF MVVM parlance, the view model for the log in page might look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;public class LogInPageViewModel : Screen, ILogInPageViewModel
{
    private readonly IAuthenticationService _authenticationService;

    private readonly DelegateCommand _logInCommand;
    private readonly DelegateCommand _cancelCommand;

    private CancellationTokenSource _cts;

    private string _username;
    private string _password;
    private string _error;

    public LogInPageViewModel(IAuthenticationService authenticationService)
    {
        _authenticationService = authenticationService;

        _cts = new CancellationTokenSource();
        _logInCommand = new DelegateCommand(CanLogIn, PerformLogIn);
        _cancelCommand = new DelegateCommand(_ =&amp;gt; true, CancelLogIn);
    }

    public void Dispose()
    {
        if (_cts != null)
        {
            _cts.Cancel();
            _cts.Dispose();
            _cts = null;
        }
    }

    private bool CanLogIn(object parameter)
    {
        return (!string.IsNullOrWhiteSpace(_username) &amp;amp;&amp;amp; !string.IsNullOrWhiteSpace(_password));
    }

    private async void PerformLogIn(object parameter)
    {
        AuthenticationResponse response = await _authenticationService.AuthenticateAsync(new AuthenticationRequest(_username, _password), _cts.Token);

        if (response.Successful)
        {
            TryClose(true);
        }
        else
        {
            Error = response.Error.Message;
        }
    }

    private void CancelLogIn(object parameter)
    {
        TryClose(false);
    }

    public string Username
    {
        get { return _username; }
        set
        {
            if (!string.Equals(value, _username))
            {
                _username = value;

                NotifyOfPropertyChange(() =&amp;gt; Username);

                _logInCommand.RaiseCanExecuteChanged();
            }
        }
    }

    public string Password
    {
        get { return _password; }
        set
        {
            if (!string.Equals(value, _password))
            {
                _password = value;

                NotifyOfPropertyChange(() =&amp;gt; Password);

                _logInCommand.RaiseCanExecuteChanged();
            }
        }
    }

    public string Error
    {
        get { return _error; }
        private set
        {
            if (!string.Equals(value, _error))
            {
                _error = value;

                NotifyOfPropertyChange(() =&amp;gt; Error);
            }
        }
    }

    public ICommand LogInCommand
    {
        get { return _logInCommand; }
    }
}

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we can see, we have a bunch of state variables that are updated from property setters and when certain state variables are updated we need to perform specific actions. Now, can you quickly identify all the behaviors of this view model?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, it's not a complicated view model so it'll probably just take a few minutes to work out the behaviors. To summarize, they are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When the user has entered a value in both the user name and password text boxes then enable the "Log in" button&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When the user clicks the "Log in" button, asynchronously attempt to log in with the supplied credentials.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When a successful login attempt is made, close the dialog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When an unsuccessful login attempt is made, display an error&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When the user clicks the "Cancel" button, close the dialog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that took a few minutes of scanning back and forth over the class right? Also, while we have been good developers and applied DRY by centralizing the logic to determine when the log in button should be enabled, in order to know under what circumstances the logic will be called, we need to perform a "Find References" on the method. The cause and effect of this behavior are &lt;strong&gt;disassociated&lt;/strong&gt;. In fact, in this instance it's event worse, as this method is only passed to the &lt;code&gt;DelegateCommand&lt;/code&gt; instance, we have to &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; that the &lt;code&gt;DelegateCommand&lt;/code&gt; will invoke this method everytime the &lt;code&gt;RaiseCanExecuteChanged&lt;/code&gt; is called &lt;em&gt;and then&lt;/em&gt; perform another "Find References" to find all the locations &lt;code&gt;RaiseCanExecuteChanged&lt;/code&gt; is called. Phew!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wouldn't it be better if we could somehow centralize this logic in discreet methods with names that describe exactly the behavior of the class? Ladies and gentlemen, I present to you the same class re-written using "Reactive Behaviors":&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;public class LogInPageViewModel : Screen, ILogInPageViewModel
{
    private readonly IAuthenticationService _authenticationService;

    private ObservableProperty&amp;lt;string&amp;gt; _username;
    private ObservableProperty&amp;lt;string&amp;gt; _password;
    private ObservableProperty&amp;lt;string&amp;gt; _error;
    private ObservableCommand _logInCommand;
    private ObservableCommand _cancelCommand;

    private Subject&amp;lt;AuthenticationResponse&amp;gt; _logInResponse;

    private IDisposable _behaviors;

    public LogInPageViewModel(IAuthenticationService authenticationService)
    {
        _authenticationService = authenticationService;

        _username = new ObservableProperty&amp;lt;string&amp;gt;(this, () =&amp;gt; Username);
        _password = new ObservableProperty&amp;lt;string&amp;gt;(this, () =&amp;gt; Password);
        _error = new ObservableProperty&amp;lt;string&amp;gt;(this, () =&amp;gt; Error);
        _logInCommand = new ObservableCommand();
        _cancelCommand = new ObservableCommand();

        _logInResponse = new Subject&amp;lt;AuthenticationResponse&amp;gt;();

        _behaviors = new CompositeDisposable(
            WhenTheUserHasEnteredBothUsernameAndPasswordThenEnableLogInButton(),
            WhenTheUserClicksTheLogInButtonAttemptToLogIn(),
            WhenASuccessfulLogInAttemptIsMadeCloseTheDialog(),
            WhenAnUnsuccessfulLogInAttemptIsMadeDisplayTheError(),
            WhenTheUserClicksTheCancelButtonCloseTheDialog()
        );
    }

    public void Dispose()
    {
        if (_behaviors != null)
        {
            _behaviors.Dispose();
            _behaviors = null;
        }
    }

    private IDisposable WhenTheUserHasEnteredBothUsernameAndPasswordThenEnableLogInButton()
    {
        return Observable
            .CombineLatest(_username, _password, (username, password) =&amp;gt; !string.IsNullOrWhiteSpace(username) &amp;amp;&amp;amp; !string.IsNullOrWhiteSpace(password))
            .Subscribe(_logInCommand);
    }

    private IDisposable WhenTheUserClicksTheLogInButtonAttemptToLogIn()
    {
        return _logInCommand
            .SelectMany(_ =&amp;gt; Observable.CombineLatest(_username, _password, (username, password) =&amp;gt; new AuthenticationRequest(username, password)).Take(1))
            .SelectMany(request =&amp;gt; _authenticationService.AuthenticateAsync(request))
            .Subscribe(_logInResponse);
    }

    private IDisposable WhenASuccessfulLogInAttemptIsMadeCloseTheDialog()
    {
        return _logInResponse
            .Where(response =&amp;gt; response.Successful)
            .Subscribe(response =&amp;gt; TryClose(true));
    }

    private IDisposable WhenAnUnsuccessfulLogInAttemptIsMadeDisplayTheError()
    {
        return _logInResponse
            .Where(response =&amp;gt; !response.Successful)
            .Select(response =&amp;gt; response.Error.Message)
            .Subscribe(_error);
    }

    private IDisposable WhenTheUserClicksTheCancelButtonCloseTheDialog()
    {
        return _cancelCommand
            .Subscribe(_ =&amp;gt; TryClose(false));
    }

    public string Username
    {
        get { return _username.Get(); }
        set { _username.Set(value); }
    }

    public string Password
    {
        get { return _password.Get(); }
        set { _password.Set(value); }
    }

    public string Error
    {
        get { return _error.Get(); }
    }

    public ICommand LogInCommand
    {
        get { return _logInCommand; }
    }

    public ICommand CancelCommand
    {
        get { return _cancelCommand; }
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As shown, the constructor instantiates a &lt;code&gt;CompositeDisposable&lt;/code&gt; containing calls to methods implementing the behavior of the class and which return an &lt;code&gt;IDisposable&lt;/code&gt; that, when disposed, will tear down the behavior. Each method is named after exactly one desired behavior and comprises a subscription to all the required inputs for the behavior, a series of projections which implement the behavior and, finally, a subscription which surfaces the result of the behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lets take the example of the &lt;code&gt;WhenTheUserHasEnteredBothUsernameAndPasswordThenEnableLogInButton&lt;/code&gt; method. Here we subscribe to both the &lt;code&gt;_username&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;_password&lt;/code&gt; properties, and use a selector function to return a boolean indicating whether they're both populated. The &lt;code&gt;_logInCommand&lt;/code&gt; subscribes to the result which will enable or disable the command (by raising CanExecuteChanged events) appropriately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, by leveraging Observables we become thread safe. It doesn't matter on which thread the source properties are updated from, the behavior will be performed and output applied without the risk of missing values or race-conditions between updates to the appropriate inputs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With behaviors implemented in this fashion, behavioral unit testing becomes incredibly obvious. Simply copy the behavior method names into your test fixture and assert that it performs as expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe this pattern provides numerous benefits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Promotes behavior driven development and unit testing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Promotes functional and thread safe programming practises.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reduces the risk of (and if done well, can eliminate) side effects as specific behaviors are isolated in a single well named method.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stops 'code rot' as all behavior is encapsulated within specifically named methods. Want new behaviour? Add a new method. Don't want a specific behavior anymore? Just removed it. Want a specific behavior to change? Change the one method and know that you haven't broken anything else.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provides concise mechanisms for aggregating multiple inputs and promotes asynchronous processes to first-class status.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reduces the need for utility classes as data can be passed through the pipeline as strongly typed anonymous classes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prevents memory leaks as all behaviors return a disposable that when disposed removes all subscriptions and disposed all managed resources.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this example targets the UI and leverages Caliburn Micro with Reactive Extensions for projection to IObservable&lt;t&gt; instances (and property change notification), this pattern can be employed across any class which treats inputs and outputs as a stream.&lt;/t&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been employing this pattern very successfully across a variety of functional layers for quite some time now. I'd be really interested to hear your thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code for above examples available on &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs/Blog.ReactiveBehaviors" title="ReactiveBehaviors Repository on Github"&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Home Network Monitoring - Part II</title>
			<link>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/HomeNetworkMonitoring-PartII</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;In part one of this series I set up my home router to send a variety of Syslog messages to LogStash which then forwarded these messages to ElasticSearch for indexing and querying by Kibana in a simplistic dashboard. In this post, I'm going to start parsing out some of the details of the Syslog messages to start giving us a clearer idea about which devices on my local network are opening sessions with remote servers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<guid>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/HomeNetworkMonitoring-PartII</guid>
			<pubDate>Sun, 10 Apr 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;In part one of this series I set up my home router to send a variety of Syslog messages to LogStash which then forwarded these messages to ElasticSearch for indexing and querying by Kibana in a simplistic dashboard. In this post, I'm going to start parsing out some of the details of the Syslog messages to start giving us a clearer idea about which devices on my local network are opening sessions with remote servers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;message types&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My router sends a number of different messages types; everything from router/dsl bandwidth information to the firewall log as can be seen below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/DrayTek-Syslog.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="DrayTek Syslog Administration"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, I'm really only interested in the 'User Access Log' which tells us when a local device resolves an IP address for a domain name or accesses a remote server. This log constitutes a number of message types such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;TCP / UDP access
This message is sent by the router when a device on the local network accesses a remote server via TCP or UDP. It looks like this: &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;150&amp;gt;Apr 10 16:55:38 Vigor: Local User (MAC=00-00-00-00-00-00): 192.168.1.205:64281 -&amp;gt; 5.10.110.36:80 (TCP)Web&lt;/code&gt;. From this type of message I am interested in parsing out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Syslog timestamp&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Syslog username&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Source Mac Address&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Source IP Address&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Destination IP Address&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Protocol&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;DNS lookup
This message is sent by the router when a device on the local network resolves an IP address for a remote server DNS nane. It looks like this: &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;150&amp;gt;Apr 10 18:52:49 Vigor: Local User (MAC=00-00-00-00-00-00): 192.168.1.62 DNS -&amp;gt; 192.168.1.1 inquire a.root-servers.net&lt;/code&gt;. From this type of message I am interested in parsing out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Syslog timestamp&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Syslog username&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Source Mac Address&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Source IP Address&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Domain being resolved&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I'll focus on enriching the incoming message with information from the access message but will move on to parsing multiple message types in a future post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;parsing access messages&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Logstash provides a great tool for parsing messages: the 'grok' filter. As explained in &lt;a href="https://www.elastic.co/guide/en/logstash/current/plugins-filters-grok.html"&gt;the documentation&lt;/a&gt; 'grok' allows you to 'Parse arbitrary text and structure it. This tool is perfect for syslog logs, apache and other webserver logs, mysql logs, and in general, any log format that is generally written for humans and not computer consumption.'&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This filter applies a regular expression like patterns to a field in the incoming message and, if matched successfully, adds each matched expression to the message being processed as a new field. The fields to capture are defined in the format &lt;code&gt;%{SYNTAX:SEMANTIC}&lt;/code&gt; where the &lt;code&gt;SYNTAX&lt;/code&gt; element is a known pattern (see below) or a regular expression and the &lt;code&gt;SEMANTIC&lt;/code&gt; is a name of the field to capture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Logstash ships with over 120 known &lt;code&gt;SYNTAX&lt;/code&gt; patterns and these patterns can be supplemented by adding new pattern files to a specific directory. However, the default patterns supplied cover nearly all common scenarios and allow almost all the pertinent information in the TCP access message above to be parsed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, by just using the default patterns, I can write the expression&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;%{POSINT:syslog_pri}&amp;gt;%{SYSLOGTIMESTAMP:syslog_timestamp} Vigor\: Local User \(MAC=%{MAC:source_mac}\): %{IP:source_address}(?::%{POSINT:source_port})? -&amp;gt; %{IP:destination_address}(?::%{POSINT:destination_port})?
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which gives us the following additional fields in the message:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;|field|value|
|-----|-----|
|source_address|192.168.1.205|
|source_port|64281|
|source_mac|00-00-00-00-00-00|
|syslog_pri|150|
|syslog_timestamp|Apr·10·16:55:38|
|destination_address|5.10.110.36|
|destination_port|80|&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neat huh! I'd also like to know whether the access message is TCP or UDP so I'm going to add a custom regular expression to the end of the pattern to parse the protocol string out of the message. In full the pattern is now:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;%{POSINT:syslog_pri}&amp;gt;%{SYSLOGTIMESTAMP:syslog_timestamp} Vigor\: Local User \(MAC=%{MAC:source_mac}\): %{IP:source_address}(?::%{POSINT:source_port})? -&amp;gt; %{IP:destination_address}(?::%{POSINT:destination_port})? \((?&amp;lt;protocol&amp;gt;TCP|UDP)\)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This would result in the following fields available in the message:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;|field|value|
|-----|-----|
|source_address|192.168.1.205|
|source_port|64281|
|source_mac|00-00-00-00-00-00|
|syslog_pri|150|
|syslog_timestamp|Apr·10·16:55:38|
|destination_address|5.10.110.36|
|destination_port|80|
|&lt;strong&gt;protocol&lt;/strong&gt;|&lt;strong&gt;TCP&lt;/strong&gt;|&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NOTE: You can use &lt;a href="http://grokconstructor.appspot.com/"&gt;Grok Constructor&lt;/a&gt; to help you perfect your grok expressions prior to trying them in Logstash&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;adding the grok filter to logstash&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, now I know how to extract all the information I'm interested in from the access message, I need to get Logstash to actually do it. This is done by adding a &lt;code&gt;grok&lt;/code&gt; filter to the &lt;code&gt;filter { }&lt;/code&gt; section of the &lt;code&gt;syslog.config&lt;/code&gt; file authored in the previous post as shown here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;input {
  tcp {
    port =&amp;gt; 5000
    type =&amp;gt; syslog
  }
  udp {
    port =&amp;gt; 5000
    type =&amp;gt; syslog
  }
}

filter {
    grok {
      match =&amp;gt; [ "message", "&amp;lt;%{POSINT:syslog_pri}&amp;gt;%{SYSLOGTIMESTAMP:syslog_timestamp} Vigor\: Local User \(MAC=%{MAC:source_mac}\): %{IP:source_address}(?::%{POSINT:source_port})? -&amp;gt; %{IP:destination_address}(?::%{POSINT:destination_port})? \((?&amp;lt;protocol&amp;gt;TCP|UDP)\)" ]
    }
}

output {
  elasticsearch {
    hosts =&amp;gt; ["192.168.1.30:9200"]
    index =&amp;gt; "syslog-%{+YYYY.MM.dd}"
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice the grok section in which we specify a 'match' field. This field takes an array of two strings; the first string is the field containing the text to match and the second is the pattern to match the text to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once this is added to the &lt;code&gt;syslog.config&lt;/code&gt; file and Logstash restarted, these new fields should be being written to ElasticSearch. The easiest way to see if this is working is to return to Kibana and, from the 'Settings/Indices' area, click the 'syslog-*' pattern on the left and then click the orange 'Refresh field list' button and the field list appears like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-RefreshSyslogIndex.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Refresh Syslog Index"&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;exploring network access information&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the additional fields are available to Kibana, I can start exploring the data to learn about which devices on my network are access which remote servers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do this I first need to add the new fields to the 'Syslog Messages' saved search. This can be done by navigating to the 'Discover' page, loading the 'Syslog Messages' search (using the 'Load Saved Search' button in the top right of the screen), adding the new fields and re-saving it. This is shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-AddingNewFieldsToSyslogMessagesSavedSearch.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Adding New Fields To Syslog Messages Saved Search"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm now able to add some very interesting new visualizations to our dashboard such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Number of access by each local device&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Number of access by port&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Number of access to each remote server&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Number of access by protocol&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll only run through adding the first visualization is they're all very similar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I navigate to the 'Visualization' area and click the 'New Visualization' button. I want to see the number of accesses being made by each device as a fraction of the whole so will use a donut chart. This is done by selecting 'Pie chart' from the "Create new Visualization" menu and selecting our 'Syslog Messages' saved search in the "Select a search source" menu. Once this is done, I get a pie chart with a single section as shown here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-NewPieChartVisualization.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana New Pie Chart Visualization"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then need to select the 'Split Slices' bucket type, choose 'Terms' as the aggregation type and finally select 'source_address' as the field on which to aggregate (i.e. count) unique terms. Applying this to the pie-chart (using the 'Apply' button) results in the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-SplitSlicePieChartUsingSourceAddress.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Split Slice Pie Chart Using Source  ddres s"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll  then  turn  this into a donut chart by ticking the 'Donut' check box from the 'Options' area as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-SplitSliceDonutChartUsingSourceAddress.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Split Slice Donut Chart Using Source Address"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I'll use the same process for adding donut charts for each of the other metrics outlined above and add all the charts to my dashboard giving me the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-DashboardWithAccessCharts.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Dashboard With Access Charts"&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I showed how to extract structured information from unstructured text data in our source message. I then showed how this can be used within Kibana to highlight which devices on the local network are accessing which remote servers, on which ports and using which protocols.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next post, I'll examine how to further enhance the information we've extracted from the access messages to make it easier to relate ip address to actual devices on the network and out in the world.&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>ToddlerBox Tops 10,000 Users!!</title>
			<link>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/ToddlerBoxTopsTenThousandUsers</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;Really that got out of hand fast! I had no idea so many people would be interested in letting their toddler loose on their XBox controller. In fact, there have been many things that have surprised me about this app:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<enclosure url="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/y3mVAxtKFjUEGk7Hdhzjl4UZ2INnFdBbw9K-tnYZ8DYoJ-VoKxpAN6w8Ng0DFTYdSxpHY6IvL5-VwJpLkQl6qWRmMQXSExLXopz5CFuSxIbyaMLrnL2Vy3yPZlISAAknXZdT4HwiZJ55zg2UtKwucBL88-xHh6rn5Mh97yzfRsCPjI%253Fwidth=1024&amp;height=574&amp;cropmode=none" length="0" type="image" />
			<guid>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/ToddlerBoxTopsTenThousandUsers</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;Really that got out of hand fast! I had no idea so many people would be interested in letting their toddler loose on their XBox controller. In fact, there have been many things that have surprised me about this app:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Acquisition rate has increased&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I kind of expected an initial burst of acquisitions then a slow tail off but this hasn't happened. As it's only been a little over a month since ToddlerBox was released to the store, I guess there's every possibility that it's still in the "burst" stage and theres just more interest in apps of this type. Well, here's hoping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reviews have been extremely polarized&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost without exception, reviews have been 4-5 stars or 1 star. Also, while a couple of the 1 star ratings are to do with app functionality (it seems a couple of people have issues running even this basic UWP app) the overwhelming majority of 1 star ratings are due to peoples dislike of ads; because...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ads are a very risky business&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with most parents, I am extremely cautious about what my toddler is exposed to. Therefore I was extremely cautious about adding advertising as a means of revenue to ToddlerBox, regardless of how small or out of the way they were.
After completing the Ad-Mediation questions in the Windows Store and being assured that ads would be both age rated and not "tracking", I felt a lot better about the idea and decided a small banner ad on the instructions screen would be pretty harmless. Furthermore, throughout the process of adding the banner, I didn't see a single advert I would be concerned about putting in front of my child; most were simple flashing inbox icons or the like.
However, after discussing ToddlerBox with a friend, he decided to install it on his Xbox and I was very upset to see that the ads being displayed were both more intrusive and more "click-baity" than any I had seen previously. I am now investigating ways to generate some revenue from the app but without upsetting parents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The reviews shown in the store are not "all reviews"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the publisher of ToddlerBox, I get to see all reviews left about the app on the store. Due to all the previous points, the app is currently averaging about a 2.6 star rating across 50 odd reviews. However, when viewing the app in the Store on my friend's XBox, it was shown as having a 4.5 star rating from just 2 reviews. Now, while some of the reviews I can see are translated from foreign languages, most are in English and I'm therefore at a loss to explain why they're not being displayed when an XBox in the English local browses the store.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It's not just toddlers using ToddlerBox&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've had more than one review stating how good this game is to play after consuming various illicit substances ;0P&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, as described above, while acquisition rate has fluctuated on a daily basis, the overall trend in acquisition shows unexpected growth:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://bnljqq-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3msqT1msmkJ_32Jewx8Ysuoys0lC35GCLY-aQPyJ9YhR75KMswOLcznSPGOOBGhhsMRb6qK3_xh_qr3h1Xh-vFwmSog1_HoOS-Isj1lMoFPpuV42oAwJi3A5JiY-ToAirVoZDnz2gQ7N6jUed82zW83IZ_qQcbqWGw1ekaNh4wjBU?width=660&amp;amp;height=252&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:660px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Acquisitions over App Lifetime"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daily usage also shows that a healthy number of acquisitions are being used regularly, with nearly 800 people using ToddlerBox nearly 1700 times just yesterday (19th December):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://bnlkqq-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3mBC-i0nboWq0ibRyIcBhs1O2MnfOUx-OxTQZDUNHbh-eVRbfH0xP9-p9hLJqC82i1SBB5ZfpcfmTlvuZwMBD-Gt0BZZC-IvVCJOd1jzexDoiC-BV4LG7X2aOyOapkCKK6wM6WWffluiuD5MKKet6MfEIjTWNZMCpFx1FP13suiCY?width=660&amp;amp;height=249&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:660px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Daily usage"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the Xmas break is almost upon us and I will be returning my attention to ToddlerBox (yes, despite the career break, I try to spend most of my time working on 'serious' projects or study). I have a number of new features in mind for it (including the #1 requested feature of "sound!!") and will be looking to try out a couple of more features of the awesome Win2D library. It's going to be a lot of fun (for me and my little girl) and will hopefully allow ToddlerBox to reach the next major (although admittedly arbitrary) milestone of 25,000 acquisitions!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch this space...&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The absolute easiest way to use SVG icons in UWP apps</title>
			<link>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/UsingSVGInUWP</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;There are &lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/a/3528493/628821"&gt;many&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/a/22107360/628821"&gt;many&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://blogs.u2u.be/diederik/post/2012/07/26/Transforming-SVG-graphics-to-XAML-Metro-Icons.aspx"&gt;many&lt;/a&gt;) ways to use SVG assets as icons in UWP / XAML apps, most requiring some form of DataTemplate or UserControl. While these approaches work &lt;em&gt;ok&lt;/em&gt; they're normally a pain to author and use, often requiring custom converters to be written if the asset is to be used via any form of data binding. Here I present an extremely flexible way of using these assets that requires nothing more than drag-and-drop.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<guid>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/UsingSVGInUWP</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;There are &lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/a/3528493/628821"&gt;many&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/a/22107360/628821"&gt;many&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://blogs.u2u.be/diederik/post/2012/07/26/Transforming-SVG-graphics-to-XAML-Metro-Icons.aspx"&gt;many&lt;/a&gt;) ways to use SVG assets as icons in UWP / XAML apps, most requiring some form of DataTemplate or UserControl. While these approaches work &lt;em&gt;ok&lt;/em&gt; they're normally a pain to author and use, often requiring custom converters to be written if the asset is to be used via any form of data binding. Here I present an extremely flexible way of using these assets that requires nothing more than drag-and-drop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach uses &lt;a href="https://glyphter.com/"&gt;Glyphter&lt;/a&gt; - a free, online tool for converting SVG icons to fonts - to produce a custom font containing your SVG assets; similar to fonts like &lt;a href="http://modernicons.io/segoe-mdl2/cheatsheet/"&gt;Segoe MDL2&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://fontawesome.io/"&gt;FontAwesome&lt;/a&gt;. Glypter's free tier allows you to craft a single font, containing just basic alpha-numerics. Should you need more than this, you can upgrade to a premium tier which allows you to work on multiple fonts of a much greater size.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you've built your font, it can be embedded in the app package and icons displayed by simply using a TextBlock element with the Text property set to the alpha-numeric code of the icon to display and the FontFamily set to the custom font. Furthermore, you're easily able to present the required icons in the desired colour - by changing the TextBlock's Foreground brush - and size - by changing FontSize or embedding within the TextBlock within a ViewBox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get started, simply locating the SVG asset you'd like to use. &lt;a href="https://thenounproject.com/"&gt;The Noun Project&lt;/a&gt; is a good resource containing an incredible number of high quality icons that can be used in commercial products for a small fee or via attribution. Once you've found the icon you want to use - lets use &lt;a href="https://thenounproject.com/localdomain/collection/memes/?oq=meme&amp;amp;cidx=0&amp;amp;i=105269"&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href="https://thenounproject.com/localdomain/"&gt;Gareth&lt;/a&gt; - simply download the icon as an SVG. Once it's downloaded, locate the file and drag it onto the Glypter grid in the desired location. After a short pause while the file is uploaded to Glypter and processed, it'll appear in the grid slot you selected; here I've added the icon to the 'A':&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/UsingSVGInUWP/DraggedIntoGlyphter.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Glyphter custom font"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Repeat this for all the icons you want to use - I'll just stick with the one icon for now - then download the font by clicking the font download button (the 'down arrow' in the 'FONT' button). This will compile all your assets into a zip file containing the font (in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TrueType"&gt;'.ttf'&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Web_Open_Font_Format"&gt;'.woff'&lt;/a&gt; formats), svg and css assets. We're only interested in the '.ttf' file so extract it from the zip file and copy it to the 'Assets' folder of your UWP app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From within VisualStudio - or better yet, Blend - add the '.ttf' file to the project, ensuring it's 'Build Action' is set to 'Content' and 'Copy to Output Directory' set to 'Do not copy' as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/UsingSVGInUWP/BlendWithGlyphterFont.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Custom font added to project in Blend"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this in place, when you drop a TextBlock on a page, you should be able to select your embedded font from the Font combobox as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/UsingSVGInUWP/SelectFont.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Custom font selection in Blend"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest, as they say, is history. In a few minutes you too can use the following XAML:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;Grid&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;StackPanel HorizontalAlignment="Center" VerticalAlignment="Center"&amp;gt;
        &amp;lt;TextBlock Text="SVG in UWP EZ!" HorizontalAlignment="Center" FontFamily="Impact" Margin="10"/&amp;gt;
        &amp;lt;TextBlock Text="A" FontFamily="ms-appx:/Assets/Glyphter.ttf#Glyphter" FontSize="96" HorizontalAlignment="Center"/&amp;gt;
        &amp;lt;TextBlock Text="Y U NO USE!" HorizontalAlignment="Center" FontFamily="Impact"/&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;/StackPanel&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/Grid&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: There seems to be an issue/inconsistency with the FontFamily value created when using the XAML designer to select your custom font. Sometimes, but not always, the designer will fail to add the "ms-appx" protocol to the FontFamily property value which, while it has no effect at design time, will prevent the app from locating the custom font at runtime. You should there ensure this value is present before deploying your app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To create this amazing UI:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/UsingSVGInUWP/SVGInUWPEZ.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="SVG in UWP EZ! Y U NO USE!"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>ToddlerBox Hits 1000 Users</title>
			<link>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/ToddlerBoxHitsOneThousandUsers</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;Wow!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<enclosure url="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/ibebbs/ToddlerBox/raw/master/store/Screenshots/Xbox/Donkeys" length="0" type="image" />
			<guid>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/ToddlerBoxHitsOneThousandUsers</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;Wow!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ToddlerBox has been in the store less than two weeks and, despite very little in the way of promotion (my other half sent out a call on Facebook for beta users), it has somehow accumulated over a thousand installs!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acquisitions have seen steady growth across a (more or less) expected demographic as can be seen below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://zphbkg.dm2302.livefilestore.com/y3mxlql02_eOqhCIiHNom5uhtzjCe_ZMvbgIGPcUuLMbuHi_cmFRtGpAIb2CVV_k_HAO6v_3BB7AfILc428eEqv96IXFv3b-Vwws3CvDkXxj9uTiBtz9C2JTxwcKIPHpbhXb1LSnjCUDMosCL5GbtEQN9PsjnFM4iq6n2cCuMcSAVo?width=660&amp;amp;height=145&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:660px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Acquisitions over App Lifetime"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://0ohtkg.dm2302.livefilestore.com/y3mJ-gCk99nTK8OuY5w0Ws1xjrRZiFLkxZMpJ-0LWENyYp0q9h-tnT73xZC4_a-hrF4rbBao7kp7vY7jrdgON0ukq9qib82QSM6vNHTvQwvTUYPfyFnfOviJ0HWYe_JRsunQODVyvcmOh0zjjzDk1LXL13blrvuAloFWFlFIFygSSQ?width=660&amp;amp;height=235&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:660px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Acquisitions by Demographic"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to the number of users, the number of countries it is being used in has been really surprising. Sure, there's no localization concerns so there's no reason it &lt;em&gt;wouldn't&lt;/em&gt; be used in non-English speaking countries but I'm genuinely pleased to see it being used all over the world; from USA to Saudi Arabia and from Canada to China! Here's the current breakdown of usage:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Country&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Sessions&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;United States&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;910&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;United Kingdom&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;311&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Canada&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;110&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Australia&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;42&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Saudi Arabia&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;33&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;China &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;25&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Brazil&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Mexico&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;19&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Germany&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;17&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Netherlands&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;14&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;France&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;New Zealand&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Ireland&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Latvia&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Hungary&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Sweden&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Russia&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Poland&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Slovakia &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;South Africa&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Austria&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Belgium&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Switzerland&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Spain &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Czech Republic&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Guam&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Puerto Rico&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Chile &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Denmark&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Romania&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Colombia &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Italy &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Libya &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Norway&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Trinidad and Tobago&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;United Arab Emirates &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Unknown&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the somewhat unexpected success of ToddlerBox I am planning to release a number of future versions with various enhancements and new interactions/visualizations for toddler's to mash away at.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All good fun :0D&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Using Wyam</title>
			<link>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/NewBlogUsingWyam</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;I've been meaning to create a blog for a &lt;strong&gt;long&lt;/strong&gt; time but never found a system with the right combination of features (power vs flexibility vs learning curve, cost, technology stack, etc). CMSs (Wordpress, Drupal, etc) were always way too much faff and most static site generators required the installation of numerous languages / run-times / sdks, etc.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<guid>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/NewBlogUsingWyam</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 09 Nov 2015 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;I've been meaning to create a blog for a &lt;strong&gt;long&lt;/strong&gt; time but never found a system with the right combination of features (power vs flexibility vs learning curve, cost, technology stack, etc). CMSs (Wordpress, Drupal, etc) were always way too much faff and most static site generators required the installation of numerous languages / run-times / sdks, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I found &lt;a href="http://wyam.io/" title="Wyam Homepage"&gt;Wyam&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being .NET based it could be used from my day-to-day development machine and, by cleverly leveraging the  Roslyn compiler platform, can be set up to be as simple or flexible as desired. A quick flick through the module and API pages and I knew I'd found a potential candidate for my statically generated blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a... ahem... pragmatic developer with somewhat dated web skills I decided to take the path of least resistance and copy someone else's blog layout. Afterall, imitation is the sincerest form of flattery, right? As such, I contacted Dave Glick - the most-excellent author of Wyam - to see if he would mind me 'borrowing' the layout he used for &lt;a href="http://daveaglick.com/" title="Dave Glick's blog"&gt;his blog&lt;/a&gt;. He quickly replied to my cheeky request and said he didn't mind at all if used his layout, even refusing my offer of attribution (which I hope this blog post somewhat makes up for).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the all clear, I &lt;a href="https://github.com/Wyamio/Wyam/releases/tag/v0.10.0-beta" title="download page for Wyam version 0.10.0-beta"&gt;downloaded the latest version of Wyam&lt;/a&gt;, cloned the &lt;a href="https://github.com/Wyamio/Wyam" title="Github repository for Wyam "&gt;Wyam repository&lt;/a&gt;, invoked Wyam to generate an &lt;a href="https://github.com/Wyamio/Wyam/tree/develop/Examples" title="Wyam Example sites in Github repository"&gt;example site&lt;/a&gt;... and got an exception.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another quick chat with Mr. Glick revealed that the project is iterating quickly and currently in a "move fast and break things" mode. Fortunately the issue was already resolved in the development branch so, after local build of Wyam, I managed to successfully generate the example sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Now for some blatant plagiarism with his blog" I thought to myself but again, after cloning his (generously shared and CC licensed) &lt;a href="https://github.com/daveaglick/daveaglick" title="Github repository for Dave Glick's blog"&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;, asking Wyam to generate the site threw an exception. This time, a &lt;a href="https://github.com/Wyamio/Wyam/issues/112#issuecomment-155165316" title="Wyam PostFile issue comment on Github"&gt;short bit of call-stack sleuthing&lt;/a&gt; revealed another breaking change which was easily resolved by examining the &lt;a href="http://wyam.io/modules/" title="Module documentation for Wyam"&gt;Wyam module documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once more with feeling and ét voila, a MVB (Minimal Viable Blog).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, not a bad experience with an early beta of a very clever project. Moving forward, I actually hope to do very little with Wyam other than post blog entries but will certainly endeavour to keep up to date with Wyam and share my experiences here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're looking for a flexible yet powerful .NET based static-site generator, go check out &lt;a href="http://wyam.io/" title="Wyam Homepage"&gt;Wyam&lt;/a&gt;. If you experience any problems with it I'd definitely recommend posting an issue on Github, Dave seems to be very on the ball responding to issues (and extremely friendly to boot).&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>WebRx and Typescript</title>
			<link>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/RxWebWithTypescript</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="./posts/RxWeb"&gt;part 1&lt;/a&gt; of this series I showed how to set up a project structure that allows you to start using WebRx from within Visual Studio. While fairly simple, the example provides a great illustration of you how WebRx allows you to separate your view and view model.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<guid>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/RxWebWithTypescript</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>
                                        


&lt;h1&gt;Continuing with WebRx&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="./posts/RxWeb"&gt;part 1&lt;/a&gt; of this series I showed how to set up a project structure that allows you to start using WebRx from within Visual Studio. While fairly simple, the example provides a great illustration of you how WebRx allows you to separate your view and view model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article I further develop the structure to allow you to develop your application using Typescript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;From 'app.js' to 'app.ts'&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previously we copied a chunk of JavaScript from the WebRx &lt;a href="http://webrxjs.org/docs/getting-started.html"&gt;getting started guide&lt;/a&gt; into an &lt;code&gt;app.js&lt;/code&gt; script that was directly used from within the &lt;code&gt;index.html&lt;/code&gt; file. We now want to &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Source-to-source_compiler"&gt;&lt;em&gt;transpile&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; the &lt;code&gt;app.js&lt;/code&gt; script from a Typescript file so that we can further develop the application in a structured and type-safe manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do this simply follow the following steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delete the existing &lt;code&gt;app.js&lt;/code&gt; file leaving the &lt;code&gt;js&lt;/code&gt; folder empty.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add and configure a &lt;code&gt;TypeScript JSON Configuration File&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add a &lt;code&gt;TypeScript JSON Configuration File&lt;/code&gt; to the solution as shown below&lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/RxWebWithTypescript/AddTypeScriptJsonConfigurationFile.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Add TypeScript Json Configuration File"&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Replace the &lt;code&gt;node_modules&lt;/code&gt; exclusion with &lt;code&gt;Scripts&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br&gt;
By default Visual Studio (or, more acurately, the TypeScript transpiler) with pick up all &lt;code&gt;ts&lt;/code&gt; files in the solution. As we don't want to attempt to re-transpile all the referenced typescript files we add &lt;code&gt;Scripts&lt;/code&gt; to the exclusion list. Further, as we added a reference to &lt;code&gt;WebRx&lt;/code&gt; via Nuget, our references are in the &lt;code&gt;Scripts&lt;/code&gt; folder, not &lt;code&gt;node_modules&lt;/code&gt;, so this exclusion can be removed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add an &lt;code&gt;outDir&lt;/code&gt; setting to transpile to the &lt;code&gt;js&lt;/code&gt; folder&lt;br&gt;
This setting will force the TypeScript transpiler to output the transpiled JavaScript files to the &lt;code&gt;js&lt;/code&gt; folder where they can be used by the client browser.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You should now have a &lt;code&gt;tsconfig.json&lt;/code&gt; file that looks like this:
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;{
  "compilerOptions": {
    "noImplicitAny": false,
    "noEmitOnError": true,
    "removeComments": false,
    "sourceMap": true,
    "target": "es5",
    "outDir": "js"
  },
  "exclude": [
    "Scripts",
    "wwwroot"
  ]
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol start="3"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add a &lt;code&gt;ts&lt;/code&gt; folder to the solution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add an &lt;code&gt;app.ts&lt;/code&gt; typescript file to the &lt;code&gt;ts&lt;/code&gt; folder.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add references to Rx and WebRx to the &lt;code&gt;app.ts&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;br&gt;
WebRx requires that you add an explicit reference to &lt;code&gt;rx.all.d.ts&lt;/code&gt; prior to the reference to &lt;code&gt;web.rx.d.ts&lt;/code&gt; in order for the Rx module to be brought into scope. The references should therefore be added like this:
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;/// &amp;lt;reference path="../Scripts/rx.all.d.ts"/&amp;gt;
/// &amp;lt;reference path="../Scripts/typings/web.rx.d.ts" /&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implement view / view model code&lt;br&gt;
You can now re-implement the code from &lt;code&gt;app.js&lt;/code&gt; as TypeScript virtually verbatim but do note how you get Intellisense for all the methods and properties of &lt;code&gt;wx&lt;/code&gt; module.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix compilation error with call to &lt;code&gt;wx.applyBindings&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br&gt;
The &lt;code&gt;wx.applyBindings&lt;/code&gt; method &lt;em&gt;requires&lt;/em&gt; a &lt;code&gt;model&lt;/code&gt; parameter which, in JavaScript, is defaulted but in TypeScript causes a compilation error. To resolve this, simply pass an empty object to the method.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your &lt;code&gt;app.ts&lt;/code&gt; file should now look like this:
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;/// &amp;lt;reference path="../Scripts/rx.all.d.ts"/&amp;gt;
/// &amp;lt;reference path="../Scripts/typings/web.rx.d.ts" /&amp;gt;

wx.app.component('hello', {
    viewModel: function () {
        this.firstName = 'Bart';
        this.lastName = 'Simpson';
    },
    template: 'The name is &amp;lt;span data-bind="text: firstName + \' \' + lastName"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;'
});

wx.router.state({
    name: "$",
    views: { 'main': "hello" }
});

wx.router.reload();

wx.applyBindings({});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol start="5"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compile the project and include the generated &lt;code&gt;js/app.js&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;js/app.js.map&lt;/code&gt; files into the project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hit F5 and you should again see the message 'The name is Bart Simpson' displayed in your default browser.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congratulations, you're now ready to develop your application using full Intellisense and in the comfort of the knowledge that the compiler (well, transpiler) will pick up any syntactic bugs you may inadvertently create.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always, the completed &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs/BlogProjects/tree/master/WebRxWithTypeScript"&gt;source code for this post&lt;/a&gt; can be found in the &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs/BlogProjects"&gt;BlogProjects repository&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs"&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Using a Hyperlink in MVVM</title>
			<link>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/UsingHyperlinkInMVVM</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;The XAML (i.e. WPF, WinRT, UWP family) &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.windows.documents.hyperlink.aspx"&gt;Hyperlink&lt;/a&gt; is a terrific little control (ok, it's not actually a &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.windows.controls.control.aspx"&gt;Control&lt;/a&gt; - it's a &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.windows.contentelement.aspx"&gt;ContentElement&lt;/a&gt; - but it does allow interaction hence using the term control here). It follows the current environment's theme such that the user naturally knows it's a link that can be clicked and it can be embedded inside &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.windows.controls.textblock.aspx"&gt;TextBlock&lt;/a&gt; elements so that it naturally flows with the other content.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<guid>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/UsingHyperlinkInMVVM</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;The XAML (i.e. WPF, WinRT, UWP family) &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.windows.documents.hyperlink.aspx"&gt;Hyperlink&lt;/a&gt; is a terrific little control (ok, it's not actually a &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.windows.controls.control.aspx"&gt;Control&lt;/a&gt; - it's a &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.windows.contentelement.aspx"&gt;ContentElement&lt;/a&gt; - but it does allow interaction hence using the term control here). It follows the current environment's theme such that the user naturally knows it's a link that can be clicked and it can be embedded inside &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.windows.controls.textblock.aspx"&gt;TextBlock&lt;/a&gt; elements so that it naturally flows with the other content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src="https://gist.github.com/ibebbs/f3b4efb09f9b0ea36397a9ab462823df.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, out of the box, this control's functionality is somewhat limited. As standard, it is simply able to perform navigation on any &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/library/windows/apps/br242682"&gt;Frame&lt;/a&gt; element the control is hosted within. Any other type of behavior requires the developer to subscribe to the control's &lt;code&gt;OnHyperlinkClicked&lt;/code&gt; event and perform the required operations from code-behind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Unfortunately, neither of these approaches work for 'ViewModel First' &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-gb/library/hh848246.aspx"&gt;MVVM&lt;/a&gt;, which, after many years employing MVVM is by far my favoured approach.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a project I've been working on which employs this pattern, a state-machine is used to track application state and each transition between states causing a navigation to be performed in the UI. In one view within the application, there was a desire to instigate a state-machine transition by clicking on a &lt;code&gt;Hyperlink&lt;/code&gt; embedded within some text. Ideally, when clicked, the &lt;code&gt;Hyperlink&lt;/code&gt; would execute an &lt;code&gt;ICommand&lt;/code&gt; instance data-bound to the view from the view-model. Obviously this wasn't possible as standard so I started thinking through alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first inclination was to restyle a &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.windows.controls.button.aspx"&gt;Button&lt;/a&gt; to look like a Hyperlink. This would, ostensibly, be fairly straight forward and naturally provided a Command &lt;code&gt;DependencyProperty&lt;/code&gt; to bind to. However, keeping the hyperlink styled as per the current system theme would be arduous to say the least.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Putting this aside, I came across &lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/a/11433814"&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; which employed an attached property to start a process (normally a browser to display external content) on the host PC. Realising this approach could be extended to accomplish my goals I refactored it to the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src="https://gist.github.com/ibebbs/654f519eec134135f7f9469150b07438.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which can be used as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src="https://gist.github.com/ibebbs/0ae7c2e0ed3c531858f5ee01c16157b8.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Et voilá, a &lt;code&gt;Hyperlink&lt;/code&gt; control which is able to execute a data-bound &lt;code&gt;ICommand&lt;/code&gt; instance. Obviously it could be extended further to disable the hyperlink when the command reports execution is disabled (via &lt;code&gt;CanExecuteChanged&lt;/code&gt;) and provide a CommandParamter binding for passing additional information through to the command execution, but in a lot of instances - and certainly for me in this scenario - &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/You_aren%27t_gonna_need_it"&gt;YAGNI&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Combining the UWP SpeechSynthesizer and AudioGraph APIs</title>
			<link>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/CombiningUwpSpeechSynthesizerWithAudioGraph</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;Synchronicity is a wonderful thing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<guid>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/CombiningUwpSpeechSynthesizerWithAudioGraph</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;Synchronicity is a wonderful thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just this morning I was considering using the new &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/apps/windows.media.speechsynthesis.speechsynthesizer.aspx"&gt;SpeechSynthesizer&lt;/a&gt; capabilities of the UWP platform to add spoken language to my &lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-gb/store/p/toddlerbox/9nblggh3zr4l"&gt;ToddlerBox app for Xbox&lt;/a&gt;. I had already started using the &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/apps/windows.media.audio.audiograph.aspx"&gt;AudioGraph&lt;/a&gt; classes to play sounds in the app so ideally wanted to continue using this API to emit speech.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, during my morning... ahem... ablutions, I came across &lt;a href="https://mtaulty.com/2017/01/15/windows-10-uwp-iot-core-speechsynthesizer-raspberry-pi-and-audio-popping/"&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; by Mike Taulty who was looking to do the same thing but for different reasons. It seems that the RaspberryPi has a firmware issue that causes a &lt;a href="https://social.msdn.microsoft.com/Forums/en-US/7c312972-6a09-4acd-8a3f-c59485a81d74/clicking-sound-during-start-and-stop-of-audio-playback?forum=WindowsIoT"&gt;popping noise&lt;/a&gt;  every time speech is emitted using the MediaPlayer and AudioGraph seems to be a way of resolving it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mike had implemented a means of emitting speech via AudioGraph by saving the &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/apps/windows.media.speechsynthesis.speechsynthesisstream.aspx?f=255&amp;amp;MSPPError=-2147217396"&gt;SpeechSynthesisStream&lt;/a&gt; to a  temporary file and then using multiple &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/apps/windows.media.audio.audiofileinputnode.aspx"&gt;AudioFileInputNode&lt;/a&gt; instances to render the speech to the AudioGraph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Well", I thought, "there's got to be a better way. How hard can this be..."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Turns out the answer is: "Not all that hard, but...".&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My approach&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to find a way to eliminate the need for the temporary files and render the speech stream directly to the graph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do this, I first saved the SpeechSynthesisStream to a file so that I could examine the content. As expected, the file turned out to be a simple 32-bit, mono, ADPCM waveform in &lt;a href="http://soundfile.sapp.org/doc/WaveFormat/"&gt;WAV/RIFF format&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having previously messed about with AudioGraph I knew there was a way of creating an in-memory waveform and that the &lt;a href="https://github.com/Microsoft/Windows-universal-samples"&gt;Windows-Universal-Samples github repository&lt;/a&gt; had an &lt;a href="https://github.com/Microsoft/Windows-universal-samples/tree/master/Samples/AudioCreation"&gt;AudioCreation sample&lt;/a&gt; that &lt;a href="https://github.com/Microsoft/Windows-universal-samples/blob/master/Samples/AudioCreation/cs/AudioCreation/Scenario3_FrameInputNode.xaml.cs"&gt;showed how to do this&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fundamentally, this sample shows how to use the &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-gb/library/windows/apps/windows.media.audio.audioframeinputnode.quantumstarted"&gt;QuantumStarted event&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/library/windows/apps/dn914147"&gt;AudioFrameInputNode&lt;/a&gt; to dynamically add &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/apps/windows.media.audioframe.aspx"&gt;AudioFrame&lt;/a&gt; to the AudioFrameInputNode which are then rendered to the &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-gb/library/windows/apps/dn914151"&gt;output node&lt;/a&gt;. An extract from the sample is shown here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;  unsafe private AudioFrame GenerateAudioData(uint samples)
  {
      // Buffer size is (number of samples) * (size of each sample)
      // We choose to generate single channel (mono) audio. For multi-channel, multiply by number of channels
      uint bufferSize = samples * sizeof(float);
      AudioFrame frame = new Windows.Media.AudioFrame(bufferSize);

      using (AudioBuffer buffer = frame.LockBuffer(AudioBufferAccessMode.Write))
      using (IMemoryBufferReference reference = buffer.CreateReference())
      {
          byte* dataInBytes;
          uint capacityInBytes;
          float* dataInFloat;

          // Get the buffer from the AudioFrame
          ((IMemoryBufferByteAccess)reference).GetBuffer(out dataInBytes, out capacityInBytes);

          // Cast to float since the data we are generating is float
          dataInFloat = (float*)dataInBytes;

          float freq = 1000; // choosing to generate frequency of 1kHz
          float amplitude = 0.3f;
          int sampleRate = (int)graph.EncodingProperties.SampleRate;
          double sampleIncrement = (freq * (Math.PI * 2)) / sampleRate;

          // Generate a 1kHz sine wave and populate the values in the memory buffer
          for (int i = 0; i &amp;lt; samples; i++)
          {
              double sinValue = amplitude * Math.Sin(theta);
              dataInFloat[i] = (float)sinValue;
              theta += sampleIncrement;
          }
      }

      return frame;
  }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imitation being the sincerest form of flattery, I then refactored this code to read the binary data from the SpeechSynthesisStream rather than generate a sine wave as shown above. This was greatly facilited by the &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/hh582142.aspx"&gt;WindowsRuntimeStreamExtensions.AsStreamForRead&lt;/a&gt; method which allowed me to use basic &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.io.stream.aspx"&gt;Stream&lt;/a&gt; methods  (specifically &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.io.stream.readbyte.aspx"&gt;Stream.ReadByte()&lt;/a&gt;) instead of having to mess about with &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows.media.speechsynthesis.speechsynthesisstream.readasync.aspx"&gt;IBuffer&lt;/a&gt; instances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short order, I ended up with the code below (where &lt;code&gt;_stream&lt;/code&gt; is a member of the containing class pointing to the underlying SpeechSynthesisStream):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;    private unsafe void QuantumStarted(AudioFrameInputNode sender, FrameInputNodeQuantumStartedEventArgs args)
    {
        uint numSamplesNeeded = (uint)args.RequiredSamples;

        if (numSamplesNeeded != 0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; _stream.Position &amp;lt; _stream.Length)
        {
            uint bufferSize = numSamplesNeeded * sizeof(float);
            AudioFrame frame = new AudioFrame(bufferSize);

            using (AudioBuffer buffer = frame.LockBuffer(AudioBufferAccessMode.Write))
            {
                using (IMemoryBufferReference reference = buffer.CreateReference())
                {
                    byte* dataInBytes;
                    uint capacityInBytes;

                    // Get the buffer from the AudioFrame
                    ((IMemoryBufferByteAccess)reference).GetBuffer(out dataInBytes, out capacityInBytes);

                    for (int i = 0; i &amp;lt; bufferSize; i++)
                    {
                        if (_stream.Position &amp;lt; _stream.Length)
                        {
                            dataInBytes[i] = (byte)_stream.ReadByte();
                        }
                        else
                        {
                            dataInBytes[i] = 0;
                        }
                    }
                }
            }

            _frameInputNode.AddFrame(frame);
        }
    }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And to my surprised, it worked!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I encapsulated this code into a class named &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs/BlogProjects/blob/master/UwpSpeechAudio/GraphExtensions.cs"&gt;AudioSpeechInputNode&lt;/a&gt; and made this class implement &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/apps/windows.media.audio.iaudioinputnode.aspx"&gt;IAudioInputNode&lt;/a&gt; so it could be treated like any other node in the AudioGraph. Finally I added an extension method to AudioGraph that created instance of this node in the same way that other nodes are created. This is shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;    AudioSpeechInputNode speechInputNode = await _graph.CreateSpeechInputNodeAsync(new SpeechSynthesizer(), "As input node");
    speechInputNode.AddOutgoingConnection(_outputNode); // device output node
    speechInputNode.Stop();
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this node in hand you're then at liberty to call the &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/apps/windows.media.audio.iaudionode.start.aspx"&gt;Start&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/apps/windows.media.audio.iaudionode.stop.aspx"&gt;Stop&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/apps/windows.media.audio.iaudionode.reset.aspx"&gt;Reset&lt;/a&gt; methods as you see fit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Et voila, a SpeechSynthesisStream rendered in an AudioGraph without the need for an intermediary file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;You said there was a 'but' ...&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, yes. Three of them actually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The big 'but'&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this approach certainly solves the issue with needing temporary files and a 'popping' sound each time speech is emitted, I'm afraid to say it does not resolve the 'popping' noise encountered when the application starts on a RaspberryPi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a good nerd, I had a spare RaspberryPi 3 hanging around with a recent version of Windows 10 IoT Core installed. It took just a few minutes to recompile my &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs/BlogProjects/tree/master/UwpSpeechAudio"&gt;sample app&lt;/a&gt; to ARM and deploy it to the Pi whereupon I could confirm that there is no popping when emitting speech but there is when the application starts. In fact, I receive three distinct 'pops' during application start-up which, by studiously placing breakpoints, I isolated to &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/apps/windows.media.audio.audiograph.createasync.aspx"&gt;AudioGraph.CreateAsync&lt;/a&gt; (two pops) and &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/apps/windows.media.audio.audiograph.start.aspx"&gt;AudioGraph.Start&lt;/a&gt; (one pop).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microsoft would have us believe that this is an issue with the RaspberryPi firmware but, as it also occurs on &lt;a href="https://developer.qualcomm.com/hardware/dragonboard-410c"&gt;DragonBoard 410c&lt;/a&gt; I'm more inclined to believe it's an issue with the Windows drivers. On a hunch, I've just ordered a &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/dp/B016CU2PEU"&gt;USB Sound Adapter from Amazon&lt;/a&gt;. This device is &lt;em&gt;meant&lt;/em&gt; to be Windows and RaspberryPi compatible (which doesn't necessarily mean it'll work with IoT Core on RPi) and, if it works, I'll be very interested to see if I still get the popping noises when the application starts. I'll update this post once I have an answer...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Update: I'm pleased to say that, not only does &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/dp/B016CU2PEU"&gt;this device&lt;/a&gt; work with Windows 10 IoT Core running on the RaspberryPi 3, but it also resolves the issue with popping noises when the application starts. Of course, this would probably also solve the issue with popping noises when rendering speech through MediaPlayer too making my solution above less necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The intermediate 'but'&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My code makes a number of assumptions about the format of the SpeechSynthesisStream and encapsulates these as constants. It would be much better to read the format from the WAVE 'fmt ' chunk of the underlying RIFF structures in the stream but, being a pragmatic, &lt;a href="https://martinfowler.com/bliki/Yagni.html"&gt;YAGNI principled&lt;/a&gt; developer... I skipped this for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The small 'but'&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As is probably very obvious, the code above is in no way optimised. I'm sure there are &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; better and faster ways of storing and copying the binary data from the SpeechSynthesisStream into the AudioBuffer (perhaps just using an intermediate byte array would help) but, for now, this code works fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Show me the code&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the code for the above can be found in a &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs/BlogProjects/tree/master/UwpSpeechAudio"&gt;UWP sample app&lt;/a&gt; within the &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs/BlogProjects"&gt;BlogProjects&lt;/a&gt; repository of my &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs"&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ibebbs"&gt;get in touch&lt;/a&gt; if you find this code helpful or have suggestions for improving it.&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>ToddlerBox Released to the XBox Store</title>
			<link>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/ToddlerBoxReleasedToStore</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;My little girl loves playing with the XBox controller. In fact, she'll make a beeline for it as soon as she sees it and sit for ages twiddling the thumb-sticks and mashing the buttons. So I thought it'd be great to provide some visual accompaniment to the tactile experience of playing with the controller. Furthermore, I'd been looking for an excuse to play with Win2D as part of a UWP app and this felt like a perfect opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<enclosure url="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/y3mVAxtKFjUEGk7Hdhzjl4UZ2INnFdBbw9K-tnYZ8DYoJ-VoKxpAN6w8Ng0DFTYdSxpHY6IvL5-VwJpLkQl6qWRmMQXSExLXopz5CFuSxIbyaMLrnL2Vy3yPZlISAAknXZdT4HwiZJ55zg2UtKwucBL88-xHh6rn5Mh97yzfRsCPjI%253Fwidth=1919&amp;height=1075&amp;cropmode=none" length="0" type="image" />
			<guid>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/ToddlerBoxReleasedToStore</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;My little girl loves playing with the XBox controller. In fact, she'll make a beeline for it as soon as she sees it and sit for ages twiddling the thumb-sticks and mashing the buttons. So I thought it'd be great to provide some visual accompaniment to the tactile experience of playing with the controller. Furthermore, I'd been looking for an excuse to play with Win2D as part of a UWP app and this felt like a perfect opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To this end, I cracked open Visual Studio, started a blank UWP app, added a nuget reference to Win2D and started coding. Using a &lt;a href="https://microsoft.github.io/Win2D/html/T_Microsoft_Graphics_Canvas_UI_Xaml_CanvasAnimatedControl.htm"&gt;CanvasAnimatedControl&lt;/a&gt; it was simple to use the &lt;a href="https://microsoft.github.io/Win2D/html/E_Microsoft_Graphics_Canvas_UI_Xaml_CanvasAnimatedControl_Update.htm"&gt;Update&lt;/a&gt; callback to read the &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/apps/windows.gaming.input.gamepad"&gt;Gamepad&lt;/a&gt; input and then use the &lt;a href="https://microsoft.github.io/Win2D/html/E_Microsoft_Graphics_Canvas_UI_Xaml_CanvasAnimatedControl_Draw.htm"&gt;Draw&lt;/a&gt; callback to draw a series of sprites based on the values read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in, from not having used Win2D before, it took just a few hours to get a minimal app working with a variety of sprites and manipulation mechanisms. Flipping my &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-gb/windows/uwp/xbox-apps/devkit-activation"&gt;XBox into developer mode&lt;/a&gt; allowed me to deploy the app directly to the Xbox and have a play. And I must say, I was very pleased with the result:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://zphxkg.dm2302.livefilestore.com/y3mynwGeO7sZByGMtgH7TP5ykDeabNNlbyLCFHZfLu2Ml9QbQft2wq6-MeIxMukEXnVpiqZfLa_lh7h15xlStRf8Eo81_y5J-zSplYIIDh5dKAkS-j2q2wS4-GUHpOpwW5eltQ8_CLhSQNoRRJwdZWs_AhjvxhhOMdCS5PB-stLlTE?width=1024&amp;amp;height=575&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:320px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Lots of animals"&gt;
&lt;h6 style="text-align: center;" markdown="1"&gt;Lots of animals&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;img src="https://zphykg.dm2302.livefilestore.com/y3mVAxtKFjUEGk7Hdhzjl4UZ2INnFdBbw9K-tnYZ8DYoJ-VoKxpAN6w8Ng0DFTYdSxpHY6IvL5-VwJpLkQl6qWRmMQXSExLXopz5CFuSxIbyaMLrnL2Vy3yPZlISAAknXZdT4HwiZJ55zg2UtKwucBL88-xHh6rn5Mh97yzfRsCPjI?width=1024&amp;amp;height=574&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:320px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Lots of colours"&gt;
&lt;h6 style="text-align: center;" markdown="1"&gt;Lots of colours&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;img src="https://zphwkg.dm2302.livefilestore.com/y3m8XFQkqAgfzj1Yt9EqXW14XVybPwILZ0Hn_yGK2sbayqyeGZVqwSOGpT_xAJS3WwzYFeyQ4Gw66Fa-QyRpM71WpPUktEfgvgteIKAXfp9qCSW_my9s-7kb4Ys7Qz1JYRHv-k8fl1Y8xTTDpLhfY5xG2m56hT_ObFWrKxFhV-N-lw?width=1024&amp;amp;height=575&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:320px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Big..."&gt;
&lt;h6 style="text-align: center;" markdown="1"&gt;Big...&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;img src="https://zphvkg.dm2302.livefilestore.com/y3mN4YESAkR1YSr8YbSDJtqi2DGD20bBa_w5RR2cYyAm9aXKXxib1A65RnVBxraAGCEXRELh0QMYDSASbm7F8ADzvh7EizJXlz-odd9Vhvq0ccfd0yNyL4v1f2qex5ol96GP6qvxE35Fo1L-hdlu9cfo08lDWZielw6ffr-vZ92aYE?width=1024&amp;amp;height=575&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:320px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="...or small"&gt;
&lt;h6 style="text-align: center;" markdown="1"&gt;...or small&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;img src="https://zphukg.dm2302.livefilestore.com/y3mcH_fRNs467C1gL7rApW6mWiFYB-eCoUexIuW3CwX4Cb0seAy8IxNhjyiGFQx3jDrcB8ToLQJgekRDInIwMkMHQvVZ05vWCPrptx2vxkcu-KG40ldNAqOZu2ulyL7OPSGt7uuFNnZLOdtycCFVs3Tl5IWJltKR6uhEgxNW_j-4tI?width=1024&amp;amp;height=575&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:320px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="And monkeys!!!"&gt;
&lt;h6 style="text-align: center;" markdown="1"&gt;And monkeys!!!!&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real test came when I handed to the controller to my 14 month old baby girl. It took a few seconds for her to realise that what she did on the controller affected what was displayed on screen but then there was no stopping her. For three or four minutes (a record for her!!!) she sat still, mashing away on the controller and staring at the screen while I sat mesmerized by how quickly she picked it all up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd call that a win!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given this success, I made some final touches and submitted it to the store; specifically for XBox. To my amazement, it passed certification first time, within 24 hours of submission despite submitting it on a Sunday. And here it is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://1y8kkg.dm2302.livefilestore.com/y3mRbMDxeVB6f5ArIwJ6FjYCPRmwpPTp6LL2IGiIFOrFVgHzox_2HUl9lPNSq09KxXP5M3LD1E3nwgFi1a8HUCT-0dTH_VmemTLCQwHggxqy8u04C85i51eLPBj1op_n2ppnjK2zkhGDHcWWAyYvkncmNy4bqw58vumGP8BY4f9nZU?width=1024&amp;amp;height=576&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:800px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="ToddlerBox in the store"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Installing from the store and ready to entertain my little one whenever I need a break.&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Breaking News - Forgot to commit</title>
			<link>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/EndOfStreak</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;After 41 days of continuous commits to Github, yesterday I forgot. What's really annoying is that I actually spent a long time working yesterday but found myself battling a stupid limitation of VisualStates in UWP apps (blog post incoming) and didn't have anything finished.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<guid>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/EndOfStreak</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 07 Dec 2015 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;After 41 days of continuous commits to Github, yesterday I forgot. What's really annoying is that I actually spent a long time working yesterday but found myself battling a stupid limitation of VisualStates in UWP apps (blog post incoming) and didn't have anything finished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ho-hum. 41 days was a pretty good streak and it was inevitably going to end over the Xmas period. New Year's resolution: Beat it!&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Achievement Unlocked!</title>
			<link>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/AcheivementUnlocked</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;So, I'm currently working on a project in which I've decided to employ the &lt;a href="http://martinfowler.com/bliki/CQRS.html"&gt;CQRS&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href="http://martinfowler.com/eaaDev/EventNarrative.html"&gt;ES&lt;/a&gt; architectural combo. Given the system is event sourced, I required read models built from the domain events and, conveniently, had blogged about doing this as one of my &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/ReactiveReadModels"&gt;first posts&lt;/a&gt; on this blog.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<guid>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/AcheivementUnlocked</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 11 Aug 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;So, I'm currently working on a project in which I've decided to employ the &lt;a href="http://martinfowler.com/bliki/CQRS.html"&gt;CQRS&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href="http://martinfowler.com/eaaDev/EventNarrative.html"&gt;ES&lt;/a&gt; architectural combo. Given the system is event sourced, I required read models built from the domain events and, conveniently, had blogged about doing this as one of my &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/ReactiveReadModels"&gt;first posts&lt;/a&gt; on this blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was very satisfying to be able to refer back to that blog post to re-familiarize with the pattern and I must say that so far everything is working beautifully. Stay tuned for a future post on using RX to implement a CQRS/ES application in a reactive manner.&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The Year In Review</title>
			<link>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/TheYearInReview</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;Saturday morning, having realized that we had no commitments or prior engagements until the following Tuesday, my partner and I decided to go on a trip. We rapidly packed bags for ourselves and our little girl, threw them in the van and set off with no set destination other than "the south-west". We ended up staying in a small farm on Exmoor and having a terrific time walking on the moor and visiting nearby sites.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<guid>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/TheYearInReview</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;Saturday morning, having realized that we had no commitments or prior engagements until the following Tuesday, my partner and I decided to go on a trip. We rapidly packed bags for ourselves and our little girl, threw them in the van and set off with no set destination other than "the south-west". We ended up staying in a small farm on Exmoor and having a terrific time walking on the moor and visiting nearby sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Other than the liberty of being able to just "get away", this weekend was notable as the previous week marked exactly one year since I left full-time employment.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in July, following an epic road-trip around Europe with my girls, I wrote &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/WotNoBlogPosts"&gt;a long blog post&lt;/a&gt; about the trip and my plans for the future. These plans centred on taking the rest of the year off as a career-break and using this time to support my family while investigating/evaluating emerging technologies in the .NET ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, six months on, it's time to look back over the last year and perform a retrospective; what went well, what could have been better and what should be changed moving forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: This is a long, detailed post with a lot of information/reflection about the previous year. As such I have published it as a MVP (Minimal Viable Post) and will iterate additional information into the post in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A Timeline&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To aid the retrospective process, I spent last week learning &lt;a href="https://www.dartlang.org/"&gt;Dart&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.pixijs.com/"&gt;Pixi.js&lt;/a&gt; in order to create a timeline visualization of the year. I'm not going to go into the process of making this visualization here as I want to focus on the retrospective, however I will be writing a "making of" follow-up post as the process was both very interesting and thoroughly enjoyable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below you can see the visualization; a timeline covering the entirity of last year and showing the various aspects of my behaviour / productivity on a day-by-day basis. In order to fit into the horizontal space available in most browsers/platforms, the timeline is scaled-down along the horizontal axis. As this obscures much of the data, the timeline was designed to allow you to use your mouse or finger to interactively zoom in and and pan across the it. Give it a go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the following sections I will discuss the various datasets displayed along with a summary of what they represent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script defer="" src="../Content/Scripts/timeline.dart.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div id="timeline"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;State&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This timeline represents my primary oocupation at any given time. From a high-level, last year can be broadly split into two halves, travelling for the first half and working for the latter. However, the detail is more telling so the timeline has been further split into seven disctinct states:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Employment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My last day of employment was Friday 15th January, 2016. I had worked at my previous company for over four years and very much enjoyed my time there. Unfortunately an &lt;a href="http://www.daedtech.com/top-heavy-department-growth/"&gt;internal power struggle&lt;/a&gt; resulted in a change of senior management and a move away the progressive development methodologes which had made the company such a great place to work. This, to me, signalled that it was time to move on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Sabatical&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I considered the couple of months following ending full time employment as a sabatical; time to reflect, get my affairs in order and spend time with my young family before  considering how to move forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this time my daughter was just 4 months old so this presented a great opportunity to support my partner and engage with my baby. Having also taken 6 weeks of &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/shared-parental-leave-and-pay/overview"&gt;Shared Parental Leave&lt;/a&gt; the previous year, this meant that, of her first six months of life, I'd been able to spend almost four with her. I feel incredibly fortunate to be in a situation where this is could be the case. The first few months of a baby's life are incredibly tough for both the parents and the baby and I'm very happy that I was able to be with my girls throughout this time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was towards the end of this period that my partner and I decided to capitalise on our unique situation and put the remainder of her maternity leave to use by taking our little girl on a road-trip around Europe. The implications of this decision were to dominate and, to a large degree, consume the entirity of the next three months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Preparation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having made the decision to spend a significant amount of time touring Europe, with an 8 month old baby no less, it became apparent that there would be a whole lot of preparation required to make this happen. In March we decided to buy a Nissan Elgrand E51 Rider Autech (shown below) and April onwards was spent preparing it for our trip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://zdfcta-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3mRDVqstf6XsjN73biGoYnN5s-SzVcHx9pEdYl2S_wM803HpiosWK5Skxm-kskeHTMkahk_PIdejAp70x14KCaOwmZb6OvAvAig8uqI4bdBs2Pb_lAUsm-O_2lO8krW_18ReDVMLXqVkJWUGUSJ-d80bOIi8ciWIgyxDzL5fw4qF4?width=1796&amp;amp;height=1347&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:800; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Nissan Elgrand E51 Rider Autech"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This preparation was complex, with numerous requirements, constraints and learning curves across a variety of disciplines... but also a whole lot of fun. On our return I wrote a &lt;a href="http://elgrandoc.uk/forum/index.php?threads/touring-europe-in-an-elgrand-part-i-to-v.3311"&gt;very long post&lt;/a&gt; for the &lt;a href="http://elgrandoc.uk/forum/index.php"&gt;Elgrand Owners Club&lt;/a&gt; which detailed all the work I had done on the van. While the post took a significant amount of time to write, the forums were invaluable in providing the information I needed to do the work in the first place so I thought it was worth investing this time in case the post helped someone else in the same manner. To this day, the post is still one of the most viewed and commented on posts in the forum. It's well worth a read a read if you have time; if not, here are some pictures of the work instead:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://mkakza-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3mTMvumgbiWf4cuNId6rdQdXFkrZEMe891yFE3uaLIn1eWi8gsAGfCe6dwKUZjSfNqkfJHNpdzXf60mJIb2RH1HlQ1ku-6IEk5IPtKNoDHcJnVFi1_AIGA-TvxRXvplxSaxmqN385ks_cd0YZ2dxxdpU3ylY7UlYPW2uP9sp8Sr9A?width=660&amp;amp;height=371&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:800; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Cargo frame"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://dotw7g-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3mAeFtD-P9o5iDeydmal4JBd-518YT4V1-WPcdo33zt8xDn7vLENvSjzaMzFf5U52ZKreB49IRMJTdoMGXtxtSsLYUdF0mPvkYh-6ts_sihIt3aWMgd2hHlmkIzm-twj54_tTlpRJm2Xi3B58mGjSM_ZxF-aAQcQq842NpEBTlOVE?width=660&amp;amp;height=371&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:800; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Electrics box"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://adlakq-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3mw8fNegXFskURlkB2qFnfOJA7BsmrmPW7hx3Xyflhqwi52YIR8NEdSqz-acBvO6cTO2X5Atjj6U2uTFjGiLhTofbHGbteqx1B1MxGWouRBLO1WF1lTUCVMLbsUJmwFy2jPKb84N9xG_-1YuOmhqovFb59UuxMYxasZ0yyVDJgAtY?width=660&amp;amp;height=371&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:800; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Electrics fitted"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://plsn1w-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3mt5MSkFV_zVYge_IQZeDn02BvYd2ngjLePZYmte7YKsEIpa-e_n6BRgS0YFM5F1fge5qaJX5aAVLsyfhxVQo11B13NwfQ1hIQy47gdIcoBCjIWPPklSUKFIG59c2SXhfEaH0_xILPK35Awxm2RTs8bWvsLtkMtNTNs4V3t4qKXSw?width=660&amp;amp;height=371&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:800; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Cargo fitted"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://mhrszq-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3m5m7EX2zp-dMeKdwNa-8RMrBapeb5hhLCpRCj8bfI277ok0RZOs7Rv3GAdXQRiTsVfE6L-skEtFtkcgoi8Nf5qo1vxuw4aSoLPyMgXr5kHtDZQ-D5Sp1Lz2_-FoBNl8Zcj9bO531eW6_WFtu_Z0SE_QiDH2CWFp_-6hFL3fljt74?width=660&amp;amp;height=371&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:800; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Cable routed"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During this time I learned a lot about carpentry, electronics and engineering... but I almost didn't. Prior to undertaking the work, I had looked to find a conversion specialist who would do the work for me but most either only provided pattern-part conversions or were too busy to undertake a bespoke project. Well, "necessity being the mother of invention", I set to it and, in retrospect, am extremely glad I did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite barely having used an electric drill previously and never having dabbled in 240v electronics, I enjoyed every aspect of the work and am immensely proud of it. We didn't experience a single issue with my work while we were away and, even if we had, it was extremely comforting knowing that I could have resolved the issue in the field if I'd had to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should a similar challenge ever present itself again, I would certainly look at taking it on and, furthermore, would encourage others to do so also as you undoubtedly &lt;a href="https://hbr.org/2016/07/if-youre-not-outside-your-comfort-zone-you-wont-learn-anything"&gt;learn a lot more when working outside of your comfort zone&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Touring Europe&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the prep done - well, as much as was possible in the time available - we left home on May 20th and didn't return again until July 17; totaling just over 8 weeks on the road. In this time we traveled &lt;strong&gt;in excess of 8000 miles and visited 22 countries&lt;/strong&gt; seeing numerous friends en-route and making many more in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it was all the prep or perhaps we were just lucky but the trip went off without a hitch and everyone - including our little girl - had an amazing time. Both &lt;a href="https://bigspune.wordpress.com/"&gt;my partner&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/WotNoBlogPosts"&gt;I&lt;/a&gt; blogged about the trip - for ourselves as much for any potential reader - and, six months on, are still reflecting on what a fantastic adventure it was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without a shadow of a doubt, and even when considering the week's of preparation before leaving, this trip was time well spent. My partner and I learned a lot about each other ("hey, we &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; spend several weeks in a confined space together, 24/7") and our daughter and have accumulated memories that will last a lifetime. We have already talked about doing another similar trip in the future and have begun planning shorter breaks around the UK as a stop-gap until an opportunity for a new adventure comes along.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Study&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon my return, I came across a code for a free &lt;a href="https://borntolearn.mslearn.net/b/weblog/posts/sign-up-to-take-the-beta-exam-for-developing-mobile-apps-70-357-today"&gt;Microsoft beta exam about mobile application development&lt;/a&gt;. As I was interested in UWP app development and had already taken loads of these beta exams in previous years, I decided to sit the exam even though the code was only valid for a few weeks after signing up, which left very little time to study!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Experiential_learning"&gt;learn&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://psycnet.apa.org/journals/bdb/17/1/1.pdf&amp;amp;productCode=pa"&gt;best&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.virgin.com/richard-branson/you-learn-by-doing-and-by-falling-over"&gt;by&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://news.uchicago.edu/article/2015/04/29/learning-doing-helps-students-perform-better-science"&gt;doing&lt;/a&gt; my study focused on writing a UWP app that incorporated as many of the &lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/learning/exam-70-357.aspx"&gt;examined technical aspects&lt;/a&gt; as possible. While the methodologies I used for this app were relatively new (i.e. CQRS/ES) the learning curve for this exam really came from some of the unique aspects of UWP app development such as designing for multiple devices/screen sizes, using &lt;a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/ef/core/"&gt;new persistence technologies&lt;/a&gt; and leveraging the huge new API surface available to UWP apps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to an awful dashboard implementation which &lt;a href="https://borntolearn.mslearn.net/b/weblog/posts/more-tips-about-beta-exams-what-to-expect-when-you-39-re-expecting-your-beta-results-that-is"&gt;causes much confusion for students who sit beta exams&lt;/a&gt;, I am still unsure as to whether I passed this exam or not. My dashboard has not changed to say I have passed the exam but I have not received a summary sheet from Microsoft with my scores nor am I able to access them from my MCP dashboard. In short, the current beta exam process is extremely poor and much worse than it was five or six years ago when I took (and passed) around a dozen such beta exams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless, time spent on this study was a huge win. I learned a lot about a platform which is becoming increasingly prevalent in the Windows ecosystem. UWP apps are able to run on everything from Raspberry Pi to Hololens, and I have since deployed/released UWP apps for Raspberry Pi, Mobile (phone/table), PC and XBox. Indeed, after completing the exam, I continued to develop my UWP study app over the next few months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Holiday&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Across the year, I allocated around 40 days (including bank-holidays and weekends) as non-work days (aka holiday). This included snowboarding with friends, trips abroad, visiting relatives and a long festive break over Xmas. Although more than the holiday allowance at most full time jobs (depending on how it's allocated), I feel this represents a fairly decent split between work and play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;OneCog.Solutions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once life had returned to normal following our tour of Europe and taking the Microsoft beta exam, I decided to work on a few projects that were interesting to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, this was continuing my investigation of UWP, initially to &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/CqrsEsMvvmRxEfSqlUwpPcl"&gt;flesh out&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/store/p/littlelittle/9nblggh51b1b"&gt;release&lt;/a&gt; the UWP app I had written while studying for the UWP exam but then to also evaluate UWP as a &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/MonsterPi"&gt;platform for IoT devices&lt;/a&gt;. I then proceeded to broaden my area of investigation into &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/DockerAndKafka"&gt;non-Microsoft technologies&lt;/a&gt; and even into areas that, while still technical, were &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/3DPrintingWithTheCelRobox"&gt;not directly involved with software development&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During this time I endeavored to keep an up-to-date public profile. Through a &lt;a href="https://trello.com/b/KoTWuFUi/public-board"&gt;public Trello board&lt;/a&gt;, products I had released (&lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-gb/store/p/littlelittle/9nblggh51b1b"&gt;LittleLittle&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-gb/store/p/toddlerbox/9nblggh3zr4l"&gt;ToddlerBox&lt;/a&gt;), posts to &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/"&gt;my blog&lt;/a&gt; and contributions to both &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs"&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/users/628821/ibebbs"&gt;StackOverflow&lt;/a&gt; I tried to make sure as much of my time as possible was surfaced publicly. Indeed, having become extremely delivery-oriented since first drinking the agile (&lt;a href="https://medium.com/swlh/agile-is-the-new-waterfall-f7baef5d026d#.jpmks6gi4"&gt;lower-case 'a'&lt;/a&gt;) kool-aid several years ago, I feel the public-facing nature of these interactions substituted as a form of delivery; or, in Agile parlance, became my &lt;a href="https://www.agilealliance.org/glossary/definition-of-done/"&gt;"definition of done"&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While, in retrospect, I had hoped to have investigated many more technologies than I actually managed during this time, overall I would consider this time well spent. In addition to releasing two applications to the Windows Store and contributing to several public Github projects (more on this later) I managed to rack up over 1000 rep on StackOverflow in just a couple of months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, during this time, I didn't achieve my primary goal; namely finding a project that could potentially be grown into a marketable product and form the basis of a company. While there were no shortage of ideas and there still remain a couple of "coals in the fire", I don't think I've yet found the gap in the market I'm looking for. One slight positive note here is that I have, at the very least, determined a couple of markets I'm very keen on investigating further and in which I'd like to work in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this visualization I have employed step count (vertical bars), weight (yellow line with dotted yellow representing ideal weight) and fat-mass (red line with dotted red representing ideal fat-mass) as a (very rough) approximation of health. While, in theory, I should have had more leisure time available to exercise over the course of the year, in real terms I found that I did far less than expected. This was due to a number of factors:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My previous employer, being a company that revolves around football, had regular football matches/tournaments between company staff which were of a very high standard. I played in as many of these as possible and, once I left, I very much missed the exercise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My commute to work each day involved a (voluntary) walk from St Pancras station to Camden Lock - and back again - every day. This constituted 30 minutes/5000 steps of valuable exercise each day that was no longer necessary when I started working from home.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I ran a football team for my village that played in the local Bedfordshire league. Unfortunately, due to lack of players this team folded at the end of last season leaving me entirely bereft of football for the majority of the year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At punching-weight, I aim to be 11st and 15% fat-mass. This used to be a fairly common occurrence while playing football regularly but, as can be seen, I've not managed to get back into a similar condition this year. Fortunately, I &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; managed to avoid devolving into a complete bucket of lard thanks to several things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Parenthood - As any parent will tell you, being a parent is both exhausting and relentless. While previously I would undertake very little exercise in the evening, nowadays I expend a significant amount of energy each evening running around after my daughter. While not often recognised, this constitutes a fairly high level of activity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Preparation for Touring Europe - During this time I did &lt;strong&gt;a lot&lt;/strong&gt; of very physical work. From lugging construction materials and tools around to disassembling and reassembling the van, the average day was extremely active, especially when compared to sitting in an office chair for eight hours.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;European Tour - as can be seen from the step count, although a great deal of time was spent driving, our time away involved a lot of other activity. This activity (particularly loading and unloading the van each day!) provided a lot of exercise and helped keep me fit over the summer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Swimming - In a desperate attempt to remain in some sort of shape, I have recently started swimming semi-regularly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In retrospect, something that came as no surprise but for which I failed to anticipate the true impact, was the effect of not exercising on my state of mind and general happiness. Having always been an active and optimistic individual, I completely underestimated the tight correlation between these two characteristics. Mid-November saw me at my least active and, as I've come to realise, my least productive/focused (as evidenced by the sudden surge in StackOverflow rep!). Fortunately I try be somewhat self-reflective and, recognising that my diminished level of activity might be a possible cause for a perceived lack of progress, I decided to start swimming again as a means to address this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, while I'm still not exercise as much as I would like, I at least feel like my activity levels are sufficient to allow me to focus on projects and achieve my deliverables. Moving forward I very much hope to re-establish the village football team in time for next season or join another team such that I get at least a couple of games a month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Finances&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In counterpoint to the Health visualization described above, the Finances visualization shows a relative interpretation of my financial health across the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of the year, when considering a career-break, I tried to calculate a monthly "burn-rate" (i.e. total out-goings per month). Given I was not planning to change my lifestyle at all and my partner and I had already planned a number of holidays, I arrived at a rough estimate of £3k per month. This was affordable and, while it would put a dent in my savings, wouldn't leave me worrying about money at the end of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through-out the year there were a number of factors that further affected my finances:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Touring Europe in the van cost significantly more than I estimated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My daughter's nursery care was cheaper than expected since moving her from four days a week to three (instead having an additional 'daddy-day-care' day).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While I typically spend a significant amount on computer hardware, this year I required very little but for a relatively cheap new server.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, looking back across the year (and excluding large one-off payments like buying the van) it seems my burn-rate was closer to £2k, one third less than I had planned. This coupled with receiving returns on previous investments meant I actually ended the year significantly better off than I started it. While this definitely wouldn't be the case were I to continue the career-break for a second year, it is very reassuring to know that I could, should I decide to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Github contributions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Across the year - although predominantly in the last few months - I made 368 commits to Github. These were spread across a couple of dozen repositories but mostly focused on the (private) repository for &lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-gb/store/p/littlelittle/9nblggh51b1b"&gt;LittleLittle&lt;/a&gt; and my (statically generated &amp;amp; github-pages hosted) &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs/ibebbs.github.io"&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;. Additionally, I contributed to several open source repositories, most notably the &lt;a href="https://github.com/Microsoft/UWPCommunityToolkit"&gt;UWP Community Toolkit&lt;/a&gt; (1000 stars) and &lt;a href="https://github.com/beto-rodriguez/Live-Charts"&gt;Live-Charts&lt;/a&gt; (875 stars).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given 2016 was a leap-year, 368 commits in 366 days averages (just!) over one a day. Overall I'm quite pleased with this level of commitment and the quantity of work it represents, especially considering the amount of time this year spent not working. Additionally, for the last three months of this year, my partner and I have both elected to work four-day weeks as we felt it represented a better balance between parental and nursery care for our daughter. For me this meant Thursdays became "daddy-day-care" so that I could take my daughter swimming - something we both really enjoy - but which adversely affected my productivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving forward I intend to start publishing much more of my work to public repositories including regular updates to my &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs/Spikes"&gt;"Spikes"&lt;/a&gt; repository which contains investigative projects and examples for solutions to various StackOverflow questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;StackOverflow&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talking of StackOverflow questions, the next visualization shows StackOverflow Reputation accumulation across the year (light blue line) with gains shown day-by-day (dark blue boxes). While I predominantly consider it a distraction, I really enjoy answering questions on StackOverflow, probably due to the awesome &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gamification"&gt;gamification&lt;/a&gt; employed on the &lt;a href="http://stackexchange.com/"&gt;StackExchange&lt;/a&gt; sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there is a low level of fairly constant reputation gain, most of the gains came in short bursts. As discussed above, I attribute this losing focus on my main projects due to inactivity. Still, there are far worse forms of procrastination than helping people and I consider this a relatively good use of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am currently endeavoring to get the 'Fanatic' badge (visit StackOverflow for 100 days consecutively) but trying not to let it get in the way of other work. This usually means only answering questions when I can quickly point the asker in the right direction but I will occasionally field a more challenging question when it's &lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/tagged/system.reactive"&gt;something I'm particularly interested in&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Blog posts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the course of the year I have written and published 22 blog posts - totaling nearly 24,000 words - across a range of subjects including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3D PRINTING (1) APACHE KAFKA (1) APACHE ZOOKEEPER (1) ATTACHED PROPERTY (1) BDD (1) BEHAVIORAL (1) BLOG (3) CAREER BREAK (1) CLIENT-SIDE FRAMEWORK (2) CQRS (1) DART (1) DATAFLOW (1) DOCKER (1) DVD RIPPING (1) EF (1) ELASTIC STACK (4) ELASTICSEARCH (4) EVENT SOURCING (1) EVENTS (1) EVENTSOURCING (1) FUTURE (1) GITHUB (2) GROWTH (1) HYPERLINK (1) IOT (1) JAVASCRIPT (2) JS (1) KIBANA (4) LITTLELITTLE (1) LOGSTASH (4) MAPLIN (1) MONITORING (4) MVVM (1) NANOSERVER (1) NETWORKING (4) PARENTHOOD (1) PATTERNS (1) PRODUCTIVITY (1) RASPBERRYPI (1) REACTIVE (7) REST (1) ROBOX (1) RX (7) SQL (1) STATE MACHINES (1) SVG (1) SYSLOG (4) TESTING (1) TODDLERBOX (3) TOOLKIT (2) TPL (2) TRAVEL (1) TYPESCRIPT (1) UWP (7) VISUAL STUDIO (2) VISUAL STUDIO CODE (1) WEBRX (2) WINDOWS SERVER 2016 (1) WYAM (1) XAML (2) XBOX (3)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This content garners an average of around 110 unique visitors and 400 page views every month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of these posts - &lt;a href="https://blogs.msdn.microsoft.com/dotnet/2016/09/07/the-week-in-net-972016/"&gt;"The absolute easiest way to use SVG icons in UWP apps"&lt;/a&gt; was featured in &lt;a href="https://blogs.msdn.microsoft.com/dotnet/2016/09/07/the-week-in-net-972016/"&gt;"The week in .NET – 9/7/2016"&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in, I think I've added some valuable content to my blog this last year but feel like I should have tried harder to increase it's reach. While writing these blog posts inevitably takes a considerably amount of time, I intend to continue making as many new posts as possible, hopefully across an increased range of subjects and - by submitting to various aggregation blogs - with increased readership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Commitments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This timeline displays any days I had expected to work yet was unable to for a variety of reasons. Over the course of the year this accounted for 42 days, mostly the Thursdays that have become my "daddy-day-care" day and during which I take my daughter swimming. While these "commitments" would have been worked around had I been in full-time employment, the flexibility of working when I can as opposed to when I have to has undoubtedly led to a greater degree of motiviation and concentration when I am in front of the computer.&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>I contributed and all I got...</title>
			<link>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/IContributedAndAllIGot</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;A while back, I contributed my &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/UsingHyperlinkInMVVM"&gt;HyperlinkExtensions&lt;/a&gt; to the &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/UWPCommunityToolkitv1_1"&gt;UWP Community Toolkit&lt;/a&gt;. This morning postman brought me a very pleasant surprise:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<enclosure url="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/y3mNzf5Sylp6SOZbv6t2Q_atZh0reZJW7RYL9EgdZ4V4aZSaf_8Sqe8UPzCEaq7t3RKQn5GX1DvkSWdsolooyOHZj9Ma389uQChI7uhzICOmFTm8aZaRBYS4jS0K8g07vYNjEJofO_Io8VnpaqgTRsLJwSIEMEzg1P1TOt9dbXzm6s%253Fwidth=2465&amp;height=1039&amp;cropmode=none" length="0" type="image" />
			<guid>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/IContributedAndAllIGot</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 12 Nov 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;A while back, I contributed my &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/UsingHyperlinkInMVVM"&gt;HyperlinkExtensions&lt;/a&gt; to the &lt;a href="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/UWPCommunityToolkitv1_1"&gt;UWP Community Toolkit&lt;/a&gt;. This morning postman brought me a very pleasant surprise:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://orvy1q.dm2302.livefilestore.com/y3mcg6h9OGMl0tKB0ohOeyyBSVI-CwtcQF9XPWLXHBQI1inTRaPd9_k1jeoOpTIga1ZVnezoWRp34VnQuSmMduXhLro6OeJ4Unrgxe3PVOAh2kA3Pae1SN3wmxv3sxPDJlD1uTFxMKkKMk2lRjxKWZE1Ktqvs7k-mr6mCjq0UdKLh8?width=574&amp;amp;height=660&amp;amp;cropmode=none" alt="T-shirt front"&gt;&lt;img src="https://orvx1q.dm2302.livefilestore.com/y3mzcdee8-cKnRVTO-rrLFoC5rQMdorNPkUwiu49xlSHN6OeisdbwOFTzvPTLZzInaP0JBQLgOu9bkX8eZZZa4SuKd2ruJI80mI38NbMcTftpRMmE9zFx6DwWNGSctfhS6F2HRlKQ7Ve60D8Y6G94bbLVuFJ5hp4E9mYWQTG0QhxVk?width=594&amp;amp;height=660&amp;amp;cropmode=none" alt="T-shirt back"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How cool is that?! Not too many open source projects provide such swag!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the &lt;a href="https://github.com/Microsoft/UWPCommunityToolkit"&gt;UWP Community Toolkit&lt;/a&gt; maintainers, keep up the good work!&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Using Rx on the Web</title>
			<link>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/RxWeb</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;So, I have recently found myself with a need to dive into the depths of modern web-development and, as I am currently looking to write a highly interactive single-page web application, the first thing to decide on was a client side framework to use. You won't have to read too many of my blog posts to realise that I'm a big fan of &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/data/gg577609.aspx?f=255&amp;amp;MSPPError=-2147217396"&gt;Rx&lt;/a&gt;. I am also keen on the MVVM approach to separating concerns when writing user interfaces. Therefore, during my research of modern web UI frameworks, I was extremely interested when I came across &lt;a href="http://webrxjs.org/"&gt;WebRx&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<guid>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/RxWeb</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>
                                        


&lt;h2&gt;Finding a framework&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I have recently found myself with a need to dive into the depths of modern web-development and, as I am currently looking to write a highly interactive single-page web application, the first thing to decide on was a client side framework to use. You won't have to read too many of my blog posts to realise that I'm a big fan of &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/data/gg577609.aspx?f=255&amp;amp;MSPPError=-2147217396"&gt;Rx&lt;/a&gt;. I am also keen on the MVVM approach to separating concerns when writing user interfaces. Therefore, during my research of modern web UI frameworks, I was extremely interested when I came across &lt;a href="http://webrxjs.org/"&gt;WebRx&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Billed as "a browser-based MVVM-Framework that combines functional-reactive programming with declarative Data-Binding, Templating and Client-Side Routing" it struck a chord with my UI development style. In fact, it elevates &lt;a href="http://reactivex.io/documentation/observable.html"&gt;Observables&lt;/a&gt; to a first class concept in a manner eerily similar to the ObservableProperty/ObservableCommand classes I wrote for my &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs/Caliburn.Micro.Reactive.Extensions"&gt;Caliburn.Micro.Reactive.Extensions&lt;/a&gt; package.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, as a framework, WebRx seems to be struggling to achieve critical mass and therefore there was very limited information available when I decided to attempt to implement the &lt;a href="http://webrxjs.org/docs/getting-started.html"&gt;WebRx "Hello World"&lt;/a&gt; example using Visual Studio. As is almost par for the course when using a new framework, I fell at a frustratingly early hurdle and, given the lack of info (seriously, only one tagged post on &lt;a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/tagged/webrx"&gt;stackoverflow&lt;/a&gt;!), I had to work through the problem 'old-skool'... ya'know, by actually finding and solving the problem rather than just googling a solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I thought I'd put together a post outlining how to get started with this framework in Visual Studio in an attempt to start addressing the lack of info regarding this promising framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The name is Bart Simpson&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than the traditional 'Hello World' app, WebRx's 'Getting Started' guide displays a page stating 'The name is Bart Simpson'. This is done in order to demonstrates the MVVM separation of concerns through the use of a view bound to an underlying view model which provides the name 'Bart Simpson'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't intend to cover the entirety of the getting started guide here, merely the additional/different steps needed to get the project work from Visual Studio. As such, I suggest &lt;a href="http://webrxjs.org/docs/getting-started.html"&gt;opening the guide&lt;/a&gt; in a browser and leaving it open while working through the steps below as I will be referring to it extensively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First up, open Visual Studio. Pretty much any modern version is fine, I am using Visual Studio 2015 Professional. Start a new project and select 'ASP.NET Web Application'&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/RxWeb/NewAspWebApplication.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="New ASP.NET Web Application"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the following dialog, select an empty ASP.NET Template and click ok.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/RxWeb/EmptyAsp452Project.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Empty ASP.NET Template"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we have a web project, lets add a reference to WebRx. This can be done using either the Package Manager Console using the command &lt;code&gt;Install-Package WebRx&lt;/code&gt; or via the visual Nuget package manager as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/RxWeb/InstallWebRxPackage.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:66%; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Install WebRx Package"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless of how you add the reference to WebRx, you will be asked whether you wish to 'Search for TypeScript Typings' as shown below. Just click 'Yes'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/RxWeb/AddTypeScriptTypings.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:300px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Add TypeScript Typings"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will also be prompted to accept the license aggrement for a number of RxJs packages which WebRx depends upon; you should accept these too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One the reference is added, you should find that a Scripts directory has been added to your solution and which contains a number of 'ts' and 'js' files for both WebRx and RxJs. With this in place, we can then continue with the getting started guide by adding an 'index.html' file to the project and copy pasting the sample 'index.html' file from the WebRx &lt;a href="http://webrxjs.org/docs/getting-started.html"&gt;getting started guide&lt;/a&gt;. It should look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/RxWeb/CopyPasteIndexFromGettingStarted.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:400px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Copy Paste Index From Getting Started"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point the eagle-eyed amongst you will notice three things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our scripts are now in a 'bower_modules' directory&lt;br&gt;
As we used Nuget and not bower to install our WebRx dependencies, the script references should be changed to refer to the Scripts directory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our scripts directory does not contain a rx.all.js file.&lt;br&gt;
For some reason, WebRx depends on a version of RxJs that does not include an rx.all.js file. To resolve this, simply upgrade to the latest version of RxJs-All, as shown below:
&lt;img src="/Content/RxWeb/UpgradeRxJsAll.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Upgrade RxJs All"&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We don't have a 'js' folder containing an 'app.js' file.&lt;br&gt;
Because we've not got to that bit yet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now add a 'js' folder to the solution and add a 'app.js' to it. In this file copy the full 'app.js' sample from the WebRx  &lt;a href="http://webrxjs.org/docs/getting-started.html"&gt;getting started guide&lt;/a&gt; as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;wx.app.component('hello', {
  viewModel: function() {
    this.firstName = 'Bart';
    this.lastName = 'Simpson';
  },
  template: 'The name is &amp;lt;span data-bind="text: firstName + \' \' + lastName"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;'
});

wx.router.state({
  name: "$",
  views: { 'main': "hello" }
});

wx.router.reload();

wx.applyBindings();
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Save all, set 'index.html' as the start page and hit F5. If everything went as planned you should now see 'The name is Bart Simpson' displayed in your default browser:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/RxWeb/TheNameIsBartSimpson.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:400px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="The Name Is Bart Simpson"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that's it. While the getting started example doesn't seem very complex, it does show a separation of view and view model. I'm very much looking forward to digging into the details of this very promising framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs/BlogProjects/tree/master/WebRxWithAsp4"&gt;completed project&lt;/a&gt; for this post can be found in my &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs/BlogProjects"&gt;BlogProjects repository&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs"&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Wot No Blog Posts?</title>
			<link>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/WotNoBlogPosts</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;Yes, it's been over three months since my last blog post. "What have you been doing?" I hear you (the hypothetical reader) ask. Well... well I'll tell you.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<enclosure url="http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/y3mKlqOBjK9u-QOTjr8e6t2pOev7BN2vWZHyEDf2l27_HhaNgR_aVCXi2-GJh_KZMQV-naegShjBydS0blOk2kSndI2eTXnRhuqA5Ry0VYn8a0HdOEj_RvSUJ8uVdzsiDmcn4XRkyaAn7kScarmtvlf5nua4L9lkP_bWrKG5Ai7JdQ%253Fwidth=660&amp;height=371&amp;cropmode=none" length="0" type="image" />
			<guid>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/WotNoBlogPosts</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;Yes, it's been over three months since my last blog post. "What have you been doing?" I hear you (the hypothetical reader) ask. Well... well I'll tell you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having left my previous permanent position in January, I decided the time was right for a &lt;strong&gt;career break&lt;/strong&gt;. Having been &lt;a href="https://www.ted.com/talks/stefan_sagmeister_the_power_of_time_off?language=en"&gt;inspired to take a career break&lt;/a&gt; some six years ago, I knew how rejuvenating time off work can be and how reinvigorating it is when you finally have some time to pick and choose what it is you want to do and, more importantly, how. Indeed, last time I took a career break I ended up founding a company which - while not successful enough to prevent me having to return to employment - was massively educational, incredibly liberating and a whole lot of fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, my motivations for this career break are vastly different to those of six years ago. At that time I had just emerged from a somewhat turbulent relationship and was looking to - &lt;em&gt;sorry for the cliché&lt;/em&gt; - "re-find" myself; this time I am in a stable and happy relationship with my partner who last year gave birth to our little baby girl. And while, six years ago, I could - and was happy to - survive on very meagre savings, I am now lucky enough to be in a position where financial pressures are not an issue, at least in the short-term. Finally, while I had very little idea of what I was going to do during my last career break (which itself was extremely liberating in that you are suddenly open to being able to say "yes" to pretty much anything) this time I have a much more developed concept of how I want to use this opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While my motivations and desires for the coming months will be the subject of future blog posts, I have started putting together a &lt;a href="https://trello.com/b/KoTWuFUi/public-board"&gt;public Trello board&lt;/a&gt; of ideas/projects I want to undertake. It's just a start and by no means comprehensive but I thought some transparency around my ideas and goals (not to mention progress!) would be good for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now though I want to share what I've been doing - and why there have been no blog posts - for the last three months. You see, a primary motivation for taking time out of my career now was to spend time with my young family and maximise the use of my partner's remaining maternity leave. To this end, shortly after leaving my previous job, my partner and I decided to &lt;strong&gt;take our baby on a road trip around Europe&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The timing really couldn't have been better; my partner still had a few months of maternity leave remaining, the baby was still happy to have long naps in the back of the car whenever we drove anywhere and I was still keen on buying a day-van (it's been a &lt;em&gt;thing&lt;/em&gt; with me for a while now). So in February we started planning and looking for a motor that could comfortably cart the three of us around Europe and by mid March we'd bought an imported Nissan Elgrand E51 Ryder Autech.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://zdfcta.dm2302.livefilestore.com/y3mRDVqstf6XsjN73biGoYnN5s-SzVcHx9pEdYl2S_wM803HpiosWK5Skxm-kskeHTMkahk_PIdejAp70x14KCaOwmZb6OvAvAig8uqI4bdBs2Pb_lAUsm-O_2lO8krW_18ReDVMLXqVkJWUGUSJ-d80bOIi8ciWIgyxDzL5fw4qF4?width=1796&amp;amp;height=1347&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="My other baby"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the Elgrand is an MPV and not a campervan (a mostly pragmatic decision based on the fact we could use it on a daily basis after the trip and only a little bit due to "love at first drive") so there was a lot of work to do in order to prepare it for such a long journey. Therefore, between March and May, I researched, built and installed a bunch of modifications for the Elgrand to support us on our adventure. This included a custom built leisure battery / charging system enclosure, custom built frame to mount the electrical systems and luggage, routing of cabling around the Elgrand and several internal modifications for enhancing the navigation / ICE systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I documented these modifications on the &lt;a href="http://elgrandoc.uk/"&gt;Elgrand Owners Club website&lt;/a&gt;. This site proved invaluable in terms of information about working on the Elgrand and I wanted to give something back to the active and very helpful community there. Due to limitations in the website's forum, the details had to be split across five posts which - if you're interested - can be found here: &lt;a href="http://elgrandoc.uk/forum/index.php?threads/touring-europe-in-an-elgrand-part-i.3311/"&gt;Part I&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://elgrandoc.uk/forum/index.php?threads/touring-europe-in-an-elgrand-part-ii.3312/"&gt;Part II&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://elgrandoc.uk/forum/index.php?threads/touring-europe-in-an-elgrand-part-iii.3313/"&gt;Part III&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://elgrandoc.uk/forum/index.php?threads/touring-europe-in-an-elgrand-part-iv.3314/"&gt;Part IV&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://elgrandoc.uk/forum/index.php?threads/touring-europe-in-an-elgrand-part-v.3315/"&gt;Part V&lt;/a&gt;. After just a couple of days these posts have already garnered significant praise and numerous follow on questions so I feel pretty good about having spent the time writing these posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an aside, it occurred to me that this work could almost have been a case-study in Agile development. Not being a carpenter or mechanic and my work on cars to date having been pretty much limited to topping up the oil, I started this project from an absolute level of maximum ignorance. Fortunately as both a stake holder and engineer, it was easy to outline use-cases for the work which, while I didn't actually document them at the time, would have included some choice ones such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"As a driver I need a non-Japanese navigation system so I know where the smeg I'm supposed to be going!",&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"As a parent I need a fridge in the van so that we can keep food for the baby food fresh and - hopefully - the baby healthy" and,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"As a caffeine junkie I need a means of making coffee in the van so that I don't murder everyone the morning after we spend a night in it!"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These could then be naturally prioritized and, where possible, undertaken concurrently by my partner and I. If something went well, we could close it off and move onto the next thing; if it didn't we could reevaluate it's value / priority in light of what we had. This way we managed to hit our deadline (the ferry departure - which we put off "committing" to until as late as possible) with as much high value work done as possible. More importantly, at departure (aka deployment) time, we had a significantly lower level of ignorance such that, should anything go wrong while we were "live", we'd actually stand a chance of fixing it without having to - possibly literally - "roll back" to England.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, yes, some of this terminology is undoubtedly tenuous but, having had hours and hours to reflect on this work while driving around Europe, it was rewarding to see how much more effective an iterative approach to problem solving can be. Who knows if we'd ever have got away if we'd tried to plan &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; up front.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, we departed England in mid-May and returned mid-July and had a truly fantastic adventure. In &lt;strong&gt;58 days&lt;/strong&gt; we travelled &lt;strong&gt;7912 miles&lt;/strong&gt; and visited &lt;strong&gt;20 countries&lt;/strong&gt;. Along the way we met a number of old friends, made a lot of new friends and saw some amazing sites and scenery. We learned a lot, not only about the various cultures / histories around Europe but also about ourselves and our daughter. And we laughed a lot, mostly about the quirks of the various cultures we were experiencing but also - in retrospect at least - about some of the challenges we faced along the way; like having to park up in a field at a border crossing in order to buy the vignette that would allow us to drive the car in the country we were about to cross in to, and getting visited by both a swarm of monstrously huge locust type insects and a heavily armed and somewhat suspicious (the Elgrand has very dark privacy glass) border guard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We really did experience so much that I frequently find myself remembering something from the trip that a) I had somehow already forgotten and b) seems like both a lifetime &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; just a few days ago. Fortunately my partner kept a very detailed (and anonymised) blog of our journey in which she does an terrific job of capturing the fun and freedom we enjoyed while away. Should you be interested, you can read it &lt;a href="https://bigspune.wordpress.com/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now we're home. The baby has started nursery and my partner is returning to work. While I'm still having to consciously work out where I am when I wake up in the night (seriously, after two months of staying somewhere different every night, this seems to be a thing at the moment) and we're still trying to get the house back into some semblance of order, life is returning to our own special approximation of normality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For four days a week and for the foreseeable future, I will have pretty much all day to do... well, pretty much anything I want. It's an exciting time in the world of .NET given the recent release of .NET Core and Microsoft's assimilation of Xamarin. Graph and document data stores (aka NoSQL) continue to make inroads on the traditional strong holds of legacy relational databases. And there are some profound changes in the broader world of software development such as the continuing move towards containerized deployment and cloud infrastructures. I'm very much looking forward to investigating / leveraging all these in the months to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who knows where it will lead. I will certainly be keeping my ear to the ground should an exciting job/contract come around. Ideally I'd want something remote / freelance which I could do on my terms and, should the right opportunity drop in my lap, I'd certainly be open to it. That said, what I'd really like to do is resurrect my company and see where I can take it. I have a couple of ideas with potential but will hold off on developing them until I've refamiliarised myself with the current trends in software development because, even though it's only been a few months, it feels like I've been out of the game for years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, game on.&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content:encoded>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>RRJwdZWs_AhjvxhhOMdCS5PB-stLlTE?width=1024&amp;amp;height=575&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:320px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Lots of animals"&gt;
&lt;h6 style="text-align: center;" markdown="1"&gt;Lots of animals&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;img src="https://zphykg.dm2302.livefilestore.com/y3mVAxtKFjUEGk7Hdhzjl4UZ2INnFdBbw9K-tnYZ8DYoJ-VoKxpAN6w8Ng0DFTYdSxpHY6IvL5-VwJpLkQl6qWRmMQXSExLXopz5CFuSxIbyaMLrnL2Vy3yPZlISAAknXZdT4HwiZJ55zg2UtKwucBL88-xHh6rn5Mh97yzfRsCPjI?width=1024&amp;amp;height=574&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:320px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Lots of colours"&gt;
&lt;h6 style="text-align: center;" markdown="1"&gt;Lots of colours&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;img src="https://zphwkg.dm2302.livefilestore.com/y3m8XFQkqAgfzj1Yt9EqXW14XVybPwILZ0Hn_yGK2sbayqyeGZVqwSOGpT_xAJS3WwzYFeyQ4Gw66Fa-QyRpM71WpPUktEfgvgteIKAXfp9qCSW_my9s-7kb4Ys7Qz1JYRHv-k8fl1Y8xTTDpLhfY5xG2m56hT_ObFWrKxFhV-N-lw?width=1024&amp;amp;height=575&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:320px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Big..."&gt;
&lt;h6 style="text-align: center;" markdown="1"&gt;Big...&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;img src="https://zphvkg.dm2302.livefilestore.com/y3mN4YESAkR1YSr8YbSDJtqi2DGD20bBa_w5RR2cYyAm9aXKXxib1A65RnVBxraAGCEXRELh0QMYDSASbm7F8ADzvh7EizJXlz-odd9Vhvq0ccfd0yNyL4v1f2qex5ol96GP6qvxE35Fo1L-hdlu9cfo08lDWZielw6ffr-vZ92aYE?width=1024&amp;amp;height=575&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:320px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="...or small"&gt;
&lt;h6 style="text-align: center;" markdown="1"&gt;...or small&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;img src="https://zphukg.dm2302.livefilestore.com/y3mcH_fRNs467C1gL7rApW6mWiFYB-eCoUexIuW3CwX4Cb0seAy8IxNhjyiGFQx3jDrcB8ToLQJgekRDInIwMkMHQvVZ05vWCPrptx2vxkcu-KG40ldNAqOZu2ulyL7OPSGt7uuFNnZLOdtycCFVs3Tl5IWJltKR6uhEgxNW_j-4tI?width=1024&amp;amp;height=575&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:320px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="And monkeys!!!"&gt;
&lt;h6 style="text-align: center;" markdown="1"&gt;And monkeys!!!!&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real test came when I handed to the controller to my 14 month old baby girl. It took a few seconds for her to realise that what she did on the controller affected what was displayed on screen but then there was no stopping her. For three or four minutes (a record for her!!!) she sat still, mashing away on the controller and staring at the screen while I sat mesmerized by how quickly she picked it all up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd call that a win!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given this success, I made some final touches and submitted it to the store; specifically for XBox. To my amazement, it passed certification first time, within 24 hours of submission despite submitting it on a Sunday. And here it is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://1y8kkg.dm2302.livefilestore.com/y3mRbMDxeVB6f5ArIwJ6FjYCPRmwpPTp6LL2IGiIFOrFVgHzox_2HUl9lPNSq09KxXP5M3LD1E3nwgFi1a8HUCT-0dTH_VmemTLCQwHggxqy8u04C85i51eLPBj1op_n2ppnjK2zkhGDHcWWAyYvkncmNy4bqw58vumGP8BY4f9nZU?width=1024&amp;amp;height=576&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:800px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="ToddlerBox in the store"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Installing from the store and ready to entertain my little one whenever I need a break.&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Home Network Monitoring - Part III</title>
			<link>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/HomeNetworkMonitoring-PartIII</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;In the last post, I configured Logstash to extracted source and destination address information from the "Client Access Log" Syslog messages sent by my router and added a number of visualizations to my Kibana dashboard which allow me to explore which local devices are access which remote servers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<guid>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/HomeNetworkMonitoring-PartIII</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 12 Apr 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;In the last post, I configured Logstash to extracted source and destination address information from the "Client Access Log" Syslog messages sent by my router and added a number of visualizations to my Kibana dashboard which allow me to explore which local devices are access which remote servers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this is already very useful, it's almost impossible to remember which devices relate to which IP addresses on the local network, let alone the on the internet. As such, I really want the ability to translate the IP addresses (and, ideally, port numbers) into device, host or protocol names.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;translating remote ip addresses to host names&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a local device accesses a remote server it will, ordinarily, do so by resolving an IP address for a host name, for example 'google.com' resolves to the address '216.58.213.110'. On my network, my router acts as a DNS server, resolving names it knows and forwarding unresolved names to Googles DNS servers. A the results of the host name to IP address lookup are cached in the DNS server (e.g. my router) I can perform a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reverse_DNS_lookup"&gt;reverse DNS lookup&lt;/a&gt; at very little processing cost and without consuming any WAN bandwidth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual, Logstash comes with a filter that is able to perform this operation called, unsurprisingly, 'dns'. However, to provide a consistent set of fields to Kibana, it requires a couple of additional steps to ensure it functions consistently. Here is the amended &lt;code&gt;syslog.config&lt;/code&gt; with the reverse DNS lookup in place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;input {
  tcp {
    port =&amp;gt; 5000
    type =&amp;gt; syslog
  }
  udp {
    port =&amp;gt; 5000
    type =&amp;gt; syslog
  }
}

filter {
    grok {
        match =&amp;gt; [ "message", "&amp;lt;%{POSINT:syslog_pri}&amp;gt;%{SYSLOGTIMESTAMP:syslog_timestamp} Vigor\: Local User \(MAC=%{MAC:source_mac}\): %{IP:source_address}(?::%{POSINT:source_port})? -&amp;gt; %{IP:destination_address}(?::%{POSINT:destination_port})? \((?&amp;lt;protocol&amp;gt;TCP|UDP)\)" ]
        add_tag =&amp;gt; "access"
    }
    if "access" in [tags] {
        mutate {
            add_field =&amp;gt; {
              "destination_host" =&amp;gt; "%{[destination_address]}"
            }
        }
        dns {
            reverse =&amp;gt; [ "destination_host" ]
            action =&amp;gt; "replace"
            nameserver =&amp;gt; "192.168.1.1"
        }
    }
}

output {
  elasticsearch {
    hosts =&amp;gt; ["192.168.1.30:9200"]
    index =&amp;gt; "syslog-%{+YYYY.MM.dd}"
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that, when an 'access' message is successfully grokked, I add a tag to the tags array field of the message called "access". If another type of message has been received (i.e. a DNS lookup) then the grok pattern won't match and the 'access' tag will not be added to tags.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the &lt;code&gt;grok&lt;/code&gt; filter, I check to see if the tags field contains the 'access' tag and, if so, use the &lt;code&gt;mutate&lt;/code&gt; filter to copy the 'destination_address' field value into a 'destination_host' field. This is done as the &lt;code&gt;dns&lt;/code&gt; filter will replace the field value if a successful reverse DNS lookup is performed but will leave the original value (i.e. the IP address) if a reverse DNS could not be performed. This way we either get the host name or IP address in the 'destination_host' field and it's never empty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the changes to configuration in place, I restart Logstash. Then, in Kibana, I refresh the field list for the 'syslog-*' index, add 'destination_host' to the 'Syslog Messages' saved search, load 'Access By Destination Address' visualization and modify it to use 'destination_host' rather than the 'destination_address' field; and get the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-AccessByDestinationHostAnalysedVisualization.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Access By Destination Host Analysed Visualization"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While initially it looks promising, a quick look at the list of hosts being accessed shows something peculiar: the domain names have been split into their component parts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;analysis, mappings and templates&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason for the host names being split is because, by default, ElasticSearch performs 'analysis' on text strings. This analysis involves splitting the strings into discrete words which can be indexed more efficiently. Some strings however, for example domain names, should be treated as a single word and as such we need to prevent ElasticSearch from performing the analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How ElasticSearch treats various fields within a message can be controlled by modifying the index mapping. The current mapping for the 'syslog' index can be retrieved by a REST call to the address 'http://[ElasticSearchHost]:9200/syslog-2016.04.12/_mapping'. This returns:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;{
    "syslog-2016.04.12": {
        "mappings": {
            "syslog": {
                "properties": {
                    "@@timestamp": {
                        "type": "date",
                        "format": "strict_date_optional_time||epoch_millis"
                    },
                    "@@version": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "destination_address": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "destination_host": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "destination_port": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "host": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "message": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "protocol": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "source_address": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "source_mac": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "source_port": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "syslog_pri": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "syslog_timestamp": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "tags": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "type": {
                        "type": "string"
                    }
                }
            }
        }
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to prevent ElasticSearch from analysing the 'destination_host' field, we need to add an 'index' key with the value 'not_analyzed'. Even though things have been mostly working correctly so far, I can save quite a bit of storage and processing time by marking almost all of the string fields as 'not_analyzed'. This is shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;{
    "syslog-2016.04.12": {
        "mappings": {
            "syslog": {
                "properties": {
                    "@@timestamp": {
                        "type": "date",
                        "format": "strict_date_optional_time||epoch_millis"
                    },
                    "@@version": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "destination_address": {
                        "type": "string",
                        "index" : "not_analyzed"
                    },
                    "destination_host": {
                        "type": "string",
                        "index" : "not_analyzed"
                    },
                    "destination_port": {
                        "type": "integer"
                    },
                    "host": {
                        "type": "string",
                        "index" : "not_analyzed"
                    },
                    "message": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "protocol": {
                        "type": "string",
                        "index" : "not_analyzed"
                    },
                    "source_address": {
                        "type": "string",
                        "index" : "not_analyzed"
                    },
                    "source_mac": {
                        "type": "string",
                        "index" : "not_analyzed"
                    },
                    "source_port": {
                        "type": "integer"
                    },
                    "syslog_pri": {
                        "type": "integer"
                    },
                    "syslog_timestamp": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "tags": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "type": {
                        "type": "string"
                    }
                }
            }
        }
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, while I could write this mapping directly to the ElasticSearch index, as the index is date-based, I'd have to resend the mapping manually everyday. Instead, I am going to create a mapping template that will match an index name based on pattern and automatically apply the template. This is done by crafting a PUT call to the ElasticSearch '_template' endpoint with the specific template name. In short, the following mapping template is posted to &lt;code&gt;http://[ElasticSearch:9200]/_templates/syslog_template&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;{
        "template": "syslog-*",
        "mappings": {
            "syslog": {
                "properties": {
                    "@@timestamp": {
                        "type": "date",
                        "format": "strict_date_optional_time||epoch_millis"
                    },
                    "@@version": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "destination_address": {
                        "type": "string",
                        "index" : "not_analyzed"
                    },
                    "destination_host": {
                        "type": "string",
                        "index" : "not_analyzed"
                    },
                    "destination_port": {
                        "type": "integer"
                    },
                    "host": {
                        "type": "string",
                        "index" : "not_analyzed"
                    },
                    "message": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "protocol": {
                        "type": "string",
                        "index" : "not_analyzed"
                    },
                    "source_address": {
                        "type": "string",
                        "index" : "not_analyzed"
                    },
                    "source_mac": {
                        "type": "string",
                        "index" : "not_analyzed"
                    },
                    "source_port": {
                        "type": "integer"
                    },
                    "syslog_pri": {
                        "type": "integer"
                    },
                    "syslog_timestamp": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "tags": {
                        "type": "string"
                    },
                    "type": {
                        "type": "string"
                    }
                }
            }
        }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this in place I need to delete todays syslog index so that it is recreated, using the mapping above, when the first syslog message is received. Once this has been done, the visualization looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-AccessByDestinationHostNotAnalysedVisualization.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Access By Destination Host Not-Analysed Visualization"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nice!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I showed how to display host names for accessed servers rather than IP addresses. I also covered how to update ElasticSearch mapping such that field 'analysis' can be prevented and host names kept together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next post, I'll show how to translate local device IP addresses in to device names.&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>A Rip Storing Time</title>
			<link>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/ARipStoringTime</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;From a youth of misspent money, I have a moderately large DVD collection. Some 600 movies in half a dozen DVD racks take a disproportionately large space in my dining room. This year, my partner and I  decided to host Xmas dinner for the family, meaning a dining table that could host a dozen was in order and... well, you can see where this is heading. The DVDs had to go.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<guid>http://ian.bebbs.co.uk/posts/ARipStoringTime</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;From a youth of misspent money, I have a moderately large DVD collection. Some 600 movies in half a dozen DVD racks take a disproportionately large space in my dining room. This year, my partner and I  decided to host Xmas dinner for the family, meaning a dining table that could host a dozen was in order and... well, you can see where this is heading. The DVDs had to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, even though I barely watch them anymore, there are still a couple of amazing films in my collection that aren't available from the (far too changeable) online streaming services and, as such, I was reluctant to simply banish them all to the attic. Instead, I decided to undertake the monumental task of ripping them all to HDD before boxing them all up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Software&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are innumerable software solutions for ripping and transcoding DVD's... if you want to do one at a time. As you can probably appreciate, this wasn't a possibility for me or I'd still be ripping discs well into the New Year (not to mention through the Xmas dinner I'm actually doing this for). So a more, 'roll-your-own' solution was required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A bit of googling revealed &lt;a href="http://lifehacker.com/autorip-rips-dvds-and-blu-rays-as-soon-as-you-insert-th-477274988"&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; which described a mechanism for ripping discs as soon as you put them into the drive. While it was still targetting people who wanted to rip discs one at a time, it did point me towards the two pieces of software I did ultimately use:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.makemkv.com/"&gt;MakeMKV&lt;/a&gt; - for ripping the entire contents of the DVD and,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://handbrake.fr/"&gt;Handbrake&lt;/a&gt; - for transcoding source files into compressed H.264 format.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both these utilities come with CLI interfaces (details &lt;a href="http://www.makemkv.com/developers/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://handbrake.fr/docs/en/latest/cli/cli-options.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; respectively) allowing them to be automated. Furthermore, MakeMKV can run multiple instances allowing you to do your drive ripping (the long slow process) in parallel from multiple drives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Hardware&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd been intending to buy a new server for my home to be used as a Docker host because my current server is so old it simply doesn't support the required virtualization instructions. I'd had my eye on the &lt;a href="http://www.ebuyer.com/714837-dell-poweredge-t20-3708-xeon-e3-1225v3-3-2-ghz-4gb-ram-1tb-hdd-tower-t20-3708"&gt;Dell T20 Xeon E3&lt;/a&gt; but was waiting for it to drop back below the £200 (after cashback) mark. However, realising I could (temporarily) use it as a DVD ripping machine, I decided to bite the bullet and bought the T20 with an additional 4Gb of RAM for £324 (less 2% Quidco and £80 cashback).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It arrived a couple of days later and I must say I'm impressed. It's a lot of machine for the money, well built, has a copious number of USB sockets and is surprisingly fast. I installed Windows Server 2016 on this as it's the OS I intend to use for the Docker host and I thought it'd be a good practice run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To this I added the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 x 1Tb internal HDDs - configured as RAID-0 providing a fast destination for the drive rips.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4 x USB DVD-ROM drives - drives for ripping from - a couple I already had plus a &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/dp/B01B8U7JW2/ref=pe_385721_51767431_TE_dp_1"&gt;couple from Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 x 4Tb external USB HDD - destination for transcoded rips&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in, it's quite a monster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Putting it together&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike most of the out of the box software I'd found, I needed software that would do the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wait for a disc to be inserted in one of the drives&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Determine that the disc is actually a DVD video&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rip the disc to a destination folder based on the volume label of the DVD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Allow up to four concurrent rip operations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Queue ripped folders for transcoding allowing only a single transcoding operation to run at a time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the transcoded movie to the external drive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there may be software out there that does this, a couple of evening's googling didn't reveal it so, I decided a DIY job was in order. Besides, I thought the multiple producer/single consumer nature of the multiple rips/single transcoding would be a great fit for playing with &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/hh228603%28v=vs.110%29.aspx?f=255&amp;amp;MSPPError=-2147217396"&gt;Dataflow&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In relatively short order, I created &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs/DriveRipper"&gt;DriveRipper&lt;/a&gt;... and it's worked pretty well. I've been happily ripping four DVD's at a time, averaging around 12-15 DVD's an hour, with only a few small problems:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Because Dataflow enforces order of tasks throughout the pipeline (one if it's biggest strengths!) a slow rip or drive can hold up transcoding such that a queue builds up. Not a massive problem as the encoding process on the Xeon is actually pretty rapid (averaging 450fps) so it catches up with the relatively slow ripping process (about 20 minutes per disc) with ease.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some DVD's - particularly the old ones - are single sided or low quality or lack additional material or all of the above. This means that the contents of the disc is less than the 4.2Gb cut off I used for determining that a particular disc is likely to be a DVD. This can be sorted with a simple code change but I dediced to put these discs to one side for now and come back to them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some DVD's - again, particularly the olds ones - don't have a rational volume name; using terms like 'e19245' or, even worse, 'DVDVideo'. This has meant that, after the transcoding is complete, I need to rename the folders so that the contents don't get overwritten by a subsequent rip.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far I'm 150 DVD's through and just been told that the new dining room furniture is being delivered Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rip little machine, rip like wind!! Oh, wait...&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content:encoded>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;So, while ToddlerBox is riding high, I'd like to share some thoughts about another app I have in the store; &lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-gb/store/p/littlelittle/9nblggh51b1b"&gt;LittleLittle&lt;/a&gt;. This app has been the subject of most of my efforts over the last few months and is significantly more complex (and, frustratingly, less successful!) than ToddlerBox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LittleLittle was started shortly after my baby girl started weaning and became constipated - apparently a very common occurrence. When we visited a paediatrician about it, they asked that we keep a record of her bowel movements so that we could track the condition to see if it was getting better or worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"I wonder if there's an app for that", I thought. And, of course, there was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Opportunity and Methodology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, while there are plenty of other baby tracking apps out there, very few work across platform (I use Windows Mobile while my partner uses Android) and even fewer work as I feel they should.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the requirement to work across a variety of platforms, maximising code re-use was extremely desirable. As such, I decided that all of the core-logic for the app needed to be written in a PCL. Furthermore, particular care would be taken to observe a pure MVVM methodology so that ViewModels (an embodiment of the app's UX) could also be shared across platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, following some work in the CQRS/ES space at my previous employer, I wanted to write an app that used this methodology end-to-end. LittleLittle seemed a perfect opportunity to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Technology and Platform&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To partner the &lt;a href="http://martinfowler.com/bliki/CQRS.html"&gt;CQRS&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href="http://martinfowler.com/eaaDev/EventSourcing.html"&gt;ES&lt;/a&gt; methodology, I was keen to use &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/hh242985.aspx"&gt;Rx&lt;/a&gt; as the driving technology for implementation. As readers of my blog will know, I am very much of the opinion that "&lt;a href="http://slides.com/robwormald/everything-is-a-stream#/" title="Everything is a stream - Rob Wormald"&gt;everything&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/staltz/868e7e9bc2a7b8c1f754" title="The introduction to Reactive Programming you've been missing - andrestaltz"&gt;is&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://weareadaptive.com/blog/2014/05/05/everything-is-a-stream/" title="Reactive Trader 2: Everything is a Stream - Matt Barrett"&gt;a&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://colintheshots.com/blog/?p=85" title="Be Reactive - Colintheshots"&gt;stream&lt;/a&gt;" and event sourcing from "a stream of events" seemed a perfect fit for Rx.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that the Event Sourcing methodology - not to mention the nature of the app itself - required a persistence layer, I decided to use a recently new technology; &lt;a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/ef/core/"&gt;Entity Framework Core&lt;/a&gt;. I decided on EFCore simply because the tooling for the UWP platform was pretty good and I liked the 'code-first' approach to schema and migration generation. Coupled with this, I decided to use a &lt;a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/ef/core/providers/sqlite/"&gt;SQLite&lt;/a&gt; database as it was a proven data store for use with EFCore and across a variety of underlying platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, when I started LittleLittle I was studying for the &lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/learning/exam-70-357.aspx"&gt;Microsoft Beta Exam "Developing Mobile Apps"&lt;/a&gt;. As such, while I was keen for the app to be cross-platform, the initial platform I wanted to support was UWP. I was - and still am - amazed by how, if you craft your code and views carefully, an application can run on an amazing number for platforms including RaspberryPi, Phone, Tablet, PC, Xbox and Hololens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;And here's one I made earlier…&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After many weeks of work, innumerable iterations and much refactoring, I ended up with this:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;div class="horizontal_list"&gt;
    &lt;div class="horizontal_list_item"&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://zuimew-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3mcsjpC-olqYg0zbsOtSdJ1adHni1Apkeklf-2gzDpiB9ph_25HlwE5jeyMxex_1ryS-zVZxkMw0vtNsDCMrnzser84bs_zq9S75PZqddHWrRfMGfo3YbQhc-3ZwJGzjHMRuX_Ml0UQ_81MQnW4oOqva8Ap2jw2DIbULXOgc9ER7E?width=144&amp;amp;height=256&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:256px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Splashscreen"&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="horizontal_list_item"&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://zuilew-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3muwswRbqzTW9QY2Ms8LyW2AAl8vIDTt8DKl-lsB_0uqQvGZJDkqFRF1Jg151-YQzqyUxourRpTXaaHttLPaXkE3hXmavIZKYyI7isdayp_PLbXDVOKCX_u83bEdzFmsfPRAikqWEVteWkTaFnX1SH8YgEd4UABUffd5dVZ4QAkvM?width=144&amp;amp;height=256&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:256px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Available actions"&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="horizontal_list_item"&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://zuikew-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3mCHoxbDYsMkbkH-RQlFyxK5Y6zVhP_TU7JYj_MLCQrEfQsClKqlWoVqSsEt-ae7tYBvH89lvstPnIfhrA6MKPXNyjAp7O9EMy28Cof7nnc22DTFYs5FUECbQUEV_P8HxaVwWSFUyEN1MGAuWfY1x-36ZHviTEjqBOZM9m6pYm80Q?width=144&amp;amp;height=256&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:256px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="History"&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="horizontal_list_item"&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://zuiiew-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3mz7gADh3Y09Fb6QuQ2CY35gjWD2T9KEY_oWWbcijxNl2URePlVW0IjLhEBWeIoPOR1a-gAhRyoYNTdtefVfe8vd6d-Lnq5Cq_rcXEt4HZ5kt-jxOsCPLkJCaJtnfi5P-dTVNtJhMBYNbOtfiHXiPd9HsZODdjUwX-LphBvBAl_98?width=144&amp;amp;height=256&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:256px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Height and weight charts"&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="horizontal_list_item"&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://zeirew-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3miUjsB3mUDyGdRCPudsd1I42ad9-MAI5JRV15z821gQAc7H_mqIgEeEDr1YWCvZh5AZOT6BAuAVSdMwz-Qnr6mG53KzP8xbeo2hinEJyplWnHoVs4FG7sbga6HMgLP6qd_x_mxRx2uqEVTfVAgXSOLMmHnQSpMxbV7DzQzPT1LXY?width=144&amp;amp;height=256&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:256px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Sleep and excretion charts"&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="horizontal_list_item"&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://zeiqew-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3m2ZYqI7vBDCM_Ptv8Xvgo-UeDhvqtKIh5cxNy40KinoCzXem7V_-gIOsrkYvWyOtI6dod-HgNweHuue9DUB9r2yvgPNNXVvkPkIJKshYS4z-M1Qts9DPdqobqwnfHpIjewlWDj_Z6sFFVgbRlvsySton_n_nQrk4buXjebRss5JQ?width=144&amp;amp;height=256&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:256px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Sleep and excretion charts"&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I'm extremely happy with the result. CQRS/ES and Rx are a perfect match and the technology stack in general has been extremely productive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This morning I drew up a (retrospective) architecture to illustrate how much of the application is portable and how simple yet extensible it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://bdliqq-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3mdSQ-fHhXJWrDI-4wfqFoaso56RU_vCH51ognfdTMYlml6nEgxQHUJWgTgHg5fw4cAEwpaJM1GVookE2ok4HscXXmd-a6WAcU7Xd509Rdmb35JaS2-5Zzx5G_YiNpAoxLekZifHRzDQittyVv6rybVIp33YiqopFatHZVcND-lhY?width=1024&amp;amp;height=626&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:800; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Architecture diagram"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;"The proof is in the dog-fooding"&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apologies for the mixed metaphors but, suffice to say, while the technology choices may be deemed to be a success, the app can only be consider to be so if it is fit for purpose. As such, I have been using LittleLittle everyday for the past several weeks - across a number of iterations and versions - and I'm very, very pleased with the result. The UI is fast and efficient to use and the app has yet to crash or lose any data (either at runtime or between versions).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, a little while ago my other half took our baby to stay with her grandparents for a several days and agreed to keep LittleLittle up to date while she was away. She came back with a couple of small suggestions but overall very impressed by how fast and easy to use it was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it has yet to see a significant number of Windows Store acquisitions, Store Analytics shows there are a few people actively using the app and, so far, I have yet to see any crashes or failures. I intend to leverage the success of ToddlerBox to promote LittleLittle in the near future so, fingers crossed, it'll start getting some serious use and useful feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Moving forward&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I intend to put LittleLittle on hold for a little while in order to work on some other projects I've been meaning to look at, I very much intend to return to the project early in the new year. I have a backlog full of features I'd like to implement not to mention the need to write a version which runs on Android/iOS (which will probably be in Xamarin).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the mean time, I will be blogging about a few of the components in the architecture diagram above and sharing some of the approaches I have taken and successes (or problems!) I encountered.&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content:encoded>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>he USB power module suggested it was working fine too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next I relocated to another room where a network connection was available. I plugged it in, turned it on and saw the network connection LED's start blinking. After 15-20 seconds or so while the RaspberryPi booted, the relays tickets on and I was able to hit the REST endpoint from &lt;a href="https://www.getpostman.com/"&gt;Postman&lt;/a&gt;. I'd even managed to get the names of the sockets on the rest service to match the sockets the relays were controlling, although I admit this was more luck than judgement (I had completely expected to have to re-configure the software to match after the hardware was complete).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I plugged in a small table lamp and recorded this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src="https://onedrive.live.com/embed?cid=03DF8A28BD9D0BC9&amp;amp;resid=3DF8A28BD9D0BC9%21266322&amp;amp;authkey=AI5IzCXupiYl-CU" width="600px" height="340px" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" allowfullscreen=""&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boom! (Figuratively speaking of course... the MonsterPi didn't literally go boom... yet :0)&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content:encoded>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>as a DHCP server, it has a feature that allows it to always allocate the same IP address to a given MAC address. Therefore I know a given device will always have a specific IP address.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Logstash provides the &lt;code&gt;translate&lt;/code&gt; filter which allows you to map from one value to another via a dictionary lookup.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With my routers "Bind IP to MAC" function set up, I will author a new &lt;code&gt;yaml&lt;/code&gt; file that meets the specifications outlined in the &lt;code&gt;translate&lt;/code&gt; filter &lt;a href="https://www.elastic.co/guide/en/logstash/current/plugins-filters-translate.html#plugins-filters-translate-destination"&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt;. It looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;192.168.1.3: TPLink Range Extender
192.168.1.9: Ricoh Printer
192.168.1.10: Server A
192.168.1.21: PC A
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll name this file &lt;code&gt;IPLookup.yaml&lt;/code&gt; and save it besides the &lt;code&gt;syslog.config&lt;/code&gt; file. Next I need to add additional filters to &lt;code&gt;syslog.config&lt;/code&gt; which now looks as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;input {
  tcp {
    port =&amp;gt; 5000
    type =&amp;gt; syslog
  }
  udp {
    port =&amp;gt; 5000
    type =&amp;gt; syslog
  }
}

filter {
    grok {
        match =&amp;gt; [ "message", "&amp;lt;%{POSINT:syslog_pri}&amp;gt;%{SYSLOGTIMESTAMP:syslog_timestamp} Vigor\: Local User \(MAC=%{MAC:source_mac}\): %{IP:source_address}(?::%{POSINT:source_port})? -&amp;gt; %{IP:destination_address}(?::%{POSINT:destination_port})? \((?&amp;lt;protocol&amp;gt;TCP|UDP)\)" ]
        add_tag =&amp;gt; "access"
    }
    if "access" in [tags] {
        mutate {
            add_field =&amp;gt; {
              "source_host" =&amp;gt; "%{[source_address]}"
              "destination_host" =&amp;gt; "%{[destination_address]}"
            }
        }
        dns {
            reverse =&amp;gt; [ "destination_host" ]
            action =&amp;gt; "replace"
            nameserver =&amp;gt; "192.168.1.1"
        }
        translate {
            destination =&amp;gt; "source_host"
            dictionary_path =&amp;gt; "config\IPLookup.yaml"
            fallback =&amp;gt; "%{source_address}"
            field =&amp;gt; "source_address"      
            override =&amp;gt; true   
        }
    }
}

output {
  elasticsearch {
    hosts =&amp;gt; ["192.168.1.30:9200"]
    index =&amp;gt; "syslog-%{+YYYY.MM.dd}"
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note the &lt;code&gt;translate&lt;/code&gt; filter where I lookup the &lt;code&gt;source_address&lt;/code&gt; field in the &lt;code&gt;IPLookup.yaml&lt;/code&gt; file and put the result in the &lt;code&gt;source_host&lt;/code&gt; field. If not found, the &lt;code&gt;fallback&lt;/code&gt; value instructs the filter to output the &lt;code&gt;source_address&lt;/code&gt; into the &lt;code&gt;source_host&lt;/code&gt; field. The &lt;code&gt;override&lt;/code&gt; value is set to true as the &lt;code&gt;source_host&lt;/code&gt; field is added in the &lt;code&gt;mutate&lt;/code&gt; filter above as a fail-safe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the changes to configuration in place, I once again restart Logstash. Once a syslog message has been received, I get the mapping from ElasticSearch and update it to mark the &lt;code&gt;local_host&lt;/code&gt; field as &lt;code&gt;not_analyzed&lt;/code&gt;. Then, in Kibana, I refresh the field list for the 'syslog-*' index, add 'local_host' to the 'Syslog Messages' saved search, load 'Access By Local Address' visualization and modify it to use 'local_host' rather than the 'local_address' field and save it as 'Access By Local Host'. Finally, I replace this visualization on my dashboard and get the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-DashboardWithAccessByLocalHost.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Dashboard With Access By Local Host"&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;further mappings&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I've got the translation of local IP addresses to names working, I'm going to add a few more translations for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IP Address to Operating System&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IP Address to Wired/WiFi connection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TCP and UDP Port to Protocol (using a &lt;a href="http://www.iana.org/assignments/service-names-port-numbers/service-names-port-numbers.xhtml"&gt;CSV from IANA&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With these in place, the dashboard is starting to come together:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-DashboardWithLocalPortAndOsLookups.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Dashboard With Local Port And Os Lookups"&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I showed how to display local device names rather than IP addresses by using LogStash's &lt;code&gt;translate&lt;/code&gt; filter. I then used this filter to provide further information about local device and protocols.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next post, I'll show how to add some variation to the dashboard by mapping destination locations.&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content:encoded>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>n-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Visualise From Saved Search"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you select the 'Syslog Messages' save search you will immediately be taken to the Visualization screen with a vertical bar chart showing a single bar with the total count of all messages. Here we want to customise the visualisation to display the count of messages over time so we first need to define the X-axis as a 'Date Histogram' as shown below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-VisualiseDateHistogram.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Visualise Date Histogram"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With these settings in place, click the 'Apply Changes' button and you should immediately see a chart of the count of syslog messages over time. Note that Kibana has automatically selected an appropriate resolution of column grouping (messages 'per 30 seconds' in the example above) but that this can be changed later if required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, we want to add this chart to a new dashboard so we can have it available to us at a moments notice. To do this, we first save our visualization by clicking the 'Save Visuaization' button as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-VisualiseSaveSyslogMessagesOverTime.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Visualise Save Syslog Messages Over Time"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next we navigate to the 'Dashboard' tab and click the '+' button as prompted. Again, we selected the visualization we just saved as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-DashboardAddVisualization.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Dashboard Add Visualization"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the "Syslog Messages Over Time" visualization added, we make it a usable size by dragging the resize control (button right corner of the visualization) to extend the visualization across the width of the window as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-DashboardSizeVisualization.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Dashboard Size Visualization"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, to make it easier to see the messages the histogram refers to, we'll add a table of related Syslog messages onto our dashboard below the histogram. To do this, click the '+' button, selected 'Searches' and then our 'Syslog Messages' search. When the table is added to the dashboard, make it a similar size as the histogram as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-DashboardWithSearch.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Dashboard With Search"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once done, we need to save the dashboard so we can reload it any time we need it. Simply click the 'Save Dashboard' button as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-DashboardSaveSyslogMessages.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Dashboard Save Syslog Messages"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once saved you can bookmark the page and get back to your dashboard any time you like. Furthermore, once saved, you can monkey with the dashboard (explore the data by highlighting various areas of the chart, change time frames, set autorefresh etc) as much as you like knowing you can return to saved version any time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I have outlined how to use a Syslog capable router to send Syslog messages to Logstash and have Logstash store these messages in ElasticSearch for querying. Furthermore we then created a dashboard in which we can explore the number of Syslog messages we received over various timeframes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next post we'll increase the granularity of the messages we store so that we can start creating more interesting dashboard.&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content:encoded>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>ockerModule
Install-7zip

# Get components
Get-Java
Get-Zookeeper
Initialize-Zookeeper

# Build docker image
New-DockerImage

# Cleanup
Remove-DockerModule
Remove-7zip
Remove-TempPath
Remove-RootPath
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;FROM microsoft/nanoserver
MAINTAINER Ian Bebbington &amp;lt;docker@bebbs.co.uk&amp;gt;
LABEL Description="Zookeeper running on Microsoft Nanoserver" Version="0.1"
ADD Root /
ADD Start-Zookeeper.ps1 /
RUN setx /M JAVA_HOME C:\Apps\Jre
EXPOSE 2181
ENTRYPOINT [ "powershell.exe", "C:/Start-Zookeeper.ps1" ]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this one worked. This one started. This one stayed up!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Building the Kafka image&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the Zookeeper scripts as a pattern, it was ludicrously easy to script up another image for Kafka. Just a few changes to file names and configuration parameters and Kafka started almost first time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won't copy the script or dockerfile here as they're extremely similar to the Zookeeper versions. Instead, all scripts and files used above can be found in my &lt;a href="https://github.com/ibebbs/Docker"&gt;Docker repository on Github&lt;/a&gt; and the resultant images can be found on &lt;a href="https://hub.docker.com/r/ibebbs/"&gt;Docker hub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Moving forward&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img src="https://oltymw-dm2306.files.1drv.com/y3mIddKC619ngQYu9mwpyXXi9YgUp-MVwZ9_lR8JRla2AKvMm91LwnW2p0G3GkOZj5X_TXQUap_XULDAaiCWMC5Hx0ZvjKdAjeW7YWqacnwEAgCSZgmgBF1DCH83Zcywki6qKmOXbKkZO_SWmvQHpajyOQRHO1pJNB3ak2YpT6DmX8?width=660&amp;amp;height=371&amp;amp;cropmode=none" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="But I don't want any of that!"&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I don't want any of that!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving forward, I need to address a couple of short-comings in the Kafka script (specifically the hard-coded IP address for the Zookeeper container) and then look to use Docker Compose to automatically bring up Zookeeper and Kafka on demand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's been an interesting journey so far and I've not even begun to actually use the deployed services yet! Still, it is truly magical to run a docker container and see it boot an entire Windows server and service in just 10-20 seconds and a few hundred Mb.&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content:encoded>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>; file. Next I need to add additional filters to &lt;code&gt;syslog.config&lt;/code&gt; which now looks as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&lt;code&gt;input {
  tcp {
    port =&amp;gt; 5000
    type =&amp;gt; syslog
  }
  udp {
    port =&amp;gt; 5000
    type =&amp;gt; syslog
  }
}

filter {
    grok {
        match =&amp;gt; [ "message", "&amp;lt;%{POSINT:syslog_pri}&amp;gt;%{SYSLOGTIMESTAMP:syslog_timestamp} Vigor\: Local User \(MAC=%{MAC:source_mac}\): %{IP:source_address}(?::%{POSINT:source_port})? -&amp;gt; %{IP:destination_address}(?::%{POSINT:destination_port})? \((?&amp;lt;protocol&amp;gt;TCP|UDP)\)" ]
        add_tag =&amp;gt; "access"
    }
    if "access" in [tags] {
        mutate {
            add_field =&amp;gt; {
              "source_host" =&amp;gt; "%{[source_address]}"
              "destination_host" =&amp;gt; "%{[destination_address]}"
            }
        }
        dns {
            reverse =&amp;gt; [ "destination_host" ]
            action =&amp;gt; "replace"
            nameserver =&amp;gt; "192.168.1.1"
        }
        translate {
            destination =&amp;gt; "source_host"
            dictionary_path =&amp;gt; "config\IPLookup.yaml"
            fallback =&amp;gt; "%{source_address}"
            field =&amp;gt; "source_address"      
            override =&amp;gt; true   
        }
    }
}

output {
  elasticsearch {
    hosts =&amp;gt; ["192.168.1.30:9200"]
    index =&amp;gt; "syslog-%{+YYYY.MM.dd}"
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note the &lt;code&gt;translate&lt;/code&gt; filter where I lookup the &lt;code&gt;source_address&lt;/code&gt; field in the &lt;code&gt;IPLookup.yaml&lt;/code&gt; file and put the result in the &lt;code&gt;source_host&lt;/code&gt; field. If not found, the &lt;code&gt;fallback&lt;/code&gt; value instructs the filter to output the &lt;code&gt;source_address&lt;/code&gt; into the &lt;code&gt;source_host&lt;/code&gt; field. The &lt;code&gt;override&lt;/code&gt; value is set to true as the &lt;code&gt;source_host&lt;/code&gt; field is added in the &lt;code&gt;mutate&lt;/code&gt; filter above as a fail-safe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the changes to configuration in place, I once again restart Logstash. Once a syslog message has been received, I get the mapping from ElasticSearch and update it to mark the &lt;code&gt;local_host&lt;/code&gt; field as &lt;code&gt;not_analyzed&lt;/code&gt;. Then, in Kibana, I refresh the field list for the 'syslog-*' index, add 'local_host' to the 'Syslog Messages' saved search, load 'Access By Local Address' visualization and modify it to use 'local_host' rather than the 'local_address' field and save it as 'Access By Local Host'. Finally, I replace this visualization on my dashboard and get the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-DashboardWithAccessByLocalHost.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Dashboard With Access By Local Host"&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;further mappings&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I've got the translation of local IP addresses to names working, I'm going to add a few more translations for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IP Address to Operating System&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IP Address to Wired/WiFi connection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TCP and UDP Port to Protocol (using a &lt;a href="http://www.iana.org/assignments/service-names-port-numbers/service-names-port-numbers.xhtml"&gt;CSV from IANA&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With these in place, the dashboard is starting to come together:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/Content/HomeNetworkMonitoring/Kibana-DashboardWithLocalPortAndOsLookups.png" class="img-responsive" style="margin: auto; width:600px; margin-top: 6px; margin-bottom: 6px;" alt="Kibana Dashboard With Local Port And Os Lookups"&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I showed how to display local device names rather than IP addresses by using LogStash's &lt;code&gt;translate&lt;/code&gt; filter. I then used this filter to provide further information about local device and protocols.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next post, I'll show how to add some variation to the dashboard by mapping destination locations.&lt;/p&gt;



                                </content:encoded>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>